Hey, welcome to the most comprehensive
NADN course on how to go from zero,
somebody that's never used this platform
to hero, a master capable of building
automations for themselves and or
selling stuff like that to clients. I've
scaled my own automation agency at over
$72,000 a month using no code tools like
make and nen. So, the purpose of this
course and any follow-up courses that I
make are all about how to use these
tools for actual business purposes. how
to drive revenue, how to improve
savings, and more or less purposes that
you would actually be building systems
for in the real world, not just hobby
projects. I've made sure to add
timestamps for every section down in the
video. So, if you guys maybe already are
coming to this with a little bit of NAN
knowledge and just want some bits and
pieces, feel free to use that to move
around. And make sure you guys bookmark
this video so you can come back to it
later. Trust me, this is the most
comprehensive resource on NAN that you
will find on YouTube, at least as of the
time of this recording. I've checked.
You guys are going to want to make sure
that you run through this from start to
finish at some point in your NADN
career. So, you might as well have an
easy and simple way to get back to it.
So, let's cover what NAD is, how to get
set up on the platform, and how to build
our very first simple practical
workflow. Okay, now that you guys
understand what the purpose of this
course is, let's actually dive into the
very first module, which is going to be
all about how to get NADN set up for
yourself. how to essentially go from
somebody that's never used this
dashboard or this platform to somebody
that at least is a little bit familiar
with it. I'm going to be basically
putting on your NAN training wheels, if
that makes sense. And we're going to
start this video by signing up to N8N.
I'm actually going to walk you through
what that process looks like from start
to finish. I'm going to be using their
cloud hosted offering today. The reason
why is it's just a lot easier for total
beginners to get up and running versus
self-hosting. But I want you guys to
know that I'm going to be covering
self-hosting in depth over the course of
the next few weeks. After that, we're
going to do a live hands-on review of
NAND's builder. We're going to cover the
canvas, the workflow, nodes, and then
after that, I'm going to be creating
three simple but effective workflows to
actually have you guys get something on
the page, so to speak. You'll actually
have created three simple workflows
before the end of this video. So, if
that sounds good to you, without further
ado, this is Nadn's website, as we could
see. Secure AI native workflow
automation. Very sexy. I really like
their branding. You can see they worked
with some big freaking names. Adobee is
using NN now. Sendin Blue, Pearson, um,
Splunk. I've never heard of those guys,
but they sound funny. So top right hand
corner, I'm just going to click get
started. And the first thing it's going
to ask me for is my full name. So I'm
going to give it my full name. Then it's
going to ask me for my company email.
I'm going to give it a company email. So
I'm going to ask me for a password. I'm
going to write down example password.
And then for account name, I'm just
going to go nickyou
YouTube.app.ncloud. Keep up with our
constant improvements through our
newsletter. No, thank you. What I have
to do here is just because I'm crazy
with it, sometimes they think that I am
a robot. I need to select a bunch of
images that match a mountain. That kind
of looks like a mountain. That looks
like a mountain. I don't know about
that, but let's see what happens. It is
embarrassing how uh common it is for me
to get these things wrong. Anyway, they
have some little onboarding stuff using
Type Form. I'm not going to harp too
much on that because odds are this will
be different by the time you're looking
at it. And then I'm not going to invite
any team members to my workspace. I
really like their onboarding. They have
fantastic onboarding. They have a little
quick start guide over here on the right
hand side as the workspace starts up. As
you can see, it didn't cost me anything
to like launch said workspace. The cloud
plan gets you up and running like ASAP.
So, despite the fact that onboardings
typically do change and yours might look
a little bit different. As of the time
of this recording, it is pretty dang
sweet. Okay. And now I just received a
notification saying that my workspace is
online. I can click start automating and
we'll actually dive into NAND proper.
They use a little dark mode action which
I really like. So, very clean, very
sleek. As you can see, they
automatically sign you up to a trial.
Um, when you get started, you'll have 14
days in said trial with a,000 executions
total. I'll cover what all that stuff
means in a minute. No big deal. The
terminology of NAN is pretty simple and
straightforward, which I like. So, just
covering the dashboard really quickly,
top to bottom. I'll talk about the
things that are important, the things
that you don't really need to know, you
want to actually use in practice. U let
me just exit out of this little top bar
here. First things first, this button
over here allows you to create. So, you
can create either a workflow and you can
create it in a specific project. So, I
only have one project here called
personal, which is why that's all that
it's giving me. You can also create a
credential. So credentials are how you
connect to various software platforms
and apps in N8N. Uh and then you can
also create a new project. So add a
project button down here. You also have
an add a project button up here. No idea
why they do that, but they do. Um as I
mentioned, things are separated into
projects. We don't have any workflows
here, but when I add one, you'll see
it'll be listed. Then we sort of have
some of the same data here as well. We
have credentials. If I click on those
credentials, I can actually create a
credential up here, too. Nothing magic.
If you're on the cloud hosted offering,
you will have this sexy admin panel. the
purpose of which I have yet to fully
understand. Uh no, the purpose of this
is basically just to monitor your trial.
You can change NAN version versions if
you need to. You can change NAND
versions if you want. You can change the
versions if you need to select your time
zone and you know do some other
settings. In practice, you basically
never really have to change any of this
stuff. So don't sweat it too much. Aside
from that, one of the most powerful and
valuable parts of N8, this little
dashboard, it's actually down here in
the bottom lefthand corner under admin
panel. It's called templates. And this
sets NAN apart from a lot of the other
no code tools that you could choose.
They basically have some of the highest
quality workflow automation templates
publicly available and completely free
to use out there on the internet. This
is the simplest way to get up and
running if you guys don't know how to
build a flow. And after you're done
watching this video, I'd highly
recommend you guys to just bookmark this
and just spend a few minutes scrolling
through clicking on various systems that
you might want to create and just
understanding a little bit more about
how professionals or people that are a
little bit more wellversed within might
put things together. There's a lot of
opportunity here obviously to template
out, you know, big chunks of flows that
you'd otherwise build. And some of these
flows, to be honest, are literally good
enough where you could just click sales
and you could find like one or two of
these flows that like does exactly what
you need before you even had put any
work in. So for instance, if you wanted
to scrape business emails from Google
Maps or the use of any third-party APIs,
that was a system you were tasked to
build maybe as a service or for your own
business, you could literally click on
this button and you could import the
flow. It would take you like 5 seconds.
Not hard at all. And a lot of the time
the developers will document the hell
out of it too. They'll do video
tutorials and and all that stuff. So
yeah, that's probably the most valuable
part of this whole page to be honest,
aside from the workflow creator. But
let's actually dive into the juicy bits
which are obviously what you're here for
by creating a workflow. So that takes us
to the canvas. When you open up a new
workflow, you are sent to this page
where you could see a lot of cool stuff.
This is basically the workbench where
all of your N8N flows are going to be
created. I'm going to walk you through
this top to bottom. Let's start on the
top lefthand corner. This is where you
can name your workflows. So, I'm just
going to name a workflow and I'm going
to call it N8N course. You can see here
you can also add a tag. N uses tags to
organize their workflows in projects
which I'll show you in a moment. But
let's just create a new tag and let's
just call this YouTube. Let's say I'm
going to be creating a big YouTube
tutorial. So, I want to tag everything
here as YouTube if it's if it's part of
my um NAN course. And then over here on
the right hand side, you have the
ability to activate your workflow. You
do need a trigger for that which I'll
cover in a moment. You could share your
workflow here, which means you can add
users to your NAND account and then give
them access to a workflow. Pretty neat.
There's a workflow history or revision
history. If you make a mistake or
something during your NAN flow, you can
just click this button. It'll actually
restore the version of the workflow that
you want. So, they have very good
persistence. They actually show you it
um live, which a lot of other no code
tools don't. In the top rightand corner,
you have this sort of like click more
button where you have can duplicate a
workflow. So, if I click this button,
it'll actually just like, you know,
create another one. I can download a
workflow. When you download it, you'll
download it into JSON, which is pretty
neat. JavaScript object notation. This
allows you to then send it to anybody
else that you want and then they can
like import it. And speaking of import,
you can import either from a URL. So
there could be like a JSON file hosted
on a URL over here. And then you could
also host it just import it from the
file too. So that NAN course over here,
I could just click that button and then
it would import that workflow that I
just exported. There's also some
settings. Obviously, there are a bunch
of like um I don't want to call these
higher level, but they're sort of like
configuration options with execution
order where there are variety of
different ways that NN used to execute
workflows. There's some error handling
workflows, some some ways to time things
out after a certain amount of time.
We're not going to cover this because in
practice, I find you rarely need to use
this when you're actually building flows
for business purposes. That's ultimately
what the purpose of this whole tutorial
and course is about. But, you know, rest
assured, there's ample documentation on
all this stuff. The really cool part
about Niten is how well documented it
is. It's basically everything that you
could possibly need. I'm not going to
switch to the old canvas. It's just like
a slightly different way that it looks.
Moving forward, this is probably going
to be the predominant mechanism just
because it's so clean and sexy and
useful, which you'll see. Okay. Now,
speaking of the actual canvas itself,
um, if I just scroll around here, I'm
holding my two fingers on my little
touchpad. You could also do this with
like the mouse wheel if you want. I'm
moving around the canvas, right? You see
these little dots that are equidistant
from one another. Um, this sort of shows
you where you're at. in the bottom
lefthand corner. You'll notice that as I
do that, there's this little white box
sort of in the middle. What this is is
this is sort of like a mini map. I don't
know if you guys have ever played video
games like uh Starcraft or Warcraft or
League of Legends or Call of Duty or
whatever. It's basically the same sort
of thing. You have a mini map here. Um
and you can actually you can drag the
canvas like I'm doing right now or you
can actually just drag the mini map too
which is kind of neat. We can zoom way
out. We can zoom way in. This is sort of
nifty and honestly sometimes I just play
with this for like 10 or 15 minutes at a
time before I remember that I should
probably be building workflows that make
people money. Um so that mini map's kind
of cool. In the bottom lefthand corner
you have a couple of buttons and these
are like quick access easy buttons.
These are just useful when you're
building out workflows. Um if you just
press this button it'll basically just
like fit back to um like I don't know
like it'll it'll zoom out to an
appropriate amount that allows you to
see most of the nodes here. The cool
thing is N makes very heavy use of uh
hotkeys. So if you actually just instead
of clicking this button, just press one,
you'll just snap back. So
one, one, one. Pretty cool. It basically
just centers this box or centers the
average location of all of the boxes
when you have multiple nodes um in the
center of your screen. There's also some
plusing and minusing action going here.
You can press plus to zoom in or you can
press minus to zoom out. In practice, I
don't really use these when I'm building
just because I have my little touchpad
and mouse wheel and I can just do this
and when I do this, my head gets spinny
and it's very fun. You then have um
reset zoom here. So, you can go zero or
one. I don't really use that in practice
if I'm mad zoomed in. And then you have
a little way to report bugs. Um I never
report bugs, granted. Uh I don't know,
maybe we have some white knights here
that want to make the platform better or
something. Okay, the last thing I want
to cover is, and you can't really see it
cuz my giant ass head is in the way, but
in the bottom right hand corner of the
screen, you can click this button to ask
an AI assistant. Says, "Hey Nicholas, I
can answer most questions about building
workflows in NAN for you for specific
tasks. You'll see the ask assistant
button in the UI. How can I help?" And
the reason why I wanted to cover this is
because this has got to be one of the
most useful features in NAND. And this
really sets it apart from the vast
majority of other noode platforms,
especially like make. I think Zapier has
an AI assistant feature now as well.
Because this AI assistant is actually
useful. you can actually use it to sort
of co-build things. Um, it has access to
all of the NAND community forums. So any
post that was basically ever made that
describes a solution to a problem, it
will technically have access to and it
can pull it like with reasonable
accuracy. Uh, and then it's also
integrated into your builder. So it it
has access to the the actual build
itself. Although sometimes you have to
give it a little bit more context about
what it is that you're doing for it to
like really figure it out. Yeah, this AI
assistant, I want to say it's not
perfect, but it covers at least 30 or
40% of all the queries that I have for
NNN. So, my usual debugging workflow,
which you guys will see if we run into a
bug later. Hopefully, we do. Fingers
crossed. Uh, I'm going to use the AI
assistant as sort of a first
pass. Okay, great. So, that's that. Um,
I think we now know everything except
for obviously the big juicy elephant in
the room, which is adding a first step.
If I click on this middle button here,
you'll now see on the left hand side,
we've opened a bunch of options. Um, and
essentially what we're doing when we add
a first step is we're adding a trigger.
A first step of any flow in N8, and it's
always going to be a trigger. And so on
the right hand side we have a variety of
different triggers we could choose from.
We could trigger manually. This runs the
flow by clicking a button in Nadn. Good
for getting started quickly. It is very
good for getting started quickly. And
I'm going to show you our first uh
module or sorry our first workflow is
going to be built like that on app
event. So this runs a flow when
something happens in one of the many
apps that you can connect to non. So if
I click this you can see there's there's
action network active campaign acuity
adalo. Maybe you want to do a trigger
when a new thing gets added to an air
table or when a new project gets added
to a Santa or maybe you want to I don't
know when you receive a new um ClickUp
task or I don't know you get a new Gmail
or something or a new GitHub repo or
ghost post was made. Right? If I scroll
through here there there are a couple of
hundred triggers as of the time of this
recording and NN is always looking to
add more. So the cool thing is you can
very quickly if there's one of the
platforms that are listed here click
this button and then you could say oh
okay um let me see a better example oh
okay you know a new air table event just
occurred and what is the air table event
in particular um I don't know it's going
to be like a a new thing that was added
to a row with a with a specific field
for instance you could very quickly get
an anal integration up and running super
super quickly anyway I don't actually
want to use this so I'm just going to
drag on the canvas And then I'm going to
press delete. And it's going to delete
that module. Sorry, the uh note. If I
right click this, you can see I can also
do a variety of things to this. But the
one that I want in this case is a
delete. So that's what I'm going to do.
And I'll show you how to do all the the
other things that you saw a moment ago
just over the course of building. Okay.
So if I go back to this open nodes panel
in the top rightand corner, you'll see
that there's a hotkey. I can just click
the the tab button instead of doing this
manually. So that's what I'm going to
do. I'm just going to press tab. So
that's what I just did. And it just
opened this up automatically. Um, let's
continue down. Uh, aside from just on
app event, you can also do things on a
schedule. So, you can run a flow every
day, hour, or whatever custom interval
you want, which is pretty neat. So, if I
click this, you can see on the right
hand side here, left hand side here, we
can trigger the interval to be seconds.
I might run this thing every 30 seconds.
I can run this every minute. I could run
this every hour, days, weeks, months.
They also have like a programming um
sort of term here called cron which is
just a specific language setup where you
could write an expression that does
something I don't know every third
Sunday of years that are oddnumbered for
instance. I'm just going to now click
delete. So we can delete that out. Press
tab to open up this right hand side
panel and then continue. You can also do
what's called a web hook call. If you
guys are unfamiliar with web hook calls,
um I'm going to cover it later on in the
course, but essentially the really cool
thing about NN and a lot of other note
platforms, it'll it allows you to set up
your own URL just like this up here,
right? Nick nick
YouTube.app.n.cloud where when anybody
tries to access that URL or sends or
receives data from or to that URL, you
can basically get notified and you can
use that as the the beginning of a
trigger um for one of your flows. And
the benefit to this too is you know how
earlier I showed you guys that and had a
bunch of you know native integrations
about like 200 or something like that
where you could connect with Acuity, you
could do ClickUp, you could do Gmail,
all that stuff. Well, a lot of the time,
especially if it's a new platform, you
don't actually have that native
connection yet. And the benefit of
having web hooks is they allow you to
create that connection yourself. In
these tools, most of the time they'll
have a thing um called like a like a web
hook listener. You can set up your own
web hook listener to be this URL here.
And then NAN can just listen to data
being shuttled to and from those
platforms, which basically in effect
allows you to create an infinite number
of integrations, connect to tens of
thousands of different apps and
ultimately become the automation god
that we both know you want to be. Okay.
Anyway, so I'm going to click that out
and I'll cover all of the uh fields and
everything like that that you saw there
earlier. Next, we have a very nifty one
which we're going to be using today
called the on form submission. If I give
this a click and then I uh add just some
very base details here. Um let's just
say
name. Sorry, let's just do example
form. Enter example data. What's your
name? We'll go Peter. If I click test
this step now, we're actually going to
open up a little form that I could use
to fill data out. And when I submit it,
this basically begins my my flow, which
is really neat. So in practice like in
business flows you don't usually use
this too much but I'm going to show you
a simple um workflow that we can build
today that will there's also when called
by another workflow. This runs the flow
when called by the execute workflow node
from a different workflow. The reason
why this is so valuable is because a lot
of AI flows will use this. So if you
want to learn how to build AI agents and
stuff like that the when called by
another workflow um execute workflow
nodes the the that relationship there is
very common and you'll see me do it a
lot over the course of the rest of this
tutorial. And then there's also on chat
message which is very valuable. So, this
runs a flow when a user sends a chat
message um for use with AI notes. As we
could see, you could ask AI just using a
little chat interface, hey, can you
check my calendar to um I don't know,
double check that I'm not double booked
for for 11:00 a.m. It'll actually go
through um this little chat window
trigger and then use that to begin the
rest of this flow. There a few other
ways. Um you could do an email trigger,
IMAP, error trigger. This one's actually
really nifty and most other no code
tools don't have this. when there's an
error in another workflow, you could
trigger this workflow to do something
with. There are a couple of like
metadata things with NAD where you could
set it up so that when you create
another workflow somewhere in your NAD
project, you trigger a flow when one of
your flows starts or when one of your
workflows is activated, you could do
something. And there also a variety of
actions here. We'll cover actions in a
moment. And then there's this SSE
trigger, which nobody really ever uses
in practice from my understanding, so I
won't sweat it. All right. Awesome. So
that in essence are all of the triggers.
In order for us to check out and learn
some of the actions, we're obviously
going to have to go and create a flow,
right? In order for a flow to be a flow,
it needs a trigger, something that
starts it, and then an action, something
it does. Now that we finished the first
part, let's actually just go and start
building our three workflows so you guys
can see how to actually do things in
NADN. It's one thing to sort of look at
things from a canvas point of view. It's
another thing to actually get in the
weeds, get your hands dirty, start
manipulating fields. Okay, I just jumped
over to my other NAND account which
contains these examples. And I just
wanted to show you one more thing that I
I haven't mentioned yet. You see how
this is now this little like yellow note
um with manual trigger send an email to
someone. We'll start by learning how the
manual trigger works. We'll also cover
creating a brief connection and using
that to send a templated email. This is
just how I'm going to document um a lot
of our work moving forward because it's
very convenient. But what is this? This
is basically a piece of documentation
that you can just insert inside of your
own N8 flows anytime you want. It's very
simple. If you go to the top right hand
corner, just go down a bit. There's a
sticky note which you can do with the
hotkey um shift and then S. So I go
shift S. I just added a bunch of notes.
I'm just going to command Z or control-
Z just to go back. Um but yeah, you can
just add a note anytime you want. And
notes are really cool in because they
allow you just to document things. You
don't just have to use notes when you're
trying to teach or show somebody
something. In fact, my recommendation
I'm just pressing one to center this. My
recommendation is to use notes for
yourself to document workflows for
yourself. um just so that you know let's
say you build a system for a client or
for your own business and it works
really well so you don't have to check
in on it for 6 months but 6 months in
you want to change something well now
you're not like basically having to
relearn the whole workflow now you have
like a note which I don't know documents
or teaches you a little bit about it
okay so the very first system we're
going to build and basically the thing
that is going to allow us to get up and
running to learn how the rest of the uh
N8 end UX works is we're going to start
with a manual trigger and we're just
going to use that to send an email to
somebody why this is valuable is because
it's going to show us how to actually
trigger a workflow like ourselves. We're
also going to learn how to test a
workflow and I'm going to run you
through how the fields in NAN work as
well. We're going to create a brief
connection to my Gmail. Then we're going
to use that to send basically the hello
world example. If I click on this,
actually, let me update that. Basically,
our quote unquote hello
world. Okay, great. So, I'm going to
drag this add a first step over here and
let's actually do it. Let's click add a
first step and let's add this trigger
manually flow. Click that node. Boot
over to the left hand side. And now, as
you can see, we have a node in our
workflow that says when clicking test
workflow. Awesome. I'm now going to
click this plus button. What this
enables us to do is basically do um some
next step. So, what I'm going to do next
is I'm going to add an action. This is
our trigger. Remember, it has this
little um electricity lightning icon
next to it. What I'm going to do is I'm
going to do probably the simplest thing
that you can do in NAN, which is just
send an email. I think most of us are
probably using Gmail at this point. Um,
I'm going to go Gmail over here. And
then what I want is I just want to
scroll down. There's so many message
action. I got a label, delete a message,
get a message, do whatever the hell I
want. But the one that I want is I want
send a message. So I'm going to click
send a message. And two things will
happen. The very first thing that will
happen is we just connected an action to
our trigger node. And so our canvas is
now updated. It has two parts to it,
which I'll show you in a second. The
second thing is we are now faced with
this screen. This is basically, you
know, there's like the bird's eye view
canvas screen where you see all the
nodes laid out, but this is a screen
that pertains to that particular node.
And the really cool part about the way
that NAND lays it out is this Gmail node
which we just added um is sort of in the
middle. On the left hand side here, we
have the input to the node. On the right
hand side, we can see the output of the
node. So N8N and one of the reasons I
love it so much is because it tries to
show everything to you uh linearly and
logically. Everything that comes in to
this node that we added will be coming
in through the left hand side which I
think looks like the right hand side on
my thing. So let's go over here. It'll
come in through the left hand side. Then
it'll hit your node. Your node will do
something with that and then it will
finally proceed uh out the left hand
side as an output. So very simple
conceptually and I can't really
overstate how valuable this is just as
somebody that's worked with like you
know over a dozen no code tools at this
point to have it laid out like this um I
think shows that the team spent a lot of
time and energy figuring out what like
the most ideal UX was for development.
Okay, so I'm going to ignore all of this
input data stuff and and we'll we'll
cover all of that later um just over the
course of building. What we're going to
do now is we're going to click this
credential to connect with. So, I've
already actually already connected my
Gmail account, but I'm going to pretend
like I haven't just because I want you
guys to be able to follow along here.
So, what you have to do is you have to
click create new credential. Now, there
are variety of ways to connect one of
your accounts to NAN. There is OOTH or
OOTH 2 and then there are also service
accounts. I highly recommend anytime
that there's an OOTH or OOTH 2 option
available, you guys go with OOTH 2. To
keep to make a long story short, OOTH 2
just refers to you clicking a button
like sign in with
Google and then you being able to select
an email address with which you can sign
in. All you then have to do is actually
sign into the service. In my case, I'm
already signed into my own Gmail because
I'm using Chrome and it already does
that. Then you click continue and now
you can close this window. It even tells
you how lovely. And you'll see that it
now has connected the account. Basically
meaning that all of the stuff inside of
my Gmail is now accessible to N8 and I
can actually do things with it using
various triggers and actions. So we're
going to exit out of this now. And you
can see that we're now connected to
Gmail account 3. Okay. Next up we have a
couple of fields. We have resource. This
just allows us to choose what thing we
are manipulating. So message label draft
thread. For now we're just going to keep
it as message. You can poke around with
that after you're done this. Then the
operations. So, we can do a ton of
things here. We could add a label,
delete, get many, mark as red, mark as
unread, remove label, reply, send, and
send and wait for approval. Lots of
options here. We're just going to click
send for our hello world example. And
now we get to the juice of it, which is
the two field. So, in my case, I'm going
to be sending this to myself, which is
[Music]
nicholas@gmail.com. And I'm going to be
putting a subject. And you can see it's
already autofilled the hello world. So,
I'm actually just going to go hello
Nick. We have a bunch of email types
here. There's text and HTML. For
simplicity, I'm just going to go with
text, but I want you guys to know that
HTML is a programming language. It
allows you to make your email pretty. If
you guys have ever signed up to like a
newsletter service and there's all these
images and and and you know, banners and
stuff like that. That's because they're
using HTML. So, you can learn how to do
that yourself. And then you can send
stuff like that through NAN pretty
easily. But then finally, we have the
message. So, I'm just going to say,
"Hello,
Nick." And then I'm going to say, "It's
nice to meet you."
Okay, great. And now we've gotten to the
point where the vast majority of this is
done. We do have some extra options down
here. I want you to know that basically
all nodes that you can manipulate will
have some form of extra option. You
don't have to memorize every option for
every node cuz there are hundreds of
nodes. As I mentioned, generally
speaking, there just a couple that are
valuable. I know just off the top of my
head that the Gmail node has one that's
append attribution. Naden will try and
market themselves all the time. So, if
you do not turn this off, they will say
this email was sent by NAND. It's not a
big deal. Most no code platforms do
this, but just make sure you actually
turn it off if you want to use it for
some sort of business use case. Okay.
And then that's that. I'm just going to
head over to my personal email here.
Just open that up just so we could see.
So, you see I have a ton of, you know,
red emails here. And I'm just going to
click test step. I'm now going to send
the email. You can see the lefth hand
side filled out first. It said when
clicking test workflow and I'll cover
that later. But the most important thing
is this output field has now populated
and we see here it's kind of like a
table right with a column called ID
another one called thread ID and then
finally label ids. So any time that you
send or receive data in NAD from one
node to the next you're generally
speaking going to have some sort of
object that is created as a result. This
data object um can take a number of
forms and then it can visualize in a
number of forms. The way that they do by
default for this type of data is they do
table view which is where it's separated
kind of into columns like this. There's
also JSON. This is JavaScript object
notation. This is what a lot of
programmers and people that are a little
bit more familiar with no code are going
to prefer because this is just a
standard convention JavaScript object
notation. They know what the brackets
mean and I don't know instead of it
being kind of left to right like this
which can be squished, it's sort of top
to bottom instead. There's also schema.
This is generally what I find most
people in NAND prefer. They prefer
schema views. Schema views are great.
They're sort of like JSON. It's just
instead of them being written in code,
it's just sort of a little bit cuter and
it's wrapped in like little bubbles and
stuff. So this data is the same as this
data and this data is the same as this
data. They're all just different ways of
showcasing um what the information looks
like to you. I should also note that you
can search the output which is cool. And
a lot of people, even seasoned
professionals at NA, they like have
never clicked this little search button.
So give it a try. If you um are looking
for a particular filter, let's say the
object that is output is actually huge.
And you'll see you can output a ton of
different parameters here. But you want
to just see if the output contains
something, you can do so very quickly
just using this. Then only that field
will show and then you can very quickly
manipulate that as necessary. Um you can
also do a couple of other things like
pin uh data. Um and I'm going to cover
pinning data later. Uh and then kind of
like one of the neat things you can do
as well is you could actually manipulate
the output data. So you could pretend
like this just output a different ID.
Maybe instead of 1 1949, it was
1821 3 or something. The reason why this
is valuable is because it will then
allow you to propagate that data moving
forward. And as you can see, we just
changed that number. It used to be 1
1949. Now it's 1823. So when I search
1949, we don't have two fields coming
up. We only have one. Right? If I want
to search for the 181, I go 18. There we
go. Okay, great. So that's what happened
in N. But why do we give a crap about
that? We don't. What we care about is
did I receive the email? Okay. And now
you can see we just received that email.
If I give it a click, it now says,
"Hello, comma space Nick with an
exclamation point. Nick leftclick.ai."
That's the connection of the account
that I made. Then it says, "Hello, Nick.
It's nice to meet you." Fantastic.
Amazing. Great. Thank you, NAN, for this
lovely email. Just for shits and gigs.
I'm going to click this append n
attribution just retest it just so you
guys can see what that attribution is
like. Um, but as I mentioned, I I
wouldn't really recommend it for
business purposes. You just got this
little almost email signature that says
it was sent automatically with N8N.
Okay, so I'm just going to turn that
off. And then voila, we're basically
done our first example. This is the
hello world of N8N. Um, if you've made
it to this point, you now literally know
how to set up a simple trigger and a
simple action. You can do a lot of stuff
with what we've just covered. Honestly,
if you take the tips and sort of the the
workflow here, you can put together
probably like 10% of all workflows at
this point. Um, so as you can see, you
know, it's it's sort of simple to get up
and running as long as you have a couple
of core fundamentals down, as long as
you know what triggers and actions are.
And obviously, um, you know, if you did
not know what you were doing before you
tried to do it, it' be a little bit
tougher. So you have the benefit of my
foresight, but flows in a nutshell are
not really more complicated than this.
You always have some trigger, then you
have some thing that happens, and then
you have the action, which is this
Gmail. So let's kick this puppy up a
notch. Instead of just doing an email,
why don't we do an email, but let's also
add AI. And then instead of a manual
trigger where we just click the thing
and then it runs, why don't we use a
form to begin our workflow instead? So,
the very first thing I'm going to do is
I'm just going to delete this. I'm just
going to scroll down here to form fill a
autoresponder. And what we're going to
want to do as our trigger is instead of
it being trigger manually like we did
before, we're going to go on form
submission. just that I could show you
um how to do things a little bit more um
complicated like things that don't just
rely and yeah, it's going to try and add
it um all the way back up here. So, I
got to go drag it down uh just so we
could see how do you get data in from a
resource that like isn't this canvas.
Instead of us just clicking a button,
let's actually trigger it based off
something. So, the way we're going to do
it is on this on form submission node.
So, I give this a click. Um you'll see
that now there are way more fields and
this can actually be pretty
intimidating. it's the first time that
you've ever mucked around with something
like
this. So, don't worry. It's actually not
that scary. Um, we'll we'll make it
pretty simple. Up at the very top here,
we have some form URLs. There's a test
URL. There's a production URL. Right
now, it's not really worth knowing the
difference between the two. Just know
that this is the URL of your form. So,
you'll be able to send this to somebody.
You'll say, "Hey, um, I'm really excited
to get up and running with you. Thanks
so much for paying the invoice. All you
need to do is fill out the information
on this form and my team will get
started." You use this as an onboarding
form. Next you have an authentication
basic off none. Basically in our case um
this just refers to how you want to
secure the form. In our case we don't
want to secure the form at all. We just
want to use it. Now we need to create a
form title. So maybe let's just go
onboarding form. Form description. This
is an onboarding form for leftclick.
Fill out the fields and our team will
get back to you shortly. As you can tell
I'm building this example. I guess I'm
framing it as an onboarding situation
where you're working with somebody and
you just sign the deal. So, you send
them over a form and that form includes
a bunch of fields with information they
need to fill out in order to get started
with you. So, uh what is your name?
Maybe we'll do the the first one. So,
we'll go first name. Well, I mean, we
should probably already know their first
name if we're on boarding them, but for
the purpose of this example, let's roll
with it. We have a bunch of different
fields we could choose here. We could do
text, text area, password, number, file,
email, drop down list, and date. So,
there's a lot going on, but let's uh
roll with first name first.
The second one, let's do last
name. And let's just use my own
information as placeholders. So I'm
going to do Nick as the first
placeholder, Sarafh as the last
placeholder. Let's make both of these
fields
required. Let's go down here. Let's go
email address. Now, because it's an
email, we can actually choose a specific
type of form field. I'm going to choose
email. The reason why is because I want
to force people to put in a properly
formatted email. If I'm going to use
this flow to send an email to somebody,
obviously I'm going to need to make sure
that email is valid. What if somebody
typed in this instead? Or what if
somebody typed in that instead? Both of
my emails wouldn't go through. It' break
my flow. This sort of pre-planning is
necessary when you're putting together
more complex no um flows because you
just want to make sure that like the
data is correct from the get- go. The
data is uh bad, so will the rest of your
flow. So will be the rest of your flow.
Okay, great. And then let's just ask for
a phone
number. Then down over here, you could
see that we have access to a bunch of
different fields. There's number. You
might immediately think that a number is
the one to go to. Um, I don't think I'm
going to do number for this. Uh, I don't
think there's a a native phone number
formatting field. If we did number, then
that would mean that people wouldn't be
able to put a format in like this, for
instance. So, I kind of want people to
be able to. So, instead, I'm just going
to go text and then I'm just going to
add a placeholder.
And the idea is this is just going to
tell them sort of what sort of format to
use for their number. We're going to go
required. Okay, great. Down here we can
now choose when we want this form to
trigger. So when do we want it to
trigger? When the form is submitted. So
that's what we're going to use. And then
down here we have some other options. We
could choose like a pen nadn
attribution. I'm just going to turn that
off. There's uh button labels. We can
change the button label if you want.
Let's get started. I think the default
one just says a submit. Um, and then
there are a variety of other ones here
which I'm not going to cover right now
because I want to keep things simple and
straightforward. Awesome. So now that we
have this, I'm just going to click test
step. This is going to open up my form.
And you can see this honestly is not a
bad looking form. So I'm going to go
nick surive nick at
leftclick.ai. I'm just going to add
a sort of example e phone number and
then click let's get started. What
happens when I fill this in? If we just
make this a little bit smaller and we
couldn't see this in real time, but what
happened right there was the output
populated. And so now we actually have
all of these fields accessible to us in
our NAN flow. First name, last name,
email address, phone number, submitted
at form mode as well. Form mode uh
wasn't and submitted at. These weren't
fields that were put in by me when I
filled out the form. These are what are
called metadata. And the cool part about
metadata a lot of the time is you can
use this metadata to do something cool
with. So, you know, we could very easily
use this to update a Google sheet or
something with a list of submitted at
dates so that we could always be
tracking and sort of know like which
form entry made it in at which time. We
could distinguish between test and
production workflows. Production being a
live workflow. Anyhoo, so now that we
have access to all this data, what I
want to do just to make my life simpler
is in the top right hand corner, I'm
going to click this little pin button.
The value in pinning the data in n and
this is kind of different from most
other noode platforms. But the value in
pinning the data is by pinning the data
we will have access to that same data on
all nodes that are downstream from the
trigger node or the node that we are
pinning the data from. And this is
valuable because as you'll see naden's
whole testing flow involves you know in
in future nodes or subsequent nodes
testing using data from the previous
node. And if there is no data from the
previous node you are going to have to
fill out that data in order to proceed.
So this is just going to save us a
little step. Now that we've done the
form submission what I want to do is I
want to send this to AI. Okay. So, I'm
going to give this a click and I'm going
to go over here and I'm going to type in
um open
AI. From here, we have a variety of ways
that we can communicate with our AI. I'm
going to scroll down until I get one
called message a model. This is the
simplest um AI module that you AI node
that you guys could possibly use. This
is basically chat GPT. It's just instead
of us using chatgpt on their website,
you know, chat.opa.com, openai.com.
We're basically going to be
communicating with it now through API,
which is way cooler and enables way more
cool use cases. So, credential to
connect with. As you can see, I already
have connected to my own OpenAI account.
I'm going to go to create new credential
just to show you guys how this works.
Now, unfortunately, this is not yet have
an ooth 2 connection. So, that means
that as I mentioned previously, you're
not going to be able just to like give
that click uh give that button a click
and then have it open up the signin with
Google button. Instead, what you're
going to have to do is you're going to
have to add an API key. Your question is
probably Nick, how the hell do I do
this? The good thing is Naden is very
gratuitous and forthcoming with
documentation. So if I didn't know how
to do this, I would actually click on
this button, open docs, go down over
here, and then I would look through to
see how to do this connection. And just
because I want to show you guys, like I
know how to do this connection, but I
want to show you guys if I didn't know
how to do this connection, how I'd
approach it, I would literally follow
the documentation one by one by one. So
to generate your API key, log into your
OpenAI account or create an account. So
I already have an OpenAI account. I'm
just going to go platform.openai.com.
openai.com. That's how you get sort of
like their main API. From here, let's go
back to the docs. Open your API keys
page. As you can see, there's even a
button there. It says API keys. So, I'm
actually just going to go API- keys cuz
that's the link that they just gave me a
moment ago, right? So, I'm going to
paste that in. It's now going to take us
to our API key page. Next up, what does
it say? Create new secret key to create
an API key. optionally naming the key
and then copy your key and add as the
API key 999. That sounds simple. Create
new secret key. YouTube example.
Awesome. I'm then going to create my
secret key. We now have a secret key
that I can copy. So, I'm just going to
go back to NAN and then paste in my API
key. Boy, is that a long API key. Great.
Now, we're going to save. And as you
see, it says credential successfully
created. This credential is currently
private to you. Now, one thing that I
didn't cover when I created the
credential to the Gmail was you can
actually rename these credentials to
make your life a little bit easier. So,
I'm just going to call this
YouTube. So, now I know that this is
like my YouTube example. And obviously,
I could have much better naming
conventions for this stuff, but sue me.
Cool. Connection tested successfully.
We're good to go. We can now exit out of
this. And we have now connected to the
credential um with the API key, meaning
this is now hooked up just like we can
now uh previously we could get all of
our Gmail information in NAND. Now we
can get all of our open eye information
in
NAN. Okay, great. So the variety of
fields here like text, assistant, image,
audio, file, custom API call. I'm just
going to stick with text cuz I just want
to talk to the model over text.
Operation is going to be message a
model. We get to choose from a list.
Now, as of the time of this recording,
the most popular model, just scroll way
down here, is GPT40, this one. But I'll
be honest, these models change pretty
quick. So, by the time that you are
watching this, might be a couple days
after I recorded this, might be a couple
months, the model's probably going to be
different. I would just head on over to
like OpenAI's model page, and then I
just look to see what the current
recommended one is, the flagship model,
for instance. As you see, GBT40 is kind
of like in the driver's seat here. Um,
has a bunch of data on it. Um, and I
just sort of use that to, I guess, guide
me. If you're using another service,
then it won't be in exactly the same
place, but I think you guys get the
idea. Okay, great. Now, we can define
our prompt. You know, when you talk to
CHP and you say, "Hey, I want you to do
this thing." Well, there's actually a
term for what you just did. You prompted
ChatGBT and specifically you did so
using a user prompt. You're the user, so
that makes sense. Basically, the user
prompt is what you want chat GBT or want
in our case GPT40 to do for us. But
there's actually one other prompt that
you don't really get unless you're using
um a no code tool like this. It's called
the system prompt. This is used to set
the model's behavior or context for the
next user message. So, we're going to
click on system first. And the way that
the system prompt works for AI is the
system prompt tells the model how to
identify. So basically I'm saying, hey,
I want you to identify as uh you know
worldclass philosopher. I want you to
identify as a PhD in genomics. I want
you to identify as a helpful intelligent
writing assistant. And however you you
put your system prompt, the better it'll
be at that specific thing more
generally. There's a little bit of
nuance there. I'm not going to go into
it too much, but in my case, I'm just
going to say you're a helpful,
intelligent email writing assistant.
Then I'll go period. So, that's what the
system prompt is. Now, we're going to
click add message. And then the next
prompt I'm going to do is a user prompt.
If I click on roll, though, you'll see
there's also an assistant prompt. This
is pretty interesting. What what you can
do with the assistant prompt is you can
pretend that the assistant has actually
already said something in your chat
chain. If you want it to act a certain
way, you can give it examples of how you
want it to be. Anyway, in my case, I'm
going to do something very simple. user.
Then I'll say your task is to customize
an email using the following
data. Now I'm going to go enter. Enter.
This is going to make this stretch this
out a bit. I'm actually going to open
this up a bit more. Then I'm going to go
um and I'm going to drag this first name
in
here. You see when I drag the first name
in here, something changed. We just went
from fixed to expression. Why did we do
that? Well, basically fixed is almost
always just going to be static text.
Okay, we don't want static text. We
actually want to connect a variable from
a previous node into this OpenAI module
or OpenAI node call. So, I'm going to go
back to expression to show you guys how
this works. All I need to do if you want
to connect the input of the previous
node into the current node is just drag
it and then drop it where you want it.
So now this is
populating the um result is populating
with the actual data from the test. If
we zoom in way here you can actually see
it says result. Your task is to
customize an email using the following
data. Then in green it says Nick. Here
it says curly curly dollar sign JS with
a square bracket. Like this is really
intimidating and scary. Well this is
just the code representation and this is
the actual thing that just got
populated. Okay. So that's how we're
going to do this. I'm going to say first
name and then Nick. Then we're going to
go last name. And I'm just going to go
and drag last name in
here. I'm going to go email address. And
I think I might have just deleted that.
So, let me just do this one more time.
Last name. Beautiful. Email address.
Nick
leftclick.ai. Phone
number. Drag this puppy in here.
Cool. That looks pretty good to me. And
now what we're going to do is I'm going
to click I'm going to leave simplify
output um as
is. Then I'm just going to write my
email template. So I'm going to go down
here and go email
template. Hey
name. Let's go first
name. How are you? Thanks for submitting
your
request, your brief or onboarding form
moment ago. I see here your number is
number. Let's do phone number. I'm just
putting this text in so the AI sort of
like knows what to fill in. If you think
about it, it has the first name over
here. And if you think about it, I could
just fill all this stuff in
procedurally, but I'll show you why I'm
doing this in a second. We're actually
going to like level up the data to make
the customization a lot more valuable.
Um, I see here your phone number is
blank and your email is
email. Could you let me know if I'm
missing anything? Thanks, Nick. Okay,
great. So now what I'm going to do is
remember how we pinned the data before.
All we need to do in order to test the
step now is we just go up here top
rightand corner click test
step. If you test the step is actually
sending this whole thing to AI. And now
we have a bunch of content. It's a
subject welcome to our program back
slashn back slashn. If you guys are
unfamiliar with what the back slashns
mean here, back slashn just means um
like a new line. So this is trying to
write us a whole email and it's doing so
with new line characters instead of new
lines just cuz AI has no real way of
like creating a new line um without
this. So this is basically just a new
line character. Hey Nick, how are you?
Thanks for submitting your onboarding
form a moment ago. I see here your
number is 6045005000 and your email is
nick leftclick.ai. Could you let me know
if I'm missing anything? Thanks, Nick.
That's pretty neat. Why don't we just
pin this
output and why don't we hook this up now
to another email
module. And just to show you guys how
useful it is to know a little bit of
like NAND hotkeys, if you just go back
to the previous email module we had, if
I just hold command and C, same thing as
right clicking and pressing copy. See
the copy to clickboard event just came
down. And I actually just paste this.
And I'm basically now just pasting the
same module I had before. And then I'm
connecting it to the output of the
OpenAI module. And you'll see here this
is now accessible to us as input. The
content is which is pretty cool, right?
I'm noticing actually that this includes
a subject line. I don't like this. So
why don't I go back to AI then I'll just
tell it don't include the subject line.
Let's do that and let's test it. Let's
unpin. Let's test the data. And now that
it doesn't include the subject line,
let's pin it again. Let's go back to our
next module or our next node, I should
say. I keep on using the term module
because I'm big on make.com. It was kind
of the major noode platform I learned
and make.com always uses the term module
for everything that uses the term node
for. Anyway, now I'm going to drag this
content field to the
message and as you can see it's already
populating with the
email. I'm going to say re your
onboarding form and I'm going to test
this. The connection's already set up.
All of the rest of the parameters are
set up. everything set up cuz remember
all we did was we just copied that
module with all of the settings. In
practice, I find I copy modules a lot.
Okay, great. Now going back to my email,
you see we have read your onboarding
forms. I'm going give that a click. Now
it says, "Hey Nick, how are you? Thanks
for submitting your onboarding form a
moment ago. I see here your number is
6045000 and your email is Nick
leftclick.ai. Can you let me know if I'm
missing anything? Thanks Nick." The
reason why this is sort of like an AI
example right now is because we actually
just used AI to write this email for us.
But if you think about it, what we've
done so far is we haven't really done
anything that you can't just do by
dragging and dropping the first name
into the email module instead. So next
up, I want to do something that's a
little bit more creative. Uh I want to
do something that paraphrases what a
person said or summarizes it. And in
order for me to do that, I'm going to
have to go in and I'm going to have to
change the way that the form was a
second ago. But anyh who, we've now done
a different hello world example.
Basically, um the hello world example we
just did was instead of a manual trigger
of us just clicking test step, we now
have a form that triggers this. So, let
me make a couple of adjustments to the
flow and then we'll actually run through
the form one final time and we'll see
what it all looks like when we put
things
together. The adjustments I want to make
to this form. I don't just want to ask
for all this
information. I want to ask for let's say
design
preference. I'm going to add a drop-own
item and I'm going to say
sleek. I'm going to say um
minimalistic. I'll say luxurious.
Then over here I'll say
playful. Then I'm going to add another
form field. I'm going to say give us a
brief description of your brand. Or
maybe we'll just say um brand
description. My
brand or maybe we'll do company
description. Leftclick builds growth
systems for B2B agencies and creative
teams, enabling them to scale without
having to manually reach out to
prospects. Let's just do something like
that. We'll make that required. Now,
what's one more thing that I could do
that might be new?
H, we'll ask
it timeline. And we'll say how quickly.
Let's say uh 3 to 6 weeks. There you go.
We'll go required field. Awesome. Okay.
So now I'm going to click test this
step. It's going to overwrite the pin
data, but now it's going to open up our
form and it's going to have way more
information here, right? So I'm going to
go Nick Sarif.
Nickclick.ai. Um design preference. I
want my website to be minimalistic.
Company description. Leftclick. Build
sleek growth systems, high performing
growth
systems for B2B agencies and creative
teams. And the timeline is I want like
one to two weeks. Okay, let's get
started. Awesome. Fantastic. We now have
all the information that we need in the
output panel here. I'm going to pin this
data to make it accessible to subsequent
modules. Now, I'm just going to go in
here and edit the prompt a little bit.
And if you think about it, I don't just
want to edit it with, you know,
information about the the name and stuff
like that. That's not super relevant to
me. What I want to do
instead is your task is to is to
customize an email template using the
following data.
Let's just add in more information here.
Let's go design
preference. Drag this puppy in. I want
to give it more data to do the
customization
with. Down here, I'll go timeline. We'll
go one to two
weeks. Okay, great. And so, basically,
instead of what I had before, just hey,
first name, how are you? Thanks for
submitting your onboarding form a moment
ago. I loved reading about
thing about company. Let's
do let's go paraphrase company
description.
I see
here that you're looking for design
preference a design preference sort of
site and you're looking to have it
done. Would you mind confirming
your number for me one last time? I'm
going to say formatted phone
number. Right. Also, okay. And obviously
they know the email because we're
sending it. Cool. This looks pretty good
to
me. Don't include the subject line.
Let's actually give this thing a go now.
Let's click test step. We're going to
feed all this data in. Let's see what
our email looks like. Hey Nick, how are
you? Thanks for submitting your
onboarding form a moment ago. I loved
reading about how Leftclick built high
performing autonomous growth systems for
B2B agencies and creative teams. I see
here you're looking for a minimalistic
sort of site and you're looking to do it
within one to two weeks. Would you mind
confirming your number for me one last
time?
604700s 5,000. Right. You let me know if
I'm missing anything. Thanks, Nick. So,
basically what we've done is we've um
taken in some of the information here
and then we've paraphrased it. Um I
guess in this case we didn't actually
paraphrase. This looks like an exact one
for one. Hm.
Cool. Okay, great. Let's test this one
more time just to make sure that we got
a personalized but customized thing
that's
paraphrased. Cool. Looks pretty good.
Um, what I'm going to do now is I'm
going to go down to our Gmail
module. Take the data. I'm going to test
it. We've now sent an email and we
should have received another one called
read your onboarding form. This is the
customized email, which looks pretty
nice and sexy. And now that we figured
out how to do this testing one by one by
one, why don't we actually test the
whole thing from start to finish? Okay.
Yeah, let's actually just run this whole
thing. So, I'm going to go down to the
bottom. Instead of us testing the module
one by one, which is where we click on
it and then we click that test step,
we're actually going to test the whole
workflow. So, I'm going to click test
workflow. It's using the pin data. It's
running through. Uh, we don't actually
want to pin the data, so I'm going to
click unpin. Okay, now it's time to test
out this flow. I'm just going to go back
to the form submission and I'm just
going to do a little bit differently to
how we did before. I'm actually going to
copy this form URL myself. Click test
workflow and let me exit out of that.
And I'll show you guys you guys can
actually just test this from anywhere.
I'm just going to go back here, open up
an incognito tab, paste it in, and this
is the same input now, right? So, I
don't know, Nick um Sarah. Uh we'll go
Nick at leftclick.ai. We'll do phone
number. Then design preference
minimalistic company description.
NY's Donuts sells sleek, high-end
donuts with a creative
twirl. We're big on uh I don't know,
let's do our favorites are chocolate and
pink sprinkles or something. Uh timeline
would be like 3 weeks or so. Then I'm
going to click let's get started. It's
now going to submit it. And I just
wanted to show you guys this is like a
live form. Like you can use this
anywhere you want to test this thing.
You don't have to just like click that
button. Um what just happened in the
background was these just went green.
Green means that you know the flow has
now been completed and that node has
been done. So this node completed, this
middle node completed and that last node
completed. That means that if I go back
to uh my page here, I should be able to
see set input. So hey Nick, how are you?
Thanks for submitting your onboarding
for a m ago. I love reading about how
Nick's donuts sell sleek high and donuts
with creative twirl. I see here looking
for a minimalistic sort of site and
you're looking to do it in about 3 weeks
or so. Um you know the data here was
different. We're paraphrasing a fair
amount which is pretty cool. Would you
mind confirming your number for me one
last time? 604500 5,000. Right. Could
you let me know if I'm missing anything?
Thanks, Nick. Very cool. Very cool.
Okay, beautiful. So, that's the uh
second example here with form fill and
some AI autoresponder. Um, worth noting
here that our AI autoresponder sent
something immediately, but you can also
use a delay. Like, hypothetically, if
somebody fills that out, you don't
really want to send it immediately. So,
why don't we just cap this off with like
a quick like 120 second delay to connect
it. Um all we do is we drag we exit um
both of these connections. We drag this
over here and then we drag that over
there. And now basically we have um the
form submission coming through. AI then
figures out what it wants to say. We
wait for 120 seconds and then we send
the Gmail. Pretty neat, right? Cool. So
big fan of that flow. Um you can
manipulate and you know improve that
flow however you want. Obviously this
paraphrasing here was pretty lowle and
weak, but you could do a ton of things.
You could ask it to generate you a list
of questions to ask the onboard for
instance. You could um have it uh I
don't know suggest a bunch of actions
based off of some form fields. There's a
lot that you could do when you want to
make the flow production ready or live.
You'd have to click on production URL.
This would then be the form that you
would use instead of the test one. Then
you'd have to activate your flow by
clicking this button up here in the top
right hand corner. So now basically
anytime that uh the production form URL
is filled out, we will fill out this
flow and then send an email which is
kind of neat, right? Not saying that
this is what you guys should do right
now. I just wanted to show you guys what
that process looks like when you
actually activate a node or workflow.
Okay, great. Now let's use one final
example to show you guys and level this
up a little bit. Show you guys how you
might actually use this in a real
business flow. So maybe instead of an
onboarding form, which is kind of
contrived example here, we instead we
have a calendar booking. What we want to
do is when somebody books on my
calendar, um, I want to reply to them
and I want to make it seem like it's a
personalized reply. Then after that, I
want to add a new row to my CRM where
I'm storing all this data. Okay, so
there are going to be a couple of moving
pieces here. And I'm just going to keep
everything very light, but I'm also
going to walk you through the process
step by step. First of all, I have a
cal.com set up,
nick-leclick/inter, so you can book
internal calls with me if you're on my
team using this calendar. As you can
see, 1:30 p.m. is open. What I want to
happen is when I give this a click, I
basically want to use this to trigger a
flow that immediately sends them over an
email. And it's an email from Nick. It's
an email from me saying, "Hey, you know,
just saw you booked today. Really
looking forward to chatting with you."
It's going to substantially improve the
perceived personalization of this flow.
It's going to make people think that I'm
paying private and and one-on-one
attention to them, which is great. Then
what I want to do is I want to take that
data and I want to use it to fill in a
row inside of my CRM. Now, I'm using a
um thing called ClickUp here for my CRM.
Sorry, wrong account. Let's go over
here. I'm using um a CRM called ClickUp.
ClickUp is a fantastic high- quality CRM
that allows you to do a ton of stuff. Um
but for the purposes of this example,
I'm just going to be filling in this
creative agency template CRM that I set
up a while ago. Basically, what I want
to happen is when somebody fills out the
calendar booking, I want to add them
over here to this meeting booked um
status so that I have their first name,
their last name, their email address,
some other information about them,
company oneliner, maybe some meeting
URLs. Let's actually get to like
business uh flows now because I think
honestly after like an hour, you guys
know more than enough to do it. And let
me show you guys what an actual
automation build for something like
this, an NN would look like. Okay,
great. So the very first thing we have
to do is we just have to set up our
trigger here. So I'm going to go over to
three NAND examples and then I'm going
to just going to remove this on form
submission trigger. The reason why is if
you have um triggers in NAN um when I
test the workflow it's going to test the
the other trigger. So we just need one
trigger per flow. I'm going to go down
here and what I want to trigger is I
just want to see if there's a cal.com
node. Cal.com is the service that I'm
using. There variety of other ones.
There's kalanly as well which I know
many people use very popular but I'm
going to use cal.com and what I want is
my trigger is I want onbooking
created. So I have credentials that I
can add here. What I'm going to do is
I'll go create new credential and then
you can see here I need to find my API
key for um cal.com. There's also a bunch
of docs over here. In my case I know
where my docs are. You can see that I
have YouTube nn example expires in 24
days. I'm just going to delete that.
I'll make a new one. And then I am going
to have it expire just in case my silly
brain forgets to update this. I'll save.
I'm going to copy this. Then I'll go
back here to my API key. I'm just going
to paste that in. The host is
autofilled. It's always api.cal.com. So
don't worry about that. Then I'm going
to click save. This is now going to
successfully create my credentials. I'm
now going to go over here, type YouTube
just to make sure that I I name it right
and everything. I'll save and test it
one more time. Exit out. Okay. So there
variety of events that I could use here.
The one that I'm going to want is called
booking created. But I want you guys to
know you can also trigger a flow like
this when a booking is canceled. You do
it when a booking is rescheduled, when a
meeting is ended even. You also have
some options here um which are a little
bit more advanced. I'm not going to get
into all of them, but essentially these
light is set like metadata and other um
payloads and stuff like that for more
advanced flows where you need to tag
people and know where they're coming
from and that sort of stuff. Anyway, so
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
click test step. When I do, it's now
listening for one of my bookings. So I'm
going to go over here to internal.
Actually, you know what? I think I have
a better one. Um, instead of internal,
don't I have one that's
for discovery calls? That's probably a
little bit better. Yeah, let's do that.
So, I'm going to go in and I'm going to
book a meeting with myself. Uh, I'm
going to pretend my name is Peter
Jackson and my email address is just
going to be my longer email address
here. I'm going to fill my gross monthly
revenue at 20K. And then for additional
notes, I'll say, "I'm a big fan of your
YouTube channel and would love to know
more about how I can grow past 20K."
Then I'm going to click confirm. After I
click confirm, I'm just going to open up
this page again because I want to watch
the event come in live. And as we see,
the event did indeed come in live. We
have a ton of fields here. Trigger
event, created at, booker, URL, type,
title, on and on and on and on. Because
remember at the beginning of this when
we were just getting started with a
simple flow, I was like, sometimes calls
have a lot of fields. Well, this node
output a ton of fields. So, what I'm
going to do just to make sure I don't
lose this is I'm going to pin this. And
then what I want to do is I want to feed
this into a Gmail node. Now, if you guys
remember my previous hack was just going
to the Gmail node, selecting it, command
C, commandV. Very
clean. And then I'm going to go double
click on this. I have all the data
accessible to me. And now instead of
this, I'm just going to say re recent
meeting. And then I'm just going to say,
"Hey,
Peter, instead of just text, why don't I
do an HTML email?" Just to show you guys
what this might look like. If you want
to write an HTML email, a couple things
you have to know. A new lines are this
BR. So, if you want to add two new
lines, you'd go BR BR. Hey, Peter, just
saw you
booked a and let's go
type. Let's drag this over here.
blank
call looking forward to learning more
about you slashthe business. Then I'm
going to say
br Thanks
Brick. So when I send this email via
HTML it'll say hey Peter new line new
line. That'll be two lines. Just saw you
booked at just saw you booked a
discovery call. Looking forward to
learning more about you/the business.
Then it'll go new line, new line. Then
it'll go thanks. Then it'll go new line.
Then it'll go neck. In terms of um you
know what this looks like. Let's see if
we could customize this a little bit
more. Maybe I'll go reming with and then
I'll grab the first name
in. So I say remeating with Peter.
Perfect. Then in terms of the email
address I'm going to be sending this to.
I'm not going to hardcode this at
Nicholas. Now, I'm actually going to
enter in Peter's email, which is
apparently going to be this value key,
which will always say
Nicholas@gmail.com with this example.
Um, and then I think at this point,
we've now filled out everything, right?
Send HTML. Yep, looks good. Let's
actually test this. Send myself an
email. We've now received a um status of
send, which is cool. So, you can see
I've received two emails. The first was
um cal.com letting me know that I've
just booked a meeting with Peter. And
the second one is the email that I'm
supposed to be sending or receiving as
Peter. Hey Peter, new line, new line.
Just saw you booked a discovery call.
Looking forward to learning more about
you, the business. New line, new line.
Thanks, Nick. That's pretty sweet,
right? Looking forward to um that
conversation with Peter. But I got to be
honest, I think that we could probably
customize this a little bit better. I
don't really like the way that this is
um so small and minimal. So, why don't
we do a little bit of like um date
customization? You guys see on the lefth
hand side here, there's a start time and
an end time. Well, this isn't a very
particular format. datetime format that
we can convert into natural language
instead of this. How cool would it be if
we could say, "Hey, looking forward to
our chat on Tuesday, on Saturday, on
Wednesday. See you." And what I'm going
to do is I'm going to drag in the start
time
here. And what you'll find is because of
the format of NAD, which can be a little
bit intimidating if you're not familiar
with it, we have these curly brace curly
brace a dollar sign JSON dot and then
the variable name start time. Well, the
cool thing about Na is if I put a period
here, I can actually do a ton of stuff
with this. Like I can do a ton of stuff
with this. What I want to do is I want
to convert this to a date time, then I
want to format this. And the way I want
to format this is I want to format this
as a date. So I don't go DD no M A.
Sorry. There's a specific datetime uh
formatting key thing here. here. So, I'm
going to read the formatting guide
really quickly. And we're just going to
find out how to say like Monday or
Tuesday or
something. Okay. See this? So, it's
CCCCC looks like. So, that's the token
that I'm going to use. Or maybe it's E.
I don't know. Let's try both. We'll
format as
E. Awesome. See you Friday. Perfect. You
see how um that we're sort of just like
iteratively developing or iteratively
editing this. And it ends really cool
because it actually shows you the value
of the thing that you are currently
manipulating down here. So, the purpose
of this is not to have me for me to
expect you guys to know how to do any of
this date uh formatting for now. I just
wanted to show you what might be
possible with a little bit more complex
JavaScript and and JSON formatting down
the line. This dot notation is really
valuable. It just allows you to very
quickly manipulate things. In my case, I
called this variable JSON.start time. I
then converted it to something called a
datetime variable. Then I formatted it
as a day of the week and that's why it
says Friday. Okay, great. So, now that I
have that, let's test this flow.
Let's just double check that Friday was
formatted well. Everything looks good to
me. And now let's move on with that last
part of our example, which is going to
be taking this and using it to update uh
my CRM, which is ClickUp. So, I'm going
to give this a click. Give this a click
up. And then I'm going to go click up.
And what I'm going to do next is I'm
going to scroll all the way down to
tasks. What I want to do is I want to
create a task. Okay, great. Now, we have
the ability to choose our credentials.
So, if I go to create a new credential,
you can see that it asks me to connect
my ClickUp account. I'm going to click
connect. It'll now say, do you want to
connect with NSM? I'll say
yes, the window can now be closed.
Beautiful. And why don't we do that one
more time? We'll call this YouTube.
Click
save. Awesome. Now, I'm going to exit
out of this. And now we have access to
the credential for for YouTube for my
ClickUp account. So, basically, if you
guys remember, what I wanted to do a
moment ago was every time a new calendar
booking comes in, I want to add a row to
this meeting booked um space, and I want
to say Peter Smith, person's first name,
um status. We don't have the project
type or email or company name or
anything like that, unfortunately. So,
I'm just going to leave most of this
out. Why don't we just um hide these
columns for
now? But I just want to show a proof of
concept to show you guys that we can
indeed get the data in. And we're going
to put the meeting URL here as well,
which is going to be
nice. And future videos will show you
guys how to build CRM like this and
connect them um using
naden. Okay, awesome. So now let's head
back over to this ClickUp module or
ClickUp node rather. And uh we'll go
operation create. What I want to do is
create a task. The team name is NSM.
It'll go and it'll find the space name
which will be template creative agency.
It'll find the folder name which is CRM.
The list name will be sales. I know this
because if I look on the right hand
side, right, this is NSM. This is my
template creative agency. This is my CRM
folder. This is my sales list. So, I'm
just going down top to bottom and
connecting them. Then, we'll have a name
here, and I'll be able to add the name.
Now, what do I want to be the name? The
reason why I picked this as an example
is because we're going to be
manipulating data from a node that's not
just the previous node, but it's
actually a couple nodes back now. And as
you can see, this previous node here,
all we have access to are a bunch of
Gmail things, right? ID, thread ID,
labels, label, ID. If you want to go one
step back, what you have to do is you
have to open up this cal.com trigger. So
basically what we have here is at the
very bottom, this is the very first node
that we executed, this trigger, this is
the second node we executed. The most
recent node is always going to be on the
top and then every node that's connected
to the the previous node. Um it's just
going to go lower and lower and lower
and lower. So if we had a 20 node flow,
for instance, the very first node in our
flow would be down here, second would be
here, third would be here, working all
the way up until the final most recent
one or the previous one up at the top.
But anyway, now I want to access data
from my cal.com trigger. So that is two
nodes back. So it's not going to be um
you know immediately behind us, but we
could still open and access stuff as
needed. What I want to do now is the
name of this record, if you think about
it, I want it to be the first and the
last name of the person. I just wanted
to say Peter Jackson. So I'm going to go
here,
Peter. And you'll notice that the syntax
here changed pretty substantially, but
we'll cover that later. Then I'll go
space and then last
name. So now it says Peter space
Jackson. That's the name of the record.
Okay. So, why don't I why don't I do
this. Why don't I go back to my Gmail?
Let's just pin this. Not that it
matters. I'll go over here. What I want
to do is I just want to test this step
and show you guys what it looks like
when something gets updated in my
ClickUp. You guys see that Peter Jackson
was just added. How cool is that? We've
now just bridged the gap and we've added
Peter Jackson who was previously inside
of NAN whose data we got from click uh
from cal.com which is a totally
different software platform and we put
it in ClickUp. But you'll notice that,
you know, a couple things are off here.
I want to make the status meeting
booked. And then I also want to fill out
this meeting URL. So in order to do this
with ClickUp, what we have to do is we
have to go and we have to fill out
what's called a custom fields JSON. This
is kind of annoying to do in ClickUp to
be honest. Um I wish that there was an
easier way to do this. Uh maybe at some
point in time ClickUp will provide an
easier way to do this through their API,
but hey, what are you going to do? So in
order to do this what we have to do is
we have to go down here to where it says
add additional fields rather what we
have to do is we have to number one set
the status name manually. We have to set
it to meeting booked. Okay. And we also
have to go over here and add custom
fields JSON. Now this is pretty annoying
to do unfortunately in um N8N. We have
to basically figure out what the ID of
the field is before we fill it out. And
then in order to do so, we also have to
do um use this format with like a square
bracket then a space left curly bracket
quote ID quote um colon space quote
quote then inside of there we'll have
the ID. Then we have the value which is
the thing we're going to fill it in
with. Sometimes you have to do this. I
know the ID already. Um so I'm just
going to paste that in. And then I'm
just going to paste in the rest of this
as well for
simplicity. In this case um I'm just
going to go expression go back here. ID
will be this and then the value is going
to be the meeting URL. So what I'm going
to do is I'll go here. I'll go
meeting. Maybe I'll go URL. There you
go. Video call URL. I'm going to drag
this over here between these two quotes.
Okay. So now if you look at the JSON
that I'm sending, it is now uh in the
right format uh that uh ClickUp is
requesting. Don't worry too much about
the code aspect of this. I put this in
here just to show you guys that like
there is some knowledge that will make
it a lot easier for you to do specific
things that you want to do. For
instance, if you didn't know this, it
would probably take three or four more
nodes in order to get there. And that's
okay. Um, everybody needs to start
somewhere. But in future videos as we
cover all of the different functions and
dot notations of NAD. Um, stuff like
this sort of just adds fuel to the fire.
Okay, great. So now I'm going to test
this one more time. We'll go back to
ClickUp and we'll see what we just did.
We just added Peter Jackson except now
we've done so with the status that says
meeting book and also with the meeting
URL of the call that we're going to
have. So in this way we've created a
very simple flow that when a new cal.com
meeting comes in we reply with an email
and then immediately after we log it in
our CRM. This sort of thing is crazy
effective for small to mediumsiz
businesses. A lot of them lack
organization and they don't really
understand how to do these sorts of
connections. Well, the great news is you
can now, you know, assuming that you've
you've built this out on your own and I
highly recommend you build alongside me.
You can now do this sort of thing, not
just for ClickUp, but for any CRM out
there and not just for Cal.com, but for
any calendar booking platform out there.
At the end of the day, they all they're
all more or less the same. Awesome. So,
the last thing I'm going to do, I don't
call any build done until I test it end
to end. So, I'm just going to remove the
pin data here.
Sorry. You got to go up here, top right
hand corner, click unpin, then click
unpin. Then what I'm going to do is I'm
going to test this workflow from start
to finish on actual data. If we double
click on this, it's listening for a test
event, so we have to actually go fill it
out. I'm going to go back to my
calendar. Now, I'm just going to make a
second test booking at like a slightly
different time. Let's open up a tab here
and let's do it. Uh, we'll go 2 p.m.
This will still be Nick. Well, let's say
Sally. Oh, what did I say? Lozen or
something. I forgot what her last name
was. I think a lozenge is a thing you
put in your mouth when you are
sick. Okay. Anyway,
confirm. This is now going to go through
the booking flow. Go on my calendar.
Apparently, book me. Uh, and then if we
go over here, you'll see we just pulled
in the data with Sally Lozenge.
Apparently, if we go to our ClickUp,
we'll go down here and we'll see Sally
Lozen was now put in, which is pretty
neat. So, yeah. Um, that's that for our
third NN example. And just to cover
things, what we did here was we didn't
just learn how to use an app trigger
like cal.com do an API connection using
an API key. You know, send emails and
stuff, but we also learned how to
reference data a couple of nodes back,
which is very important. And ultimately,
you know, most of the complex flows that
have value will be you referencing data
from all over the freaking place, not
just the previous node. So, I hope that
this makes sense. What I'm going to do
is I'm going to save this and I'll make
this accessible for you guys to play
around with. Note that we do not have
the trigger nodes in this. That's okay.
You guys now, if you've made it to this
point of the video, know everything you
need to know to get to the same point.
Future videos, as I mentioned, are going
to be covering a lot of the more code
oriented stuff that I just did here for
that last section with the IDs and the
JSON and the dot notation in detail,
just so you guys can add fuel to the
fire and, you know, get a lot more
competent with NAN and no code in
general. Great work uncovering that
first section. You now hopefully
understand what NAND is, how to get set
up on the platform, and even how to
build some simple but useful workflows.
But if you guys really want to
understand NAND and not just NADN but no
code in general, you need a little bit
more knowledge in terms of logic data
handling and then the ability to
manipulate some of the data that we've
seen already. That's what this next part
is all about. We're going to dive into
some more foundational concepts to
separate maybe the NADN automation
entrepreneur who is solely restricted to
copying and pasting blueprints from the
internet to somebody that can actually
build templates of this kind out on
their own. Just a quick note before we
dive in. If you're serious and want to
turn these technical concepts into a
real business, definitely check out
Maker School. It's my Noode AI
automation community with daily
accountability that shows you how to
take this skill set that we're
developing right now and actually put it
in front of real customers. I have over
2,000 members in the community as of
right now. We get new wins, thousands of
dollars closed every day. And if you
guys want the straightest line path
between somebody that doesn't understand
any of this to somebody that is actively
running and managing a successful and
thriving AI automation business, there
is no better way. Anyway, whatever you
do, let's dive into the next part. So,
if you guys have seen some of the other
videos on my channel, you'll know that I
put a very big emphasis on building
things practically. I don't really care
much for the academic side of things. I
prefer we just dive right in and then
teach some of these concepts by actually
putting nodes together, making workflows
that you could sell for business
purposes or implement into your own
companies. And that's what we're going
to be doing today. We can't really get
away from doing some of the academic
stuff with JSON just because, you know,
if you don't know JavaScript object
notation, you are going to have to learn
some things like types and objects and
what variables are and stuff like that.
But for the most part, we're going to be
learning all of these concepts down here
by building two workflows. The first
workflow is up here. And essentially
what this does is it feeds in a bunch of
lead data to artificial
intelligence. This is the Google sheet
containing four leads with a bunch of
information here. So, we're going to
feed in this information to AI. Then,
what we're going to do is we're going to
have AI generate a subject line for an
email, an icebreaker for an email, an
elevator pitch for an email, a call to
action, and then a post script, little
PS sign. The idea here is this is a real
workflow that people pay me for. And so,
these are the ones that I want to I want
to start with. Essentially, this will
allow you to customize email outreach
that it seems as if you've done a lot of
research into the person. Uh, which is
very very valuable in a business
setting. The second workflow is a little
bit more peculiar, I guess. There's this
service out there called source of
sources. It used to be called helper
reporter at Haro. Basically, the way
that it works is this lovely gentleman
here, Peter, will send you uh a bunch of
information basically where journalists
are looking for professionals in a
certain industry to weigh in on some
developments and then if you're a
professional in the industry and you
give the journalist some good info, they
can actually tag you and then like use
you in an article. It's quick and easy
way to basically get listed in a
magazine or some very authoritative data
source. And what this system does is it
basically gets an email like this. Then
it pumps in the titles into AI, does
some cool processing, and then we
actually write a draft of that email as
if we were an expert in that field,
which all you need to do is just like
quickly review, give a once over, edit a
little bit, and then send off to
journalists. There's another system that
I've sold a number of times. And so I
want the videos that I create on NAD to
be practical in nature. I want them to
be on things that you're probably going
to be using for business purposes. So
these are the two systems that uh we're
going to be building. They're cool
systems and all, but you know, for the
purpose of this video, I kind of want to
build them from scratch. So, why don't
we just exit out of that puppy? That's
the prompt that we're going to be using
for AI. And for the rest of this, we'll
just get rid of that. Okay. The very
first concept I want to cover are fixed
fields and expression fields. I'm going
to be basically convincing you to just
use expressions all the time. And I'm
also going to show you how to map
different field inputs cuz the last time
that we jumped around Nadn, we built a
couple of workflows, but I was sort of
glancing over a couple of the um like
some of the nuance behind fields and
stuff like that. So, for the purposes of
demonstration, it's going to be pretty
easy. We're just going to build the
first system out by clicking a button
that is going to get a bunch of data
from our Google sheet, and then we're
just going to pass all of that data in
kind of rowby row into AI. Pretty
simple, pretty straightforward, but
ultimately something that is very useful
and you'll find yourself doing quite a
bit if you do cold outreach. So, first
things first, I'm just going to press
tab. That's going to open up this
trigger thing on the lefth hand side.
And then, you know, if you type trigger
here, there'll be if you type trig, I
should say, you'll see a ton of options
here. Um, you could either do that or
you could just scroll down to the bottom
where it says add another trigger and
then press trigger manually. Either is
fine, but for the purposes of demo, I'm
just going to do that. And basically
what I want to do is the second that I
run this trigger when I click on test
workflow, um, I want to uh, get all of
the rows and all the data in my Google
sheet. So, I'm going to go up here to
nodes. I'm just going to type in sheet.
We're going to get Google Sheets. Now,
what I'm going to do is if you scroll
down here, you'll see that there's this
one node called get rows and sheets.
That's what I'm going to click on. Now,
I've already done a connection before.
Um, what you're going to have to do if
you want to connect to your Google
Sheets account is go to create new
connection. Now, because I'm on the
cloud hosted offering, and keep in mind
if you're not on the cloud hosted
offering, um, these sorts of connections
are a little bit more difficult. You
have to go to Google Cloud Console and
get set up there. But because I'm on the
cloud hosted offering, all I need to do
is click sign in with Google over here,
and I'll actually go connect to my email
account, and then it'll create a
credential for me, which is pretty
handy. So you can see it's saying it's
already has some access just because
I've already done this connection. But
for the purpose of this demo, I just
wanted to show you guys what that looks
like. And then I'm just going to save
this connection here with a name so that
it's just nice and organized. Okay. And
what we want to do is we just want to
grab this Google sheet up here. Right?
So in NAN there are variety of ways to
do this, but I'm just going to I'm going
to be looking for a document. Sorry, a
sheet within a document. My bad. The
document we're going to want to select
is from the list. And we're actually
going to go down. We're going to choose
this one called leads, comma, space,
January 27th, 2025. So, as you can see,
we have already manually found that.
Okay. And then the specific subshet that
we want is this sheet one because I
guess that's the only one that we have
here. So, I'm just going to click on
this. It's going to actually do an API
call to Google Sheets. It's going to
find that there's only sheet one here.
Then I can give it a click and then
voila. Let me just run test step and
let's see what happens when I click
test. Okay, great. So, I've offiscated
this data. This data is not um actually
one for one whoever this this person is.
I've gone through and I've like renamed
them and stuff like that just for
privacy purposes. But as we see on the
right hand side here, we we have a bunch
of output and we can see the output in a
variety of ways. Tabular JSON schema.
Most people and they like the schema
look because it just kind of compresses
the information nicely. It's a little
bit easier for them to see. I'm a little
zoomed in here too. Um but uh yeah, you
know, normally like you see most of the
node variables which is pretty handy.
But this JSON one over here, this is
really intimidating for a lot of people.
And so we're we're going to cover this
in detail. I'm going to show you exactly
how you read JSON, what all those things
mean. But just I just want you guys to
know that for the remainder of this
course, I'm going to be using primarily
the JSON and the schema view. But I'm
actually going to tend towards JSON. And
the reason why I'm going to be tending
towards JSON is because like JSON says
all the same stuff that the schema view
does anyway. But unfortunately, part of
the way you learn JSON is just by kind
of staring at it a lot and squinting at
it and kind of inherently and
intuitively understanding the
formatting. If we're going to be looking
at outputs all day anyway, we might as
well kind of get, you know, kill two
birds with one stone. All of the same
data in JSON is represented in schema
anyway, it's just instead of like the
quotes around key names and stuff, you
just have sort of this light gray box
alongside like a type sign here. So, I
guess the point I'm making is we might
as well double up and just learn how
JSON looks while we're proceeding with
the course. Um, and that's why I'm going
to be using this. Even if it looks a
little bit more intimidating, don't
worry too much about it. Okay, so I said
that I'd talk about fields, right? So
fields in N&M just as I was covering on
the previous video are stuff like this
right we have this sort of center node
config option here for our Google sheets
node um you know one of the fields we
selected was this YouTube credential to
connect with another one was this
resource sheet within document operation
document sheet but I want you to know
that these are actually all
representable in code as well so as you
see over here we have two different
types of fields one's called fixed and
the other is called expression
So, by default, just to keep your life
easy and to not like freak you the hell
out, especially if you're like a newbie
in NN, um they're going to keep all the
fields to the fixed type. But if you
click on
expression, you'll see that things are
now a little bit different. Notice how
when I went to fixed, we had like a nice
little, you know, it said um leads
January 27, 2025. And then when I jump
over to expression, now we have some big
long ID. So, what is this? Why is it
structured that way? And what exactly
does any of this mean? Well, if we pay
close attention, this ID field here, 1
lowerase o t r r r r r r r r r r r r r r
r r r r r r r a t4 C capital C and then
the rest of this big long ID string over
here. If we go to our Google sheet, what
you'll see is that that ID string
actually matches the URL of our Google
sheet
exactly. This takes me to a wider point.
Most of the time, sorry about that. Most
of the time, anytime you're accessing a
resource on some API or even just on the
internet, they will store the ID of the
resource, which is sort of like a hidden
representation of it, in the URL. So,
you know, one of the examples that I
provided the other day was I went over
to ClickUp, right? And inside of
ClickUp, I like searched around for some
record. I'm just going to click on this
here. This is this was my old content
calendar. Um, how to send 1,000 cold
Instagram DMs per day. That was one of
the things I wanted to do. This right up
here is the ID of the record.
86B27A7Zm, right? If I wanted to do
something with this through their API,
this is the ID of the record that I
would be calling. So, I want you to know
that like ClickUp, uh, Monday, uh, like
even Gmail, basically every service out
there, they will store the ID of the
thing you want to modify or update or
whatever just in the URL. So if ever a
field asks for an ID, you can almost
always just go to the URL of the thing
on the actual user um you know on the
actual app like the user interface. Then
you can find that URL thing. You just
hardcode it in here. Okay. So that's
just a just a brief look at some of the
differences between fixed and
expression. Basically fix a lot of the
time just to to keep you guys um to make
sure that like we're on the same page
here. Fix is just the simpler version.
Then expression is sort of what's
actually going on under the hood. So,
you know, um, NAND just defaults to fix
like it just did here because it doesn't
really want to scare you away. But in
order to really unlock the value of NAN,
we have to go to the expression, um,
field. And I'm going to show you here
why, you know, I basically just use
expression for everything at this point.
Okay. So, looking at the output here,
what we have is we have we clicked and
then we got a click event that was
counted as one item. And so, N8 actually
shows you the number of items that are
passed on. Then we pumped that click
event into Google Sheets and then that
click event outputed four items. So now
we actually we're working off of array
data or tabular data which I'll cover um
in a moment. But essentially with these
four items now what we want to do is we
want to pass each of these items into
artificial intelligence and we want to
have AI tell us something about it
before um writing some cold email copy
for us to insert into an email or maybe
we could just send a Gmail directly or
something. So what I'm going to do is
I'm going to click on this button. I
zoom out a little bit. What we want is
we want um if you go down advanced AI,
we want is we want this open AI node.
And specifically what I want is I want
the message a model. So if you've seen
me connect this in the previous video,
you'll notice that you know in order to
create a new credential, you actually
have to go and you have to find the API
key from OpenAI in order to do this.
This is pretty simple to do. You just
type
platform.openai.com/ I think it's like
account/appi or something. You'll have
to click on this button here to open the
documentation to tell you more. But
anyway, you can basically just create an
API key for N8N. Um, it's very simple
and very straightforward to do so. And
I've already done this and I've called
it YouTube. So, I'm just going to use
that credential just so I don't have to
like leak another API key. Now, again,
we have a ton we have a ton of fields.
We have resource text operation message
model from list choose. Keep in mind the
fields are again fixed, right? It's
trying to make it really easy for us to
select GPT40. So, I'm just going to go
down here, type
GPT four, and then I'm just going to
click 40 O. And now we actually enter in
the text that we're interested in. Okay.
And this is really where you're going to
start learning the differences between
the fixed and the expression. So fixed,
again, fixed is just I mean, it's what
the name implies. It's fixed. It's text.
You can't make this dynamic. You can't
add variables to it. It's the simplest
way to get up and running with a node,
which is why NAND will default to fixed.
Um, but over the course of the next few
minutes, I'm going to convince you to
basically always just use expression.
Okay. So, I I saved my prompt somewhere
else. The first thing I'm going to do is
I'm going to add a system prompt. So,
I'm going to go down here to system.
I'll just say you are a helpful
intelligent writing assistant. Usually,
the way that you will do um AI calls is
you will have a system prompt first.
Then you'll have a user prompt after.
And the user prompt is where you
actually give it the instructions you
want it to do. So, you know, in our
case, it's going to be like, hey, I want
you to write a bunch of fields that are
templates that we're going to insert
into a cold email later. And then after
you have the choice to provide a bunch
of examples. So you could provide an
assistant prompt and then you could do
another user prompt. Assistant prompt.
User prompt. Assistant prompt. You can
do that however many times you want just
to show it how things work. For the
purpose of this example, I'm just going
to be providing a single user prompt.
And what I'm going to be doing here is
I'm just going to copy over my prompt
below. Let me paste that in. And let's
just read through this together. Your
task is to personalize an email. You'll
do this by taking as input a prospect
LinkedIn profile. Then editing five
templates for different sections of the
email. Subject line, icebreaker,
elevator pitch, call to action, and a PS
or postcript field. If you're unfamiliar
with postcript, you know, at the bottom
of an email, it'll just say PS, I really
miss you. Can't wait to see you. That's
what a postcript field is. We basically
want AI to automate that for us because
there's a lot of value in making those
postcript fields seem human written.
Anyway, now we're offering it some
templates. subject line. Hey, name I
think I have something for you. Re and
then cool thing about them that we
discovered. Let's just go unique thing
about them or their company. Icebreaker,
I know you're doing thing and I've been
following related thing for a while, so
I figured it made sense to chat. Next
elevator pitch, the TLDDR. I think I can
add 5K a month to their paraphrase
business with a few automated systems.
And then there's a call to action. I
just did this for a very similar
industry company and we had 28,350 in a
few months. They do related things. So
I'm very confident I can duplicate this
at minimum. Would be 100% risk-f free. I
guarantee at least 20 appointments
booked or you wouldn't have to pay.
Pretty neat, huh? So then I give it a
bunch of guidelines. And feel free to
pause the video if you want to take a
look at it. The last thing that I do is
then I say respond in JSo N using this
format. And if you've at all used AI
before, you'll see this JSON thing come
up again. JSON. JSON. JSON. We're going
to cover that in just a few minutes, so
buckle up. Okay, great. So, we've given
it a ton of uh instructions in the first
user prompt. So, what I do next is I
just give it a user prompt with the
actual body of the input that I want to
give. And if you think back here, um you
know what this Google sheet is just just
so you guys um are all on the same page
as me, is I've basically gone and I've
scraped a bunch of data about random
people on the internet that fulfill some
criteria that I have. So, chief
executive officer, director of demand
generation, director of marketing,
business development, manager, some
dentistry person or something. Okay. And
then I have a bunch of fields here. One
of the fields I have is I have a summary
field where people basically write their
own summary of who they are and what
they care about. We have a ton of other
fields as well. We have company
location. We have a description of their
title. We have um I don't know their
their industry. And the cool part about
AI is you can just feed this into a
large language model and have it have it
automate something for you. Have it have
it write something customized. And so
that's what we're going to be doing
here. The thing is though, right, how do
I get dynamic data into this? So, I
don't know, let's say um one of the
things I want is I want to feed the AI
the person's full name. Notice how this
is fixed here, right? If I just typed
Amy
Wabe, then that means that every time I
do an API call that includes their full
name, I'm going to have it say Amy
Wabby. This is fixed. It's the same
thing every time. If you want to make
this dynamic, what you have to do, there
are variety of ways to do this, but I'm
going to use the expression field, is
you have to click
expression and then you drag the field
that you want and then you drop it. And
you'll see that when I do that, we've
now just inserted a little bit of code.
This is in N8N's
um code format, the equivalent of the
variable that we just pulled from our
pinned data or our our data from the uh
input. And what you see down here is
this is separated into two halves. The
top half is the code representation. We
said full name just in like regular
characters. And I can manipulate this
how I want. Then a colon, then a space.
And then there's uh curly bracket curly
bracket space dollar sign Js N. FU L N A
M E space. And then a right curly
bracket right curly bracket. Up here you
have the code representation. And then
notice that underneath here we have
result. It actually shows us what the
data that we're pulling in is from the
input, which was right over here. Now,
I'm going to be feeding it a bunch of
data in order to have this personalized.
I'm going to be feeding in their full
name. I'm going to be feeding in the
summary. I'm going to be feeding in the
title. But I just want you guys to to
notice how these these variables change
between the full name, between the
summary, between the title. And you're
going to notice that there's kind of a
pattern there. Okay. So, full name was
that. We'll go title. I'm just going to
drag this
in. Paste it in. Notice how the first
one was jso nf full name. Second one was
jso n.title.
Right. Let's see what the third one is.
Let's go down here to
company. Company. If I drag and drop
this now says JSON company. You know
that the C is capitalized. That looks a
little bit new, but for the most part,
it's still pretty self-explanatory. It
seems to me if I were an alien staring
at this and looking to try and figure
out what the pattern here is. It seems
to me that every single time I drag and
drop one of these fields in there, it
says dollar sign JSo N dot and then the
name of the variable. The name of the
variable tends to be whatever I'm
looking at on the left hand side here.
So what if hypothetically instead of me
doing this drag and drop what
if I were to actually just try and write
this myself? Well, let's see what
happens. If I zoom in a little bit, just
so we could all see. If I go curly
bracket curly bracket, you'll see that
I'm now entering sort of the next level
up in NN. I'm now manipulating like code
or JavaScript, their version of
JavaScript, the JMSE path, I believe
it's called, directly in the expression
editor. And this is where N gets really
powerful because you also have a ton of
built-in methods and built-in ways you
can manipulate this data with literally
one click, one little button tap without
having to drag and drop all these
modules everywhere. You can just do so
in the convenience of your own field
editor. Okay, so the very first thing
that pops up is it says suggested JSON.
If I just type that and then I press
enter, you'll see that now I have access
to all of the fields that I had access
to earlier. So instead of me dragging
and dropping all this stuff, what if I
just wanted to write the word summary
here to grab this, if I just type
summary, notice how this now turned
green. And we've added all of that
information down here to the results
tab. All that information is here. How
cool is that? So now, you know, if I
want to continue on, I'll go industry.
I'll go dollar sign JSON industry.
Voila. Next, we're going to go company
location. I'm going to go um JSON.co
company location. Voila. Notice how it's
trying to autofill this for me, right?
I'll go title description dollar sign
JSON dot to ital description. Voila. And
I basically have the ability to do this
um infinitely depending on how nested
the data is in the JSON structure of the
input. I I'll run through how to do all
of that um in a moment, but I just want
you guys to sort of pattern match, look
from the outside in. How am I actually
referencing all these variables from
from previous
calls? Okay, great. So, to me, you know,
as somebody that does this sort of
personalization all the time, if we
click on this little button here, we can
actually open up, we can see all of the
um code and all of the text. To me,
somebody that does this all the time,
this looks like sufficient amount of
information for us to personalize an
email off of. So, I'm actually just
going to call it there, and we're
actually going to just run this puppy.
But basically what's going to happen is
we're just going to be feeding in all of
this stuff to artificial intelligence
and we're going to be saying, "Hey man,
based off of all of Amy's info, I want
you to tell me something about her." And
then I want you to write an email um
based off of the template that I
provided you earlier. The last thing I'm
going to do is I'm going to go down here
and press output content as Jason. Give
this a click. And then I'm not going to
modify any of the options here either.
Um but I'm just going to click test
step. Okay. Okay, so what's just
happened or what is occurring as we
speak is I'm feeding in four items to
open AI. I'm basically Blitz going item
one, item two, item three, item four,
and it's happening all at once before
they show us the output of each of
these. So that's why it takes a little
bit longer than usual. Um, but this is
more or less what's happening under the
hood. Okay, great. And we just received
an output. Um, so what I'm going to do
is I'm just going to zoom out a little
bit just so we could see this in
completeness. And I'll use schema for
now just to make it easier for you guys.
doesn't you don't have to like scroll
all the way to the right to see it, but
let's take a look. Um, the output was
content, subject line, icebreaker,
elevator pitch, call to action, PS. So,
it actually went it outputed five fields
for us and we can use those fields in
future nodes very easily. The first
thing in the subject line was, "Hey,
Amy, think I have something for you
regarding boosting online strategies."
The icebreaker was, "I know you're
leading creative web solutions and net
directives and been following innovative
marketing strategies for a while, so I
figured it made sense to chat." The
TLDDR, I think you can add 5K a month to
your client focused internet marketing
efforts with a few automated systems.
The call to action, I just did this for
a very similar IT consulting company. We
hit this amount. They do e-commerce and
marketing, too. How cool is that? So,
I'm very confident I can duplicate this
at minimum. Would be 100% risk-f free.
I'd guarantee at least 20 appointments
booked. You wouldn't pay. P.S., even if
we just chat, I'd love to hear about
what you're doing with video marketing.
That sounds pretty cool to me, right?
And if I were to receive an email like
this, you know, aside from the subject
line, which is a little bit vague,
boosting online strategies, but you
can't fault the AI for not being perfect
100% of the time. Um, you know, even if
I were to get something like this, it
would seem as if, uh, you know, like the
person that's reaching out to me did
their did their research at minimum and
is reaching out to me sort of in a
personalized customized way as opposed
to just like blasting me a big sequence.
So, uh, what else do I want to do with
this? Well, if you guys, you know,
remember back to the beginning of the
video, the there weren't just two or
three nodes here. There was um there was
a node that updated the Google sheet. So
I'm going to show you how to update the
Google sheet. And what we're actually
going to do is we're going to take this
one step further and I'm actually going
to draft some emails to send to Amy and
the rest of the people here. So actually
the first thing I'm going to do is I'm
just going to go over here and pin this
output. The reason why is because if you
think about it, me calling um OpenAI
there, that was a little bit like
computationally expensive. It took me a
little bit of time. I don't actually
want to have to rerun that over and over
and over again. pinning the data just
allows me to capture that, cache it, and
now I can just like test all subsequent
nodes using that, which is very
straightforward. Okay, so what I want to
do, I want to update this Google sheet.
So I'm going to click here, search
nodes, I'll type sheets, and what I want
to do is I want to um update row and
sheet. I'm going to select my
credentials again, YouTube. The resource
will be sheet within document. The
operation will be update row. Let's
instead of using the fix, let's actually
just use the expression so I could show
you how this works. Just going to grab
the ID of this field or of this sheet.
Paste that in there. Voila. Then the
sheet that I'm going to be picking, it's
just going to be sheet one. So notice
that the top here we use the expression
field view and then down here we just
use the fix. So it actually use the
expression field view to do an API call
to their backend to discover that sheet
one was the only sheet and then we
selected it there. We can also just feed
in an expression. And as you see when
you go from fix to expression for the
specific sheet type, it just says G
equals Z. G equals Z just refers to the
first sheet. um basically here. So we're
we're always going to be selecting the
first sheet. But anyway, for this I'm
actually going to go from list and then
I'll just go sheet one. Keep this
simpler. Okay. Now it's going to be
fetching a bunch of columns for us. And
basically in order to do this update,
what we have to do is um we have to grab
the data from the previous nodes and
then we have to update every single
column here with that data. If I were
just to, you know, scroll all the way
down and update the columns that I care
about, like subject, icebreaker,
elevator, pitch, call to action,
postcript, it would just leave the rest
of these blank, which is kind of
annoying if I'm being honest. But I
don't want the rest of these to be blank
and these to be filled. I want all of
this data because I'm just going to
import this into some cold email tool
later, right? So, what we have to do is
now, this is kind of the initial idea
behind this system. I'm going to go
through and I'm going to update every
single one of these um using the
expression tab, and then I'm going to be
pulling data in. But I'm not going to be
pulling data in from here. I'm going to
be pulling data in from one node behind
it. So you guys could see what it looks
like in code basically. Okay. So the
first thing we have to do is we just
need a column to match on. In order for
the automation to know which row should
be updated, we have to find data that
includes that email. So I'm going to go
email. Then the first thing I'm going to
do is I'm going to scroll down here to
the previous node, not the OpenAI node,
but the Google Sheets node, the one that
like first listed us the data. I'm going
to drag this feed that in there. And
you'll notice that the format now looks
different than it did before.
Previously, we had a dollar sign JSON
dot item. Right? Now we have a dollar
sign and then a bracket single quote
sign. The name of the node, another
single quote sign and then another
bracket. And then we go do
item.json. So when you when you access
node data from more than one node back,
you have to use this new format here,
which is kind of annoying, but you'll
see how easy it is when we just like
kind of copy paste and spam our way
through. So, uh, how about this
civility? I'm going to go to expression.
I'm going to paste this in. Then,
instead of email, I'm just going to go
civility. How about this first name?
Let's paste that in there. We'll go
first name. How about this first name
suggestion? Paste that in there. Go
expression. Go first name
suggestion. How about the last name? I'm
going to paste this in there. Go last
name. How about the full name? I'm going
to paste that in there. Go expression.
We'll go full name. How about the title?
I'm going to paste this in there. I'll
go title profile URL. So, you can see,
you know, we're picking up the pace a
little bit. It's getting a little bit
faster and faster.
Company, company, illegal
name, company
phone. And I'm just going to go ahead
and um cut to me having actually filled
all this stuff out just for brevity.
Okay. Okay, elevator pitch, call to
action. Looking good. And then last but
not least, we'll do um I think it was
just PS or was it a post script? Yeah,
sorry, it was just PS for that. This is
the one situation which uh the column
name is a little bit different from the
variable name down here. Okay, now that
we're done with that, let's just quickly
cover um just some little differences
here in the formatting just so we can
get a runup on the JSON, which I'm about
to teach you. If you scroll all the way
up here, you'll see that some of these,
well, actually most of these followed
this format. It was Oops, sorry about
that. Let's go over here. It was um
curly brace curly brace dollar sign the
name of the node in single quotes dot
item.json dot whatever the value was
dots summary. In this case, this one was
regular company URL. This one down here
was VM ID. You'll notice that a few of
these are actually a little bit
different. a few of these in particular
the variable names with spaces. They
weren't just dot you know the name it
was square bracket single quote and then
the name of the variable that we're
referencing. The reason why we had to do
this instead of just doing the dot and
then the variable name is because JSON
in JavaScript object notation you can't
query I mean the technical term is you
can't query a key that has spaces
basically just because spaces aren't
really represented. So, you know, if we
scroll down here to some of these
variable names, first space name space
suggestion, there's a bunch of spaces in
there, right? So, the way that you get
around this in uh NAN's formatting is
instead of calling, let me get that
specific example company legal name or
was it uh first name suggestion. So, the
way that you get around this is you
can't just go first name suggestion cuz
that kind of breaks the formatting here,
right? The way you can get around this
is two things. when you can make it so
that the input data aka the columns in
your Google sheet are all just one word.
So if instead it was first name
suggestion, this would be fine. You
could also do something like first name
suggestion. Some people do that format.
I don't really like that. I don't know
why. What I do is um called camelc case.
It's kind of like a programming
convention. And here we can get into
like a a lifelong mutually assured
destructive battle where some people
prefer camel case, other people prefer
underlining. Um, but I'm team Camel
Case, so go team camel case. Um,
instead, you know, if we want to
represent the spaces, what we have to do
is we have to go brackets here, um,
single colon, first name, suggestion,
another col, uh, another quote sign, and
then another square bracket. So, don't
don't sweat the small little formatting
stuff too much. I just wanted to give
you guys like the best way that I found
to learn this is literally just to like
spam a bunch of examples. Um, that's
what I did when I was picking this stuff
up. I didn't read a bunch of books on
JavaScript object notation or
expressions or whatever. I just spammed
a bunch of examples. And the human brain
is such that if you squint at it long
enough, you'll sort of figure it out
intuitively. Uh, okay, great. So, now
that we've mapped all these, let's
actually go and let's, um, let's update
this data, right? That's the whole point
of this. So, uh, now that we've mapped
all the data, if I click test step, and
then I go over here to my Google sheet,
scroll all the way to the right, you
see, and it just took us a second, but
you see that we just, boom, we just
updated all four of these
simultaneously. Uh, we got the subject
line for Amy, subject line for Joe,
subject line for Mercedes, subject line
for Susan. Same thing with all the
elevator pitches, call to actions,
postcripts. You'll see that the the the
copy of the email is pretty similar, but
um it it changes. So, this one's I know
you're leading creative web solutions. I
know you're le into leveraging customer
voices. I know you're focused on
building relationships. I know you're
advancing digital dentistry. These are
all basically like reframing or
paraphrasing
um the things that they said in their
profile which ultimately uh you know is
meant to make them go like oh okay this
person did their research they read a
little bit about me. So that's pretty
cool. Um why don't we take this one step
further now. Why don't we pin this and
then I'm actually going to create a
Gmail draft in my inbox just so we can
see what's going on here. So I'm type
draft create a draft. I'll connect with
my Gmail credential and this is before I
did the naming convention so it was
probably number three. We're just going
to create a draft. The subject line is
going to be, let's just go to fix now
that we know how to do this. It's going
to be JSON dot uh subject right
here. And then the actual message, it's
going to be pretty interesting, but I'll
show you I'll show you how we put it
together. First thing we're going to do
is we're going to go JSON dot. And then
what I want to do is I want an
icebreaker.
Uh, sorry, I don't want an icebreaker. I
want to go hi. And then I want to grab
the person's name. So I'll go Jason
first name right
here. So hi
Amy, then we have the the JSON
icebreaker. Next up, I want to go JSON
dot uh sorry dollar sign JSON dot and
then what were we doing here? Was it the
elevator pitch? Yeah, it was the
elevator pitch. Paste that in there.
Then we want to go dollar sign JSON dot
what's the next one? Call to action.
Beautiful. And we also want to go dollar
sign JSON dot and I'm sure you guys can
guess what the last one is, but very
quickly make sure you do make sure you
know u postcript. Now if we open up this
thing in the bigger example window,
you'll see the email says, "Hi Amy, I
know you've been leading creative web
solutions and net directives. Been
following innovative marketing
strategies for a while, so I figured it
made sense to chat. The TLDDR, I think I
can add 5K a month to your client
focused internet marketing efforts with
a few automated systems. I just did this
for and even if we just chat, I'd love
to hear about what you're doing with
video marketing." I guess I actually
need to add a PS sign here. And it looks
like none of these have periods.
Actually, I think this last one has a
period, but not all of these do. So,
just because I was a little bit um fast
in kind of designing this and I didn't
put periods over, I'm actually just
going to add the periods directly into
the expression editor. I'm go PS here.
Okay. And now, if we open it up, this is
what it looks like. We got periods
everywhere. Cool. Wonderful. And then we
have a little PS sign here. Even if we
just chat, I'd love to hear what we were
doing with video marketing. Very, very
cool. Awesome. Awesome. So, now that we
have that pinned data, um, why don't we
just draft these emails? So, I'm going
to, uh, create a draft. I'm not actually
going to send this cuz I don't just want
to spam a bunch of these people. I've
also changed the email address and
stuff, so I'd get a bunch of bounces.
We're just going to test step. It's
executing. We just executed four nodes.
So, now if I go over here, go to
drafts, you'll see here that we have,
"Hey, Susan, think I have something for
you. Red digital dentistry." Oh, gez,
I'm realizing I didn't put the um email
address in actually. Yeah, I did not put
the email address in. I just did the
draft. U in options you have to go to
email. And then what we want to do is we
just want to drag that back here. JSON
email to get that address. Let's create
four more drafts just for shits and
gigs. Then why don't I just delete the
ones that I just generated uh right over
here. Going to just discard
these. And then you see that the four
that I just did now have just popped up.
And they also have the email addresses
there. So yeah, that's that with that
example. Um, I think at this point you
guys probably have an intuitive
understanding of how these fields work.
And hopefully I've made a case for why
you should just always use expression.
Like there's no real need to do fixed
because if you think about it, like you
could just write the same fixed thing.
Like if I wanted to type, hey, think I
have something for you regarding
marketing strategies. And I just wanted
to send the same thing every time. I
could do so with the expression view of
the field, right? Like same thing. It's
just here I also have the ability to u
modify uh code a little bit and like do
something if I wanted to. So, I
personally am always going to be using
this moving forward. And the reason why,
sorry, it can be kind of a lot to see if
you muck around with. Just always put a
dollar sign first if you're referencing
data from the previous node. Uh, and the
reason why is it's just going to be the
easiest for me. Um, you know, you get
all the variables up here anyway. It's
no big deal. So, we're doing subject.
Stick that in there. We got the subject
line. We are good to
go. So, uh, I think we probably learned
a fair amount about the fixed fields and
expression fields at this point. Um, the
last thing I wanted to cover, I say
mapping different field inputs to it.
The last thing I wanted to cover was uh
if we go back to Gmail
here and if we scroll down to actually
this is a bad example. Why don't we go
back to open
AI? You see here how um I selected the
RO field and it was fixed and then I
selected from a dropown user assistant
system whatever. Well, I can actually
just go expression and what you see here
is this is just text that we are feeding
this API the uh the node. We're actually
just writing user. So instead of writing
users, you could also write a system.
This fix stuff. This is just made to
make our life a little bit easier. But
anytime you want to get the actual data
representation, just move over to
expression. So what are some examples of
that? Well, like you see these simplify
output and output content is JSON
fields. We go to expression. You'll see
that what we're actually passing is
we're passing this true value. We're
literally just writing true. Um output
content is JSON. If we move it to
expression, you can see we're actually
just passing true here. For output
content is JSON. The point that I'm
making is um all of this is basically
just um you know if we just strip away
all of the basic simple stuff. You can
start getting into what's actually going
on behind the scenes. How we're actually
communicating with these nodes. The way
that we're actually communicating with
these nodes in practice is we're sending
the term true. Now the reason why this
one has quotes around it I believe is
because um true is a special case. It's
called a boolean which I'm I'm about to
cover right now. Um so I believe you
need these quotes just for NAD to like
not bug out at you. um just one of those
unfortunate peculiarities of the
platform. But that's that for fixed
fields and expression fields. Okay, next
up, let's talk more about JavaScript
object notation. And if you guys already
know JSON, if you've already
experimented and and understand the
various formatting types available here,
feel free to skip on until we move on to
how data in N8 is represented. Um should
be about 15-ish minutes or so. Uh but
for everybody in the audience that
doesn't understand JavaScript object
notation, I just want to go real deep
into it and I want to make sure you
understand everything about JSON because
ultimately as opposed to a lot of other
noode platforms, NAD it doesn't ignore
code or try and shove code away. It
actually embraces code. So understanding
a little bit of some of the um code
types like JSON for instance makes you
way more powerful. This is really what
like everybody that makes money with
this platform uses. We just use JSON to
send data back and forth. Um, and you
know, if you don't know JSON,
everything's going to be a little bit
trickier for you. Okay. So, what's the
best way to um intuitively understand
JSON? Well, what I'm going to do next is
I'm going to walk you through the
various data types in JSON. Uh, I'm
going to give you just like a a brief
little um structure and format, and then
we can actually just walk through JSON
kind of step by step depending on
different variables and stuff like that.
So, I'm just going to go and type in
JSON formatter. This is just the
simplest and
freesting platform I found online. As
you can see, we got tons of ads in the
middle here. you don't pay anything to
use it, but basically what's happening
under the scenes is behind the scenes is
it's running um with every time you
press a keystroke, it's just double
checking to see if it's valid JSON. This
is actually pretty useful for us because
we can we can verify if something is
indeed JSON or not just by looking at
it. This isn't the only way to do it.
Obviously, we could do a ton of
different things. We could I could open
up like a code platform like VS Code or
something and do the same thing, but I
just wanted to keep this thing
accessible for all of us. All right. So,
zooming way in here, um, just so I don't
get ads in my face 24/7. So, what is
JavaScript object notation? Basically,
JSON um is just a way to represent data
in a structured and standardized
format that minimizes the number of
characters and it also minimizes the
ambiguity so that when we send data to
and from some API or something, we could
do so as efficiently as possible.
So the way that JSON works, the way that
you send and receive data is based off
of two um two concepts. The first
concept is a key. So I'm going to write
a key here. This key is going to involve
my name. The first name is going to be
sorry um the the key name is going to be
called first name. So the key is just
you can think of it as like the name of
a variable. So the variable is called
first name, but what the variable equals
is a whole different matter. And that's
where the value comes
in. So first name I'm going to set to
Nick. So this here is proper or well
formatted JSON. It's not yelling at us
or anything like that. It's it's it's
actually good, which is nice. So this is
an example of one of the simplest
JavaScript objects that you could build.
It is a onekey uh one value object. The
key being first name and the value being
neck. You've undoubtedly seen examples
of this before if you tried working with
any noode or coding platform um you know
nadn included. The thing is in JSON
there are a few simple but consistent
formatting quirks that you just have to
pay attention to. So the first is there
are variety of different data types. Now
as you can see here what I've done is I
have this open curly bracket and then
close curly bracket. I have the key name
over here, a a colon, that's just these
two dots, and then I have the
value, but what I've done is I've
wrapped everything in these double quote
signs here. So, first name, double
quote, Nick, double quote. The reason
why is because the data type that I'm
going with here is called a string. It's
actually a particular data type. A
string is just like written text. Okay,
so this is if if instead of first name I
say ID, this here this is a string data
type, but it's not like you don't only
have strings available to you. Although
a lot of platforms prefer strings, you
also have a variety of other data types.
Here's another data type we have access
to. This is a number data type. It's
numeric. So in order to um you know send
and receive numbers, you don't actually
have to wrap them in quotes. This red
here just corresponds to it being linted
or formatted or whatever by this JSON
formatter as a number data type. So this
is still valid JSON even though we don't
have the quotes around this. Okay, this
is not valid JSON, right? This does not
mean anything because we're using string
characters uh and we're inserting it in
something that the software that we're
going to be using NN is going to be
expecting to be a number. So basic rules
of thumb are uh you can't just write a
string without wrapping it in
quotes. And the unfortunate reality is
numbers can be both numbers and
strings. So three ways to do X. Maybe we
call this titles, right? The three here,
this is a number, right? But we are
still wrapping this within the quotes of
a string. However, this is different
from this.
And so in practice, the reason I harp on
this is because uh in practice this
usually doesn't matter that much. No
code platforms will take care of like
the type conversion for you between
number to string. Um if you're using a
number, if you're sending it as like
just the three without the quotes around
it, um for the most part, that's that's
okay. You'll be able to use this as a
string later on. But in like pure
JavaScript and a couple of programming
languages, you can't actually just like
if you wanted to, I don't know, run a
function after this that added a number.
um you know maybe it was like here let
me show you number of things then title
template let's say I had some function
where I wanted to add the number of
things to the beginning of the title
template so that it said three ways to
create NAN flows five ways to create N
flows 15 ways to create NAN flows some
programming languages wouldn't let you
do that in which case you'd have to
convert this to um you know a string and
then you could just go number of things
plus title template equals 15 ways to
create N
flows. Okay, great. So, we've covered
numbers. We've also covered uh and
numbers, I believe they have some fancy
name, int or or technically they could
be floats. They could be a number of
things, but um in our case, we're just
going to go numbers. Next up, I want to
cover a couple of additional data types.
So, one of the data types is called
bool. So, a bool stands for boolean.
Boolean just means zero or one, true or
false. So, true, see how this just
turned into orange instead of gray. Um,
true is an accepted bool and you don't
actually need to wrap uh quotes around
this true in order for it to technically
be valid JSON. Now, for the most part, I
will always just wrap quotes around all
this stuff anyway because as I
mentioned, they do type conversions and
it doesn't really matter to me too much.
But I just wanted you guys to sort of
explain why sometimes you see stuff that
is not wrapped in quotes, and that's one
of them. You also have a few higher
level data types. And one of the higher
level data types um that I'm going to
show you guys, I'm going to show you
two. The first is I'm going to show you
an array. An array looks like this. It's
with square brackets. So you have a left
square bracket and then a right square
bracket. Then the other is another
JavaScript object. And the really cool
part about JSON is you can infinitely ne
nest different data types within the
values of uh of a key. So, I could
theoretically wrap an array, which is
just a number of things. And then inside
of that
array, I could wrap a number of other
JavaScript objects that go infinitely
deep. And I'll show you guys how to do
this in practice. But maybe we'll just
go items. Then here we'll go first name,
Nick. Here we'll go first name. And
we'll go Sally. Then here, uh, let's
just do two so I don't run off the page.
So now what we've done is we've created
JSON where we have a key called items.
Then inside of said key we have an array
and inside of set array we have two more
objects. Both objects have the key
called first name and then they have
different values. The first has a value
of Nick, the second has a value of
Sally. Now to make people's lives easy,
usually the way that this works is you
will do some level of uh formatting like
this string formatting just to make your
life really really easy. You'll be able
to
see like where the item starts and then
there's usually like a fair amount of
indentation and I don't know the exact
amount of indentation but usually it
looks something like this. Now at a
glance you can kind of see the structure
of this. It's sort of nested. You have
um this top level array and inside of
the array you have two objects. First
name Nick, first name Sally.
Okay, great. So, let's create a
hypothetical JSON object. And just
because I know the most about myself,
I'm going to be creating this for
myself. Let's hypothetically just create
a JSON object. And let's just do like a
user object. Okay. So, what I'm going to
do is I'm going to go user. That's going
to be the key name. Then I'm going to go
uh colon. And then I'm going to create
another
object. Inside of my user object, I'm
going to have first
name. First name is Nick. We have a last
name. My last name is
Sarafh. Um I'll have city. My city for
the time being is Calgary. I'll have
um foods he enjoys or foods, let's just
call it food preferences, right? Cuz if
you say foods he enjoys, now you're um
insinuating that has to be a he. And
then what if you add a user in the
future that is a woman? Do you want to
change the key name? No, obviously not.
So food preferences, I'm just going to
add an array. And inside of my array are
going to be a bunch of strings. So, one
of my food preferences is um I don't
know,
Thai. I'm going to have another one that
is uh I don't know, like Japanese. Okay,
so I like Thai food and I like Japanese
food. Apparently, I like absolutely
nothing else. I have a very strict diet.
Okay, cool. And then why don't we add
um let's just add one more. And then I'm
just going to add one called friends
hypothetically. Um but because as we all
know, I have absolutely no friends. Um,
and then inside of friends, we're going
to add a another object. We're going to
add an array. And inside of that, we're
going to have first name. We're going to
have Peter, my uh dearest and longest
friend, of course. Thank you, Peter.
Then underneath that, we're going to
have um last
name Griffin because I am now
uh loving family guy. And that's one of
my friends. And then I'm just going to
copy this over. I'm going to add a a
comma because you need a comma in
between all items in an array and also
all items in an object. So, we have our
object here. It's a pretty intense user
um object. We have a first name, last
name, the city the person lives in, the
food preferences, we have a list of
friends, right? The reason why I go into
this much uh detail here to create this
object is just because I want to impress
upon you that you can make an object
arbitrarily detailed. You can make it as
detailed as a human being could ever
possibly want. And a lot of the time
you'll see that these APIs that you're
accessing, these these calls that you're
making to these different nodes that
return you data about a particular
software platform, they will be really
really deep and they will have nested
data like six or seven things uh levels
deep essentially. So the easiest ones to
use in my experience are just the ones
that are all um you know surface level.
You just have like a user object and
then a first name and then a last name,
a city and then maybe some food
preferences. But in practice, you know,
we need to be a little bit more capable.
And understanding how data is structured
in JavaScript object notation is uh
probably like half the battle to be
completely honest. So, I believe I've
covered everything I wanted to cover.
The last thing I'll mention is um you
can't have a comma, I believe, be the
last Yeah, it doesn't allow you to have
a comma for the last item in an object
or an array. So notice here how we have
a curly bracket, then we have the key
name user, then we have another object
sign, and then we have the key name and
then the value. The key name and the
val, the key name, and then the value.
Between each of these, we have a comma.
But just know that at the last item in
an array or the last item in an object,
you can't have a comma. So you just need
to remove that. If I press format or
beautify, which is just my button that
tells me everything's okay. Um, then you
see that it is indeed formatted and
beautified. Everything's everything's
all right. Okay, cool. So that's the
meandering um you know that's sort of
how to understand this stuff from a
bird's eye view. Moving forward what I'm
going to be doing is just to make our
lives a little bit easier. I'm going to
be showing you guys in every module or
every node I should say on what the JSON
is of the input and the output. The
reason why is it's just going to make it
a lot easier for us to ultimately you
know reference stuff and then do cool
things with the data. So I go back to
our Google Sheets example from earlier.
I'm just going to move the input sorry
I'm going to have the output be JSON.
And you'll see that in this case what we
have is we have an open JSON curly
bracket. Then we have a bunch of top
level keys. So row number over here,
well that's a key. And you can see that
it's represented as a two. Very similar
to what we talked about earlier, right?
You'll notice that the formatting here
is a little bit different. Notice that
this one has an underscore and then
these other ones are all camel case and
some of these are capitalized. Because
these are within quotes, none of this
stuff really matters. But just showing
you guys that there's a there's a
variety of like conventions that people
do. Some people like capitalizing
things, some people don't. So my
recommendation to you just to keep
everything really clean and and expected
is just to pick one format and stick
with it. If you like the underscores,
use the underscores for everything. If
you like the camel case like me, use the
camel case for everything. But anyway,
civility is Mr. First name Amy. First
name suggestion, it's empty. You know,
when something is empty in JSON, you
just use these quotes. Notice that every
item here has a comma in between it.
last name, comma, full name, comma,
right? Just going all the way down. And
then if I zoom out, I scroll, you'll see
now what do we have here? This was just
one item. So if I just click on this
little blue left curly bracket, it'll
actually nest the item for me. And
you'll see that inside of this item are
38 other items, but it'll just nest it
for me. And then I can see the next one.
Now I can see the next one. Now I can
see the next one. Right? We only have
five. So that'll be it. But now I want
to show you guys a little bit about how
an format stuff because it's a little
bit different than Jason I just showed
you. But once you understand this,
basically everything from here on out
will be child's play. Notice how the
very first character that you see on the
output page on the JSON is a square
bracket. Well, if you think back to the
example that I gave you earlier, if we
click out of this um Pizza Hut ad, as
much as I love Pizza Hut, this array
here starts with these square brackets.
And so we see over here we have a square
bracket as well. That means that this is
an array basically. So the way that data
is represented in NADN is all data on
the platform is represented as an array
of objects. Okay. So if I scroll down
here to how data in NAN is represented.
All of it is an array of objects. All of
it will basically be those two square
brackets on the outside of a number of
items. And you could have as many items
as you want. As we saw, we had four back
over there. And inside of those four
items, we had an additional 38 items
nestled inside. But all data is an array
of objects. Meaning that that's how you
send and receive multiple objects.
Remember at the beginning here we had
one item. We just outputed a single
variable there. Well, now after this
Google Sheets call, we're doing four
items. Those four items are represented
in our JSON as an array inside of which
is another object that has the key name
row underscore number, civility, first
name, first name, suggestion, and so on
and so on and so forth. So all data in
NAD is an array of objects. The number
one gotcha that I always see when
beginners start out with this is they
end up not fully understanding how many
objects the previous node is sending or
the current node is receiving. And so
then when they try and reference a
particular item inside of the data
structure, they find that it just
doesn't exist or they need to like index
it, they need to slice in to find a
specific item inside of the array of
items or some other problem. But this is
the number one problem that I see in
practice just running through reading
like NA and help threads and stuff like
that that people struggle with on this
platform. So if you understand this the
fact that all inputs and all outputs are
an array of items represented as follows
and now if you understand how to format
JSON what JSON looks like and now
further if you just make it so that you
look at the JSON and not necessarily the
table or the schema format every time
you're sending and receiving data you
will solve the biggest gotcha that
people have within it's just going to be
a lot easier for you moving forward to
you know create flows. You're you're
basically going to take so much of the
load off that most other people spend
like hours and hours and hours trying to
debugging. um right from the get- go
which is ultimately what I wanted to do
here. Okay, great. So now we know that
data in N8N is represented as an array
of objects. So how do you actually
reference that data? You guys remember
earlier in that example here where we
were using this Google sheet module?
Sorry, this Google sheet node I should
say. And if we scroll down here, we were
updating a field using data not from the
previous node but from a few nodes back.
Well, basically if I go back to JSON
here, what you can see is we can go one
node back to open ad, two nodes back to
Google Sheets, three nodes back to when
clicking test workflow. Okay, let's just
go to this Google sheet. In order to
reference data, actually in this case,
we will use the schema cuz you can
actually see sort of them logically top
to bottom. In order to reference data
more than one node back, what we have to
do, if we just want to redo this email
one, we go curly bracket curly bracket
dollar sign. Then what we want to do is
we go this left round bracket. Then we
have access to all of our earlier nodes.
We can select the current node open AI,
but we can also select Google Sheets.
And we can also select when clicking
test workflow we want is the Google
Sheets. And then if you just dotindex,
if you put a period, then you'll get an
item. And the reason why I bring up this
item is because basically all of this
stuff is buried under this dot item
syntax. And it's kind of annoying, but
in order to reference, I don't know, the
row number, what we have to do is we
have to reference the Google sheet. Then
we have to reference the item. Then we
have to reference JSON. Then we have to
reference the row number. Why? Because
NAN actually hides some of this
information from us. We don't actually
see the nested data structure. All we
see is the nice representation of it.
Okay. So this isn't actually represented
this way despite the fact that it looks
kind of like it is. The way that this
actually looks kind of underneath the
scenes behind what NAN is showing us is
it looks like this. And if you
understand this, you'll understand how
to reference basically any item in NAN.
So this is equivalent to what we're
seeing here. What we actually have is
there's an additional two layers between
us accessing the data through the dot
thing. It's actually
item.json and then we have the row
number, stability, first name, first
name, suggestion, stuff like that. Okay.
So that means that when we want to
access it kind of just just looking over
here, the very first thing we have to do
is we have to reference the Google
sheet. Then think about it logically.
Then we have to reference the item. So
go item. Then we have to reference the
JSON.js.
And then we have to reference the row
underscore number if we want to like
that. And then we get that data. Okay.
So big issue, big misunderstanding I
would say with Naden. Um unfortunately
their documentation in my experience is
not clear enough to really elucidate
what's going on here unless you have a
programming background. Um but just want
you guys to know that this is how it's
done when you reference nodes that are
more than one module back. If you wanted
to just reference something in the
previous node, it's a lot easier. You go
dollar sign and then you go JS. then you
can just go immediately into the
variables. Message content or something
like that dot subject line for instance.
All right, so let's start looking at
some of these foundational nodes over
here because I think at this point we've
done four different workflows and I
think you guys probably have a
reasonable understanding of how to put a
workflow together now as well. Some of
the more nuanced portions of NAN like
the way that they do their JSON, some of
the the nuances behind burying names
inside of various keys and how to do
arrays of objects and backtrack and all
that fun stuff. Let's actually cover
like nodes because nodes are ultimately
what you guys are going to be using on a
daily basis. After we're done that, then
I'll I'll rebuild this flow up here and
I'll show you guys how all that stuff
works under the hood. This will allow us
to use some of the more um I guess code
oriented features of N&N. Then I think
after this point, like you guys have a
reasonable enough understanding to build
most things. It's just a matter of like
what can you build and how exactly do
you put the various Lego blocks I've
shown you together. That's what the
subsequent videos in this course are
going to are going to ultimately just
show you. It's going to be non-stop
building 24/7, baby. Anyway, so let's
cover these foundational nodes. The
first thing is we're going to cover
nodes for doing things. So, HTTP
requests, web hooks, and open AI nodes.
And we'll cover nodes that modify flows.
So, if filter, merge, split into
batches. There are a couple of other
ones, but these are the ones that we're
going to be focusing on, at least for
today. So, you know, in terms of nodes
that do things, um, if you guys aren't
familiar with, um, HTTP request, this
stands for hypertext, I don't know,
hypertext transfer protocol. And what
we're doing when we do an HTTP request
is we're doing the same thing that your
browser does when it goes to a website.
So just like when I go to google.com,
I'm sending a request to Google,
receiving a bunch of information what
this web page looks like, and then I'm
using my browser Chrome to render it
into the beautiful, wonderful image you
have in front of me. The HTTP request
does the same thing. It just it just
returns the thing to you in the code.
You don't have that rendering portion.
So I'm going to do a get request here.
And the get request is just the simplest
and most basic request. And this is
ultimately what you're probably going to
be using for for most cases. And the URL
I'm going to be doing is just my own
leftclick.ai. So leftclick.ai just for
the purposes of this discussion. Looks
like this. We build hands-off growth
systems for B2B founders. There's a
bunch of information about what our
clients get, our leads. The lovely Joe
Davies left me a testimonial. I should
probably touch this website up at this
point. It's been the same for a while.
But anyway, I'm just doing an HTTP
request using a method get to
leftclick.ai I with no authentication,
no nothing. We're just going to see what
happens. So, let me click that test
step. And the response that we've
received is again an array of objects.
Our one object has a key name data. Then
inside of that key name, you'll see that
there is a ton of code. HTML it's
called. Okay. And just because this is
not the easiest to see here, I'm just
going to go to schema view so you can
see a little bit more of it. But
basically, this here is the code of my
website. This is what my website looks
like to the browsers. um you know and
like what ultimately my browser uses to
render it. You can see it says leftclick
space vertical carrot space AI and
amperand. This is just a symbol that um
allows it not to break any characters.
Process optimization. Left click is an
AIdriven performance optimization agency
is cutting edge tech to scale your
company. This is all the code, right?
It's pretty badass. If I were to go to
leftclick and then I were to go to
inspect, if I were to open this up, this
is like the Chrome dev tool which allows
you to see the code of the website. It's
the exact same thing that's over here in
the bottom lefthand corner, right?
Literally no differences whatsoever. You
built your agency, we'll scale it. The
only difference is some symbols like the
amperand or maybe the ad sign, they just
have like little replacements here or
there so they don't break any um string
formatting. So that's the HTTP request.
Why why does an HTTP request matter and
why would we want to do an HTTP request?
Well, the reason why is because you can
do pretty cool stuff with this. Like if
I go um HTML and then I say extract HTML
content. What we can do is we could use
the code of the page to pull out all of
the text. Okay. So why don't I just go
text? I'll go P. Uh let's just do H1,
H2, H3, H4, H5, H6. Let's do P. I'm
going to return this value as text. And
then I'm going to return uh let's just
test this and see what happens.
What we're doing is we're basically
feeding in the HTML and then we're using
uh various CSS selectors they're called
to extract a bunch of text for us. And
it looks like I didn't do this right
because we're not actually retrieving
anything. Let's just try P for
now. We'll do this. You're seeing
already that we've extracted a bunch of
P text. We've extracted basically like a
specific type of
tag inside this website that starts with
a P. Okay. Now, we can do the same thing
with a variety of other tags. Let's say
I want to do H1. This is going to return
all of the um top level selectors
basically. So, let's do H1
test. We build we build hands-off growth
systems for B2B founders. That's pretty
cool. If I return an array, let's return
all of them. We build hands-off growth
systems for B2B founders. A better way
to build ops. What our clients get. If I
do uh I think if I want to select
multiple, I just would I just do P like
this. H1 and P. Yeah, there we go. Okay.
So now I'm getting all the text of the
website. We build hands-off growth
systems for B2B founders. Find the
perfect offer. Automate your lead
acquisition. Solve your project
management. A better way to build ops.
This is all the text of the website. And
all I needed to do in order to feed this
in was I basically went through and then
I fed in a bunch of elements which I
know just correspond to text like this.
And then I pressed test step. It went
through and it extracted all of them
into this big fat array which is really
cool. Now like if you think about it, I
could actually do some pretty cool stuff
with this. I could have AI tell me
something about the site very easily.
You're a helpful intelligent uh website
scraping assistant. We'll go got to add
my credential first. We'll go down here
and I'm just going to have AI tell me a
little bit about this website. Return in
JSON just some data. I'll do that as my
system prompt. And then here, your task
is to take as input a bunch of scraped
website text and return as output a JSON
that follows this
format. I'm going to say summary. I'm
going to say three unique
points. We'll do an array. We'll do um
probable customer demographic. Okay, I'm
going to have it return an object. we'll
see contact
information if any and then we'll do I
don't know some sort of like array of
objects. Okay. And then that's that's
what we're going to have it return.
We're going to output the content as
JSON and then as input add a message.
What we want to do is we just want to
join this is um being output as an array
right now. Right? Arrays as we see are
many options or many different um things
on various lines. What we want to do is
we want to take all of this output data.
We just want to turn it into one big
long string. The way you do that here is
I would use the expression tab and then
I'm just going to add some lines so the
AI knows that this is my input. Then I'm
just going to go
JSON.ext and then dot we'll just go
join. Join is just a way to convert an
array of items into just one big long
string. And the thing you put inside of
the join is you just put what you want
to separate it by. So in my case, I'll
just separate it all with a new line. If
I enter the detailed editor here, you
can see that now I've just turned all of
this into one giant long string. I'm
going to feed this into AI and I'm going
to have it just tell me something about
the
website. So, this took us just a few
seconds. And we already have a scraper
that's basically capable of coming up
with and then outputting a summary of
what I do, three unique points that
separate me from the competition,
probable customer demographic
information maybe I can use to do
something, then contact information if
any. And it looks like it separated that
into a subobject that says method, book
a call, details, get started today,
platform, website. As I'm sure you guys
can imagine, I spent 15 seconds putting
this puppy together. If you guys wanted
to maybe scrape emails or do something
like that, you could put something
together that does this pretty easily.
So that's the HTTP request node. Pretty
simple, pretty straightforward. The next
thing I want to show you is I want to
show you basically the inverse of the
HTTP request node. Instead of us sending
data, I want to show you a quick and
easy way that we can receive a little
bit of data if necessary. But it's
nowhere near as hard as you think. There
are a variety of different ways that you
could do this, but I'm going to show you
guys a really simple and easy one that I
personally use all the time. It's called
the web hook. So, I'm going to go over
here, then I'm going to type a web hook.
Starts the workflow when a web hook is
called. Basically, what a web hook is is
it's just a server URL that you spin up,
almost like my website, leftclick. And
every time that server gets a request to
it, it'll show up here with all of the
data. Why is this so valuable? Well, it
allows us to do a million things.
Connect workflow to workflow, add up and
create our own API integrations, do a
variety of things that otherwise we
wouldn't really be able to do without
them. This is basically the glue that
holds the internet together. And this is
a quick and easy way for you to make
your own piece of that. So, this is what
the web hook fields look like. We have a
test URL, production URL. Don't worry
about the distinction there for now.
We'll just use test URL. HTTP method we
want to allow to access our service.
Think we might actually allow multiple.
One of these I think allows us to do
multiple, but we're just going to go
with get for now. The path, we're going
to leave the path as fixed. The path is
just this URL string. Authentication,
we're going to turn this off. We don't
want any authentication. They recommend
that you have authentication, but for
simplicity sake, I'm just not going to
have any because otherwise it might be a
little bit too much at once. Then we're
going to do respond immediately. What
I'm going to do is I'm going to set up a
test event for this URL. Okay. Actually,
I don't know if I can do this within the
same workflow. Actually, no, I can't
because the workflow is already running.
So, I'm actually going to make another
workflow really quickly. And I'm going
to use that to call this web hook to get
some cool data. So why don't I create a
workflow. We'll just call this three
nadn concepts. And then we'll go web
hooks http
requests. I'm going to make a new HTTP
request here. It's going to get this
long thing that I've done over here.
Okay. I'm going to test it. Then over
here I'm going to grab that data. And as
you can see like what just happened if
you were paying close attention is this
just ran. The second I sent the data
from this node which is in another
workflow over to this node which is on
the current workflow we received a ton
of info and the info that we received
was received a big object one item
inside of our array of objects here. So
a single object with a key name headers
which had a bunch of other data
underneath params query body web hook
URL execution mode test. So this might
look a little bit dry and a little bit
boring to us right now but what's the
value here? The value is you can run
something from one workflow, send it to
another workflow really easily. So in
our our first example, we sent no data.
But what if I go back to my other
workflow, okay, that's number three
here. And then I send some query
parameters and I say first name and I
say Nick. Then I go here a last name
surive. And then here maybe I go UU ID.
That's just like user ID. And then I
type something like this. Now if I go
back here, then I listen for a test
event. I go back here and then I send
the test event. Now when I receive it,
not only do I get the headers, sorry,
the headers over here, not only do I get
the params inside of our query are the
variables that I just sent over inside
of JSON. First name, last name, UU ID.
So man, I can do so many cool things
with this. It's crazy. I could connect
this to any web service out there. just
give this URL as the URL where the
events are sent and then voila, I
basically have like an infinite machine.
I'll show you guys a quick example right
now using
ClickUp, but you guys can extend this
example and do whatever the hell you
want with it. So, ClickUp is just this
project management platform that I have
that allows you to send out web hooks.
And most services that are good will
allow you to do stuff like this. But you
see there's a call web hook feature
here. I'm going to go back to my web
hook and I'm going to copy this URL.
Now, this is for get only. I don't
actually remember if ClickUp sends a get
or a post. So, we're going to see what
happens here. And then what I'm going to
do is I'll just have status change.
We're going to say from specifically
hook to specifically
outline. And we're going to create this.
And basically what this means is when I
change a field called status inside of
my my project manager, it sends a web
hook over to this
address. So hook to outline find
something that's hook. Maybe this one
here. Now what I'm going to do is I'm
going to go over here, listen for a test
event. Then I'm going to change this to
outline. And I don't remember if it's a
get or a post request. So we might have
to wait and try two or three. This
unfortunately does not respond to the
methods that are not the same. methods
are, you know, kind of a deeper story,
but basically there are variety of ways
you can query a website or a web
service. HTTP, most commonly, you'll do
either a get or a post. Um, in this
specific instance of ClickUp, it looks
to me like they're probably using post.
So, I'll go HTTP method. I'll go
post. Now, I'll listen for this test
event. I'll change this back to
hook. Then, I'm going to change this
back to outline. And now that it's
outline, um, we're waiting for this this
post request. Let's see if we we are
receiving it from ClickUp. Okay, great.
Looks like we received it. Now, what did
we receive in reality? Well, excuse me.
I'm like really close to sneezing, but
I've decided not to, so I won't. Uh,
before we updated the query field, now
we're updating the body field. We see
it's built into ClickUp. What we did,
ClickUp has a number of default things
that they send over when you do this web
hook integration. One of them is the ID
of the record. Now there's the trigger
ID ID the trigger payload ID the name of
the thing which was three chat GBT
prompt engineering hacks you need to
start using next some hooks some order
in text some information about the
person that created it the point that
I'm making is we just created our own
integration with ClickUp and it took me
like 30 seconds realistically after I
got off the HTTP method hump so in
practice sometimes APIs like ClickUp I'm
sure they have API documentation
somewhere but sometimes they just don't
tell you right at the point of creating
the web hook whether it's going to be a
get or a post request. So if your get
request doesn't come in, just change the
HTTP method to post and then rerun it
with the post uh example and then one of
those will work, which is pretty cool.
Okay, so that's how you do it as a test
URL. Ultimately though, we don't just
care about having this workflow be sort
of a test. We want it to be live. And so
when your workflow moves to production,
aka you publish it and you make it live
to actually interact with the internet,
you're going to want to go over to this
production URL and then copy this URL
and update all of your web hooks to send
here. And this will enable you to
activate this. If it's in test mode, you
actually won't be able to activate this.
Um, just I guess for safety or security
purposes. It just makes the transition
to publish it unfortunately involve an
additional step, but it also makes your
workflows a little bit more secure. So,
that's how you do web hooks. The last
thing I'll mention are these OpenAI and
AI nodes. Now, I'm going to have many,
many videos after this one be all about
AI agents since that's obviously the big
thing that's blowing up right now. What
I'm going to do here is I'm just going
to cover them super super briefly. I'm
not even going to like run anything, but
I just wanted to show you guys that NAN
is very AI native. And so whereas I've
been doing some very basic um OpenAI
calls with this OpenAI module, there's a
variety of things you could do. You
could create an AI agent which generates
an action plan and executes it. Uses
external tools. You can have Open AAI
message and assistant or GPT. This is
what we've been using. Some basic LLM
chains and a bunch of like specific
tools that are used to do things like
categorize information, summarize
information, and so on and so forth. AI
agent. Just to give you guys a very
brief example, probably is one of the
most intimidating looking modules or
nodes, but it's actually one of the
simplest in practice. When you create an
AI agent, it'll automatically open up
this when chat message receive node on
the side. And then you'll see that down
at the bottom of my screen, there's an
additional button that allows me to chat
with my with my model. But in order to
make this work, what we need to do is we
need to hook this up. Notice how there's
this little um warning here. What we
need to do is we need to go down to chat
model. We actually need to select the AI
module or AI node that we want the AI
service I should say that we want to
use. For most intents and purposes, I
use OpenAI. This is just the best to me.
But you could use O Lama, Mistral,
Google, Gemini, Anthropic. Feel free to
play around with this for whatever your
use case is or whatever your data
privacy security requirements are. So
I'm going go down to my Open AI chat
model. The model I'm going to be using
for this is going to be GBD40. I just
find it has better answers. And then now
you'll see that the warning sign is
gone. Now we have an additional node I
can drag and drop here. And now I can go
to chat and I could say, "Hey, how are
you doing?" We've essentially opened up
our own chat window. Hey, I'm just a
computer program, but I don't have
feelings, but I'm here and ready to
assist you. Thanks, Chat GPT. And on the
right hand side, probably the most
valuable part about this is you could
see a log of what is happening and how
many nodes were called in order to get
you the result. This is important
because the whole point of AI agents is
their ability to call other tools to do
things for you. So this says system your
helpful assistant human hey how are you
doing? This is just their prompt setup.
So the input to open AAI was this right
here. And because we just asked how it's
doing and so on and so forth um you know
it didn't it didn't really do anything
special. There were no additional tools.
This is the same thing as you just
sending a message to chat GBT
essentially. Now in order to make an AI
agent like really work you're going to
want to add two things. The first thing
you're going to want to add is you're
going to want to add some sort of
memory. If an AI agent doesn't have
memory, then basically if I go back here
to chat and then say, "What did I say in
my last
message, it will have no context or no
idea. I don't have any access to past
messages or personal data. Each session
is independent." Basically, this is like
a one it's like it's like a send a
question, receive an answer sort of
window. But we don't want that. We want
this to actually have access to our chat
history. We want it to see what we've
been talking about over the course of
the last like 20 or 30 minutes and be
able to reference those. So, there are a
variety of ways to do this. Basically,
you need to implement some sort of
database. I'll show you guys how to
implement some more complex databases in
the future, but the simplest one, the
one that Naden provides right out the
gate, the one that most people on
YouTube are going to be talking about is
this window buffer memory. Window buffer
memory basically just allows you to
store it here inside of the test window,
which is the easiest to do. And the
default is five messages. So, u
basically every time you send it a
message, it will send up to five pass
messages. But just for the purpose of
this discussion, I'm going to go 10. So
now what I'm going to do is I'll go to
chat and then I'll say hey how are you
doing and I'm going to say what did I
ask you in my previous message and
you'll see that it's asking how it's
doing right so we're actually now
accessing the previous message using
this buffer memory and on the right hand
side you'll see here that the log has
gotten a little bit more intense too so
basically we called the AI agent up at
the top the next thing that happened was
we went through the buffer memory we fed
this in and basically basically added
this to some big long stack of message
history. Then we fed that in plus the
previous message. Then we said, "Hey,
what did I ask you in my previous
message?" This is the input that is
currently being fed into the model on
that second call. And then we went down
into buffer memory. We saved all of this
again. And then uh we kind of came up
and then and sent the answer. How about
now? Cool. So now we're three levels
deep. And as you can see, this is just a
quick and easy way to load the memory.
make sure that we're always having some
sort of topical contextual conversation,
which is pretty cool. Now, the real
juice in AI agents, the reason why
they've gained so much popularity is
just because of this tool section here
where you can essentially call an action
just like we were doing before
procedurally, but you can call it using
AI and you can automatically format and
get information from different tools.
So, there are variety of tools that are
just sort of set up for you. Air table,
base row, calculator, Gmail, Google
calendar, Google Docs, Google Drive, all
this stuff.
What I'm going to do in this example,
just because I don't want to spend all
day on it um before I do my more
detailed AI agent tutorials, is I'm just
going to select Google Calendar. I'm
going to create a new credential, sign
in with my Gmail
account, and then I'll go over
here. I'll close this window. Now that
I've uh I've connected my Google
calendar agent, what I'm going to do is
I'm going to select my specific
calendar, which is nick
leftclick.ai. And then now that it's
connected to my AI agent, this is the
create event. I don't want to create, I
just want to get. So get all of my
events basically from my calendar. Okay.
And then in addition to that, what we
have to do is we have to use this dollar
sign from AI feature here. And we just
have to paste that into the expression
field. Um what this does is this just
tells AI, hey, I want you to provide uh
you know your own details for the value
of a field. In our case, I wanted to
feed in some options that say, hey, you
know, I want you to grab data that is
after this date, but before this date.
So, if I'm asking
AI like, "Hey, what's going on? Can you
tell me what I'm doing tomorrow?" And
I'll just say, "Jan 28, 2025." The whole
idea here is AI now has access to my
calendar. It also has the ability to
call that API. Then it can actually go
and retrieve specific events from my
calendar and then return them here. So,
as you can see, I have this call uh me
and my my buddy Zach. And then it just
has all of this information. Okay,
great. How are you more generally? you
know, I can also just chat with it like
I'm chatting to chat GBT or something
like that. So, I don't always have to
use like the tool that I'm I'm calling.
And the idea is you basically stack on
3, four, 5, 10, 15, 20 of these tools.
Although, I find in practice when you
get um past maybe six or seven, instead
of calling a tool, what you want to do
is you want to call another agent which
then decides to call a tool. It's
basically like a big almost like a
search tree or something. But any more
or less the AI side of things. The last
thing I'll mention here is uh this
OpenAI note doesn't just have the
message a model text action like we've
been doing before. There's a variety of
other things you could do. You can
create an assistant, delete an
assistant, list assistance, message
assistance, update assistance, analyze
images, you can generate images,
generate audio. Like you have a ton that
you could do here, which is pretty
sweet. I go down to generate audio and
I'll say um I don't know, Nick is
awesome and very pretty and I generate
it using the Nova voice. Click this test
step. Not only can I generate text and
stuff like that, but I can also have
this generate me an audio output I can
then listen to. Variety of cool things
you can do with this. Nick is awesome
and very pretty. You're damn right I am.
Um variety of cool things you can do
with this, but definitely don't sleep on
the AI nodes. Uh you know, don't just
like stick to the one that I've shown
you guys so far. Okay, great. So, those
are the foundational ones. In practice
with NAN, you're probably going to be
using these quite often. What I'll do
next is talk about some nodes that
modify flow. And here are a bunch more
that like you're going to want to read
their docs and add them to your toolkit
because this is like an everyday sort of
thing. The first is an if. The second is
filter. The third is merge. And the
fourth is split into batches. So let me
show you guys a very quick and and
simple example of the if. If I go
here and then I add my own trigger. Uh
and I just want to trigger manually. Oh,
sorry. It looks like I already have one
somewhere in here. Right. So let's just
repurpose this um manual trigger for an
example workflow that I'm going to build
down below.
this example trigger. I'm going to click
it. And then what we're going to do is
we're going to use the edit
fields. We're going to go down to JSON.
This is just a handy dandy tool that
allows you to set your own inputs and
outputs. So I can now set my own um
output. And I could say first name Nick,
last name uh Sarif. And if I if I test
this, if I test my whole workflow,
you'll see this broke because um Sarif
was not in quotes there. Got to make
sure that all of your strings are in
quotes. If I check out the JSON, you see
the output of this module is now first
name, Nick, last name, surf. Okay, I'm
just going to pin this. Now, let's say I
want to do something else, you know, if
the if the input is Nick, I want to do
something really cool. I want to provide
prize. I don't know, um,
$100. If the input is Nick, I want to go
through my my sequence and then I want
to generate another variable called
prize, and I want to I want to have it
be $100. Okay. But I only want to do
that if the input is Nick. If the output
is something else, then I want to have
my prize be just $5. So Nick gets all
the prizes here. He's very greedy. Okay.
So how do you actually implement this
sort of logic? Well, the simplest way is
if I click this plus button and I just
type if, you'll see I'll have this node
pop up that says if wrote items to
different branches, true or false. So
I'm going to add that in there. And what
I'm going to say is if first name, which
by the way, we could still just drag if
we wanted to. could say if first name is
equal to Nick then proceed through the
true node which is up here and if not
we're going to want to proceed through
this false node. Isn't that cool? So now
we basically have two things that are
occurring. Okay, prize up here was 100.
Prize down here was five. I'm going to
click test workflow. This is now going
to run and I just want you guys to see
what's happening. I clicked test
workflow. We then edited our fields. We
added Nick as the first name. We then
went to the if and then as we saw here,
first name was equal to Nick, meaning
oops, if I double click this again, the
output is now only going down the true
branch with one
item. And then the uh upper branch was
illuminated. It's green. And then that's
how we get to edit fields with the prize
equal to $100. Now, if I change this,
instead of Nick, if it's like Sally or
something, and if we run this again,
what you'll see is the
data is flowing through here cuz I
didn't unpin it. So, let's unpin it. If
we if we test this now, uh what you'll
see is the data didn't go through the
top uh route anymore. Went through the
bottom route. Okay, great. So, now with
this example here, why don't we just
pretend like we're emailing somebody.
So, I'll go draft an
email. I'm going to create my thing here
and we'll say congrats you won. Good
expression. Then what I want is dollar
sign
Jason.prise right over here. So like
congrats you won $5. How cool is that? C
title
loser. Uh okay, great. And then I'm
going to go here and I'm going to create
a
draft. Voila. I have it. Now if I go
back here to my SOS media queries page,
see it says, "Congrats, you won $5."
There's nobody to because we didn't set
the email to. But pretty neat, huh? We
gave the same thing with this $100
field. Go over here. You'll see that I
just copied like all of the same logic.
It says, "Congrats, you won Jason.
Prize." It's grayed out right now
because there's no data coming in. But
you'll see that it'll work if I change
the um input back to Nick. Then if I
test this, I'll see it'll follow the top
route and then also send me an email.
Okay, great. So now let's look to use
the filter node. Um, what I have here is
I have my little first name Nick here.
Um, what I'd like to do instead is I'd
like to just change this a little bit.
So, instead we'll create an array of
names. And inside of this, we'll have
Sally, John, and then Nick. Okay. And so
now, if we test this, we see three
entries in an array called names. We
have our top level array, which contains
an array of objects, and we have our
object. And inside of that, we have key
whose value equals a list of other
objects or an array of other objects. I
know the terminology can be kind of a
lot and unfortunately there are many
ways to refer to the same thing. So if
something doesn't make sense just bear
with me here and we'll in a moment.
Okay, great. So let's say what we want
to do if this names array includes Nick
then um I want to continue with the
flow. So I'll go array. Then what I want
is I want to see if this array of of
names feed that in here contains and I
just want to say Nick. I'm going to test
this out. What you'll see is that we've
kept it because it does in fact contain
Nick, which is pretty cool. If instead
we wanted to see if it contains Peter,
we test this. You'll notice that we are
now following the discarded route. Okay,
there's kept and then there's discarded.
The thing is um it just goes down the
same flow. Whereas if sort of split into
two, there's a true and a false route.
Uh this one actually just like continues
and proceeds down the same flow. If
something matches the filter, it will
continue. Something doesn't match or the
fil match the filter, then it won't. So,
what we could do, if I just paste in
this Gmail node, so we could basically
build uh a very similar flow, but what
we could do is if it is kept, then we
could send a prize of $100 instead. We
could hardcode that $100 in. So, I'm
going to do is I'm going to check to see
if it's kept. Okay, so right now name
contains Peter, it's probably not going
to be kept, right? So, test workflow.
It's going to stop right here. Does not
proceed any further. If instead I change
the filter so that it contains Nick,
then we test it. What we see is we're
going to move on and we're actually
going to like proceed with the rest of
our flow. So, this filter here just
allows us to kind of stop if it doesn't
match our condition or or continue. And
you can add as many conditions as you
want. You can go and or or um you can
add whatever sort of logic you'd like. I
used array logic here too, but there's
also a lot. There's like string. You
could check to see if something exists
or matches array x, number, date and
time, boolean, array, and then there's
also a bunch of object ones as well. So,
that's filter. Pretty straightforward.
But I would say the last thing is two
more. There's one called merge and then
there's split into batches. What I'm
going to do here is I'm going to have
two routes or two outputs of a module
and then I'm going to combine them back
into one. And I'll show you guys what I
mean by this. Remember earlier how we
had some HTTP requests. What I'm going
to do is I'll go first name
Sally and I'm going to
have let's just say second name.
Actually, let's
go person one. Go person two. Just for
the purpose of this example, we're going
to have two people. Person one, Sally.
Person two is Nick. Okay. Next, what
we're going to do is we're going to add
an AI node. You going to down to open
AI. And I'm just going to message a
model. Then here, I'm going to say write
a
detailed fun story about. What I'm going
to do is I'll go I don't know person
one. So, JSON.person one. This example
is sort of silly if I'm honest because
we could just hardcode the names in
there. But I just wanted to do this to
show you guys how this logic of the
merge node would work. I'm going to
select
GPT40. And then I'm, you know, because
this is just a very quick and easy
example, I'm actually going to add a
user
prompt. Okay, it's now going to go and
it's going to write me a fun story about
Jason.person one. Person one was Sally.
So, we're going to see it in a
second. Very fun. Thank you very much
for the detailed story.
Q Jeopardy
music Q other elevator
music. All right, it's taking its sweet
ass time. Could be for a variety of
reasons. I might have like a little bit
of rate limit action going on on my end
just because of all the examples that I
provided, but could also be something
else. I don't
know. Let's see
here. Okay, cool. Looks like it did once
upon a time in the vibrant city of
Elmssworth, where the streets hummed
with the rhythm of hopeful dreams and
endless possibilities. Okay, so we just
uh you know we just wrote a cool story
about Sally. What what you can do in N8
is you can actually connect the same
output to multiple um multiple future
nodes. So what I've done is I've you
know I have one over here which I'm
going to rename write story about uh
Sally. Then I have another one over here
which I'm going to say write story about
neck. Then down over here, I'm going to
say write a story about person two
instead of person one, which is, you
know, now going to equate to neck,
right? If I test the step, same thing's
going to happen. It's going to call
GPT40, it's going to write me a cool
story. The issue is if you think about
it logically, we now have two routes. We
have one top route that writes a story
about Sally, another bottom route that
writes a story about Neck. Um, so if we
wanted to do something with these
stories, like I'd kind of have to repeat
the same logic up here. Let's say I
wanted to email this to somebody. Well,
I'd have to Gmail up here. and I'll set
to Gmail down here, right? I have to
duplicate it. And it then provides a
pretty simple and easy built-in way to
avoid that. It's called the merge node.
So, you can merge data of multiple
streams once data from both is
available. So, if you just click on it,
you'll see that there's a mode append or
combine or SQL query. I'm just going to
stick with append for now. I'm just
going to feed in these
inputs. And in this way, what I can do
is I could actually just write, you
know, one Gmail node here instead of
two. Um, and maybe I could like append
both of these stories or something. But
let me actually show you um what this
looks like. Now, I'm actually going to
test this workflow from end to end. So,
you see it first does the top route and
you can see this is orange because it's
like filling out the um story about
Sally right now. This is currently
active. It's waiting to fill in the
merge the second this is finished. And I
think I probably should have set some
character limit to the story cuz now I'm
thinking about I was probably writing a
lot of my
tokens. And then after it's done with
the story about Sally, it's gonna go and
just gonna do the same thing. Write a
story about Nick. Um hopefully this
finishes before the next ice age. Okay,
that took way too long, but uh just make
sure you put in some sort of limits next
time you do one of these calls.
Otherwise, you'd be waiting here until
the end of time. However, what we see as
our final product is the top route
completed and then populated the merge
and the bottom route also completed and
populated the merge. Now we had one item
from a top route, one item from the
bottom route. Then we also carried
forward one end from the top route, one
item from the bottom route. But what
you'll see is the output of this merge
is now two items instead of one. The
reason why it's two items is because we
use the the append. So now we have uh
you know the story number one and we
have the story number two. Basically we
don't actually have to just output two
things. We could actually just output
like one item instead. Um but because in
N8 um outputs are arrays of items, you
kind of have a choice there. Now, since
we output two items, what we could do is
we could add our little Gmail node.
Stick that down here. Connect
it. Then I'm just going to pin this. And
what I could do is I could email myself
this
story. I could say story about just cuz
I back myself into a corner here. I need
to write kind of like a little bit more
difficult of a line of code. But I don't
have access
to Nick here, right? Like I don't have
access to a single variable that
contains the value that I'm looking for.
So this is person one, Sally, person
two, Nick. So I mean I could select
person one, but then my second run would
also say Nick, right? So both of these
would say story about Sally, story about
Sally, even though they'd have different
stories. So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to say I'll look at the actual
story. So I'll go
uh sorry, I'm going to go to the merge.
I'll look at the actual story here,
which now that I think about it is
actually just JSON. Then I'll go
message. I'll go content. Then if it
includes the term
Nick, then I'm just going to return
Nick. Otherwise, I'm going to return
Sally. That's how that works. So if this
contains Nick, I'll return Nick. If not,
I'll return the ter I'll ret the term
Sally. This is just a kind of a
shorthand way to use the if um else
logic. Same as what we had before. So,
I'm just going to pop this puppy
open. Um, and let me take a look at the
data. Story about Nick. Nick was an
ordinary guy with an extraordinary
dream. I wanted to become the first
person to ride a unicycle all the way
across the United States. Then Sally,
uh, Once Upon a Time in the quaint town
of Lavender Hill, I think, uh, this was
the one where I timed out or something
because of the rate limit,
unfortunately. So, it doesn't look like
it generated me anything more than Once
Upon a Time in the Quaint Town of
Lavender Hill. But, I'm sure we could.
Yeah, like I could rerun this. Let me
just make sure that the prompt is a
little bit
shorter. Less than 100 words. Let's just
do
that. And then good. Uh, awesome. We
should be good now to actually produce
this puppy. Let me just go over here and
delete
these examples that I don't need in
preparation for the next run. And cool.
We We warmed up two
Gmails. Now we have a story about Sally,
who's a curious hamster. And then I am a
curious inventor. Lovely. Wonder why uh
they use the term curious both times. H.
But anyway, I hope you guys see now that
like basically the merge connects two
things together. The if statement sort
of does the opposite. It kind of creates
two routes,
right? Yeah. This is kind of neat when
you contrast and compare them like that.
So I believe now uh we have everything
we need except for the split into
batches run. Split into batches is kind
of a a little trickier of a thing to
conceptualize. So, I'm going to show you
a real example from a source that I used
to extract a bunch of data. So, let me
take a quick peek here at
um I think I was doing depersonalization
system. Yeah. So, I created a video on a
depersonalization system a while ago and
as part of it um what I'm doing is I'm
waiting over here for data to come in
through a web hook. I send in data to
this web hook and then I use it to call
an API that gets a bunch of data set
items. The data set items are pretty
big, right? As you can see over here,
it's a bunch of data about specific
leads. But notice how it says 128 items
above, right? Anytime you output more
than one item in N8N, what you can do is
you could loop over every item. Then you
could perform something individually on
just that item. And then once you're
done with that, you could go back to the
loop over and over and over and over
again until you're completed. So in my
case, I had a lot of items in this. I
had 128 for Christ's sake, right? And
what I wanted to do is I wanted to run
my five column personalization flow
similar to what we saw earlier. And then
I also wanted to add a row to my
spreadsheet. Now unfortunately every
time I did that I consumed one API uh
call and a lot of these platforms have
pretty intense rate limits. So instead
of me um one issue I always found I
found very frequently was I just kept on
getting timed out. It would say 400
error or 403 error or whatever.
Basically, the gist of that is that, you
know, I'm over the rate limit and
they're not going to allow me to make
any more requests for a certain amount
of time. So, what I did instead is
instead of me just submitting all of
those requests simultaneously, I added
this to a loop over items and then I
added a designated weight node. The
weight node is a simple node in N that
allows you to wait for a certain number
of seconds. In my case, five. And in
this way, I was able to basically take
one item, go from start to finish, wait
5 seconds, and then loop back and then
proceed with my next item. And I
basically just went, you know, one after
the other after the other after the
other over and over and over and over
again. So that's just to give you guys
some context on on what that actually
might look like. If I go down
here and I set um my items here, I'm
just going to use a future a feature in
NAN that allows you to automatically set
like your own test data. So I'm going to
say, you know, there's there's first
item and then there's second
item and my data for that. Where is the
edit fields? Right over here.
If I zoom way in, you'll see that I'm
not outputting two items, right? So,
what I can do is I can go loop over
items, split in batches. You set the
batch size to one. What it'll do now is
it will go first item and then second
item. What I'll do is when you add a
loop over items, it immediately adds a
replace me node. And this is what you're
supposed to basically replace with the
thing you want to do. So, in my case, I
just want to wait 5 seconds. So, I'm
just going to go over here and go wait.
wait exactly five seconds. What I want
to do is for the loop route, for the
route that is going to be looping over
my items. So basically for every item,
you can think of this as I want to wait
and I want to wait 5 seconds. Very cool.
Then the output of this needs to feed
back into the input. This is kind of
like the tricky
part. So when you go through a loop, I'm
going to click a test workflow. I'm
going to generate two items and then I'm
just going to pull one item out of that
and I'm going to wait 5 seconds. I'm
going to go to the second item and I'm
going to wait 5 seconds. Is this going
to do anything? No. But notice that
there is both a loop route and then
there's a done route. Basically in NAN
once you're done with the loop route, it
just automatically goes to the done
route. So I could do something like this
and maybe I send myself an email. Let's
just
draft. And then let's say um you
know done
looping. You successfully waited 10
seconds.
Awesome. So, we're going to wait 5
seconds and then 5 seconds. Then we're
going to Gmail. Okay. So, that's that.
I'm going to test this workflow. That's
the first 5 seconds
here. And that's the second 5 seconds
here. And once this is done, we can now
send over an email draft or queue up an
email draft, I should say, which is
right over here. I should note that I
may have ran this twice. I feel like I
just ran this twice. Looks like it's
carrying all of these here. Oh, yeah.
Sorry. It'll it'll output all of the
records that you feed it in basically.
So, I fed it in two records and then the
third run it went and then fed both of
those records in as input to my Gmail
branch. Um, what I could do is I could
take these two items and I could convert
it into just one item by combining them.
Um, and then I wouldn't have to deal
with this, which is kind of neat. So,
that's probably what I would do in
practice. I wouldn't actually proceed
here with two items. I would just do
one. There's a really cool built-in way
to do this in NAN just called execute
once. So if you just go to the settings
page of any node and then just click
execute once, you basically stop the
multiple executions regardless of the
number of elements that precede it. So I
just clicked execute once and instead of
me sending two emails, now it's only
going to send one. That's run number
one. That's run number two. Then it'll
go and it'll feed one item as an output.
So if I refresh this now, instead of
two, I'm only going to have one. Quick
and easy hack. Um, and yeah, you know,
because we're building stuff live,
hopefully you guys get to see the
applications of this in real time as we
put something together. All right, so
now I think we are at the point where we
can realistically build out
substantially more complicated flows.
What I'm going to do now is basically
run almost like a test of sorts where
we're going to take all the information
that I just tried to shove into your
brain and we're going to use it to build
out a flow that actually does something
business worthwhile, a flow that I've
sold many times before and a flow that's
made people a fair amount of money. So
this is what the flow looks like right
now. I'm actually going to simplify it.
I've decided to do it a little bit
simpler just over the course of the last
like 20 minutes thinking about it. But
basically, just to keep things make a
long story short, there's this service
out there called SOS. Um, and I
mentioned this at the beginning of the
video, they send out like a a query
every day from journalists uh where the
journalists are looking for people that
match their criteria to answer
questions. So, uh, for instance, you
know, this one up here is from Jordan
Rosenfeld who's saying, "Seeking
healthcare Medicare specialist weigh on
how RFK Junior and Dr. Medat Oz might
affect benefits or healthcare if
appointed. know that this is usually
like US specific. I think they have kind
of like a like a global arm sometimes
too, but most of this is going to be USD
uh US specific. And then it says, "Hey,
um I'm looking to speak to people in a
nonpartisan way, but the possible
changes, things like Medicare,
healthcare, insurance, these are two
stories. Specify what you're commenting
on can be both. Robust and longer
answers are prioritized. You must have
the relevant experience. We'll link back
to your site. Please include pronouns."
There's a lot going on here, right?
Basically what we want to do is we just
want to take this whole long
email and we just want to extract all of
these. So this would be
one, this would be one, this would be
two, this would be three, and so on and
so forth. And we want to feed this into
AI. And we just want AI to give us a
very simple answer. Hey, is this
relevant to me based off of some
characteristics I'm going to give you?
and two, if it is, can you like
pre-draft an email for me? So, pretty
pretty simple, pretty straightforward
stuff, right? Let me show you how
straightforward this flow can be given
what you now know. And I want you to
treat this as like a test. Basically,
like you've made it this far, let's
actually see if you could build
something out that's business
worthwhile. If something that I'm saying
doesn't make sense, uh, pause the video
and look for the specific part that I've
covered the concept in, cuz that's
that's basically the purpose here. I
just want you guys to be able to
reaffirm your knowledge and show you how
now you can do something pretty cool.
Okay, so the first thing I'm going to do
is I'm just looking for a Gmail trigger
there. I'm going to select my
credential. Sorry, not create a new
credential. I'm going to select my
credential, Gmail account 3. And the way
that this module or node works is it
extracts emails from my inbox that match
my specified filters. And it does so in
the timing that I give it. So every
minute, hour, day, week, month, x,
custom, whatever. I'm just going to say
once a day for now. It's going to be
zeroth hour, zeroth minute, simple
stuff. The event I'm looking for is
message received. Then what I need to do
is I I need to add a filter down here.
And there's one called search where I
basically just look for emails from SOS.
Luckily for me, they're all formatted in
very similar ways. SOS media queries. So
if I want to get all the emails from
SOS, this is just what I do. Now I don't
just want to get any email. I just want
to get the specific email just to show
you guys what I'm working with. Later
on, we'll then um we'll separate it. So
it's just SOS media queries will work
with any of them. But for now, I just
want to grab this one. Here's what you'd
do. You just go
subject and then you'd feed this in.
This is a Gmail operator. So just use
whatever same filtering mechanism you do
for your own emails in Gmail. Uh and
just feed it in over here and it'll work
fine. Okay. Now let's test this out.
Let's grab the data. We've received a
ton of data. Uh this is an object with
11 items inside. But this simplify is
sort of working against us here. The
Gmail trigger just natively always has
simplify on. We actually want to get rid
of this. So, I'm going to go to
expression just like we know how and
press and and type in false. This is the
same, by the way, is just turning this
off. I just wanted to be clear that I
always use the expression field. And now
I'm going to get the actual data of the
email, which is way more as you can see
here. Instead of whatever it was 12 or
something, now it's or six, now it's 13.
And uh the headers object has 27 items
buried in it just in and of itself. The
thing we're looking for is this text
variable, which is the same as what we
had before. Tell friends to join source
of sources. It's always free. want to
know how to strengthen your relationship
with journalists blah blah blah. We're
then going to pin this. So now we have
access to all of this JSON in future
nodes. And I think I got lost here with
my Gmail
trigger. And now let's actually go ahead
and let's let's split this data. Let's
basically get our data so that it's just
a bunch of these. How are we going to do
this? Just think about this. We got a
bunch of text processing features
available to us. We know a little bit
about the JSON uh JavaScript and and
stuff like that. But what are some ways
we might actually realistically be able
to do this? Well, the way that I see it
is the great news about source of
sources and the previous uh service
called Haro is that they just have the
same like characters everywhere. So,
they have a bunch of stars here. Then
between every story is basically just
like these underscores. So, underscores
there, underscores there, underscores
there. So when you see a similar pattern
like this, it becomes very easy for you
to like process this in a noode tool
using a term or a function called split
where you basically just feed in a whole
big string and then you just split it
based off something that you want. So
I'm probably I'm going to probably need
to split this twice. The first thing I'm
going to do is I'm going to split based
off this up here and then is you know
there's like this top section and then
there's going to be this whole bottom
section. Then after that I'll grab the
bottom section. I'll split it based off
of uh this probably. then I'll just be
able to get like the individual
sections. If that sounds like rocket
science to you right now, don't worry.
We're going to go over here, press edit
fields. And what I'm going to want to do
is for now I'm just going to go manual
map and click add field. This allows me
to create my own variable basically
based off of um you know the the
previous module. So I'm going to type
above. Uh
actually yeah, let's let's just call
this
below. And then what I'm going to do is
I'm going to feed in where is this text.
Ah, it's right over here. We'll go to
the expression field. Then I'm just
going to type dollar sign JSON dot. And
what I want is I want text. Okay. So now
if we open up this big fat editor here,
we got all the text right here. Pretty
sweet, right? We don't want all the
text. We only want the stuff that is uh
below this line. So I'm going to copy
this. And then I'm just going to go over
here and press dot. Now we have a bunch
of functions. And I haven't covered all
these functions yet. I will in the
future videos. Um, but one of the
functions that I use all the time is
called split. Just press split. And all
we need to do now is we just need to
feed in the thing that we want to split
it by. So I'm going to feed in what I
just copied a moment ago. Okay. And now
instead of just seeing the string, we
actually see an array. And this is what
arrays look like when they're output in
um naden. It says bracket array and then
colon space. And then we actually have
the whole array here. And this array is
split based off of wherever this was. So
I think it's going to be split right
over here. The last character before it
will say information week. Okay. So we
go information week. I'm going zoom way
in. And yeah, that's what the array
looks like. We have a comma. So this
whole thing was a string. Then we have
um quotes and then a comma, a space, and
then we have another quote. And this is
the beginning of everything underneath
it, which is awesome for us. Okay, so
this is basically what we get. Um, and
now the really cool thing that allows us
to do is it allows you to pull objects
out of an array. So this is an array
with two items inside of it. The one
string that's everything above those
lines, this little star line, then
another string that's everything below
the star line. We can just go dotlast.
And now we'll just pull out the actual
string itself, which is this. All of
this. How cool. Now what else we could
do is theoretically we could just split
this again. We could split this again
and then extract everything split based
off of these characters. So I go
dotsplit feed this in. Now we have
another array, right? How many items are
in here? I don't know. Let's find out.
So I'm going to test the step. You click
on test step. And now we have a bunch of
different items. So yeah, just make sure
you like set the array um here anytime
you're screwing around with data.
Otherwise, I believe they have a field
like autotype convert or something. Um I
haven't used that one before. type
conversion errors or something. Um, I
actually just set the specific, uh, data
type that I want. In this case, I'm
creating an array. I'm splitting stuff
to turn it into array. So, uh, I'm going
to be doing so with this array drop
down. Okay, but anyway, now we have a
big array. Pretty cool,
right? And it looks like we have 19
items in total. What I want to do with
this is, first of all, I'm going to pin
this. Second of all, I'm going to go
over here to extract titles. And I'm
just going to copy this because I don't
want to have to rewrite the whole
prompt. I think that would probably take
like 15-ish minutes or so once when all
is said and done. Um, what I want to do
is I want to um grab this data which
looks just like this. And all I want to
do is I just want to feed this into AI
now. And I just want to have AI tell me,
hey, am I good? You know, if I'm good,
then go ahead and like draft an email.
If I'm not good, then um then don't. And
I know just from experience that this is
sort of split into two parts here.
So, I'm just going to copy this
over. I'm going to use it to create my
prompt. Okay. What does this prompt look
like? You're a helpful intelligent
administrative assistant. Very on brand
for me. That's a system prompt. Then,
hey, I'm a business owner specializing
in AI, automation, marketing, and
software. Then what I'm going to say is
below is an email requesting a
uh below is an email requesting let's do
an email request from a
journalist looking for a
story about sorry information about
their story.
Then just going to paste a bunch of data
in. Your task is to determine whether it
is relevant to me and if so pre-draft an
email that answers their questions using
my tone of voice and I'll say casual
Spartan. Some
information about me. I own one second
copy. Here are my
links. Then I will say
uh sorry I just got a lot going on here
because I'm piecing this together
between two different
um prompts. But anyway, some information
about me. I own one second copy a
successful AI marketing company came up.
My name is Nick Stra here. My links
don't use unless asked links and then
um below is a request by a journalist
for outreach. Write a syncing spartan
email responding to each query.
says spart an email be concise use the
following
format.
Okay. Then I will
say if it is relevant return a JSON
object as
follows.
True. Email body. Email body goes here.
If it is not
relevant, return false for relevance and
leave email body
blank. Some information about me.
Good. Use the following email format.
Email template when responding to
relevant inquiries. Cool.
Make sure to respond in
JSON. Very sweet. Okay, great. And now
all I'm going to do is I'm going to
provide as input
um the specific item that I am
referencing. So what you'll find is when
you're referencing a an array like this,
what it'll do is it'll grab the specific
item of the array. So JSON.blow0ero,
below zero. I don't actually want that.
Um what I want to do is I I basically
want to loop through this array and then
for every item I want to feed this in as
input. Um this is selecting the first
item here with the zero. Um everything
is zeroth indexed. So this is 0 1 2 3 4
and so on and so forth. Um so in order
to do that we're going to have to take
our data and do just a little bit of
pre-processing first.
Um, we're going to want to combine a
field from many items. Sorry, uh, turn a
list inside items here using the split
out node. I don't believe I talked about
split out, but rest assured, all this
does is it turns an array into a bunch
of items. So, you can run them one by
one. Okay, great. So, below, no other
fields. And now we have uh 20 items on
the right hand side. And now, basically,
we can feed in every one of those 20
items to AI.
So all I'm going to do now is I'm just
going to feed in uh this below field.
And now instead of me having to go JSON
items.0 below one below two because we
are now splitting this into a top level
uh array instead of before how it was uh
an array and then the curly bracket
below and then another um array with
like 20 records. Now it's just below
below below below below. It's going to
run basically once for every item that
we've received. So yeah, that's that.
Um, we should be able to get some JSON
here. Uh, I don't want to run it on all
20 as a test, though, cuz all we're
doing is testing. So, what I'm actually
going to do is I'm going to go in
between these and type in limit. Limit
allows us to restrict the number of
items. So, I actually only want to run
this twice to start, and I want to see
what happens. So, I'm actually going to
do this on two items. Then, we're going
to see what those two item outputs are.
And if they're good, then we'll
continue. We'll pin them and then move
on. And if not, then we won't. We'll be
able to modify them before we actually
waste 20 uh tokens worth of data. And
I'm just going to pin all the data
moving forward. And then I'm going to go
over here to limit. And then I'm just
going to press test
step. Okay. I'm going to pin this now.
So now we have the two items. So I'm
going to go over here. And then I'm
going to test this
step. Looks like we are now producing.
Uh and it looks like both of these were
false. So I'm going to want to up this
limit just a little bit. Maybe we'll try
three last items instead. We'll
overwrite the data that's pinned. We'll
pin it again. I'll go back to extract
titles. Now we're feeding in the last
three enterprise genai users. Yeah, this
is probably
me. Edge AI and stuff. Looks like they
kept their AI entries at the end, so
that makes
sense. And we're now doing three API
calls. It looks like uh there were two
TRS. So true up here, true up here. This
looks like it was just junk data. So we
could actually cut that out. Show you
how to do that later. Um but now we
actually have like emails drafted. Hey
Pam, I own one second copy accessible
blah blah blah. Here's a big answer to
all of these questions. That's pretty
cool. All we need to do now is we just
go Gmail. We draft. Oh, you know
what? Uh, we need to grab the email,
don't we? Yeah, I don't think I actually
grabbed the email address of the
person. Yes, I did not. So, let's
actually change our prompt a little bit
and let's edit it so that we actually
output the email
to. So, I'm going to go back here. I'm
actually go
um email address
um discovered or let's just go their
email. Okay, there you go. That should
probably be
sufficient. Let's actually test this one
more time. So now we should actually
extract their email address as well,
assuming the AI does what I what it's
silly human overlord tells it to
do. And now that we have the the email
um address, we'll actually be able to
like use that to feed into a draft.
Yeah, I kind of forgot about that. So
we'll go back to Gmail. I'm going to go
draft create a draft credential Gmail
account 3 resource draft operation
create. Then I'll say
re and then I'll say SOS inquiry. I'm
going go message and then all I'm going
to do is I'll go back to my schema. Just
going to drag my email body in here.
Then I'm going to add an option called
uh now we'll go to email and then we're
actually just going to feed that puppy
in there. And now we can actually test
this out on three. So let's go one, two,
three. So we have three items. All of
them just wrapped up. We go back to my
email inbox, go down to
drafts, we'll see that uh I created one
for each. It looks like I created an
additional one, but anyway, I'll cover
that in a second. The first was this one
to this lovely Pam lady. Very nice.
Second was this other one to this lovely
John
fella. Very cool. Uh, everybody followed
my email template. No issues. And then,
yeah, looks like we just used one
additional um
email. I think the reason why we sent
that additional email is because we
technically outputed an item. So, I
wonder if we could just not output an
item. That'd be one way to do
[Music]
it. Yeah, we could just not output the
item. Or, you know, we could just add a
filter like I uh was showing us how to
do so
before. So, if uh let's just go down
here. Let's go JSON dot
Let's go item
three. We'll go down to
[Music]
JSON.relevance
message.content.relevance. So basically
if this is equal to true then we'll
continue and then if not we won't. So we
should get two, right? Yeah, there you
go. We uh kept two items and now we're
only going to be sending emails on the
two items that passed our filter. So,
just because I always like to do an end
toend flow, I'm just going to discard
some old drafts here, delete everything,
and then run this one final
time just to show you guys what all this
looks like. We will use the Gmail
trigger, edit the fields, split them
out. I'm going to have the limit be
three items just for now because I don't
want to like draft a bunch of emails.
Extract the titles, add a filter, and
then create three drafts. Let's run this
from start to finish. We're now
extracting the titles. And by sorry
extracting the titles I mean we are um
filtering and creating an email. And
then the end result is we have two
drafts in our inbox which is kind of
neat. And if we wanted to take this even
further what we could do is we go down
to Gmail and then we could add a label
to this message. Just to make it
abundantly clear if I select the message
ID that we just created. It's going to
be right over
here. Uh I could just call this public
relations or something. And
now basically it'll just automatically
apply a label to these drafts inside of
my inbox that I just know that these
are, you know, these are public
relations inquiries basically. Um these
are not, you know, other email drafts
for some purpose. And that's kind of
cool of a flow, but I'm actually just
going to stick that right over there.
And then because I'm already getting
mixed up with the extract titles, I'm
just going to say filter and respond to
email or maybe create email body. There
you go. A little bit simpler. So yeah,
we used a ton of new functions here. Um,
we use the split. I then use the split
out. Uh, I don't actually use all of
these super often. We did use the
filter, which I talked about and
covered. And then the limit is just
basically like an internal tool that I
like to use to uh make sure that I'm not
screwing around with token usage or
spending a ton of like executions or
anything like that. Um, I think this
system is a lot cleaner than that other
system that I was going to build with
you guys before. It's also a little bit
more simple. Here I have just a ton of
code unfortunately, but we'll get rid of
that. We'll use this as the two
templates for us. Then I'll also just
make this nice and easy to see. And
yeah, I hope you guys appreciated this.
Um, just so that we could do a quick
recap and because in my experience doing
a recap of the stuff is sort of how you
remember it. Um, we started off by
talking a little bit about fields
specifically two types of fields. There
were fixed fields and then there were
um, expressionbased fields. I sort of
made a case for you as to why you should
probably favor expressionbased fields
over fixed fields whenever possible
because you could do the exact same
thing anyway. And you also just get like
a ton of code options. So I always just
toggle little expression. I then showed
you how all of these different field
inputs, even like the little toggle
buttons, these really are just
expressions at the end of the day. You
know, if it's a toggle button, it's true
or false. If you're selecting a Google
sheet or something, there's actually an
ID behind it. And so now you know a lot
more about sort of the underlying data
and the way that NAN structure stuff. I
then covered JSON JavaScript object
notation in probably pretty excruciating
detail. Hopefully that wasn't too
boring. But we covered a bunch of
different variable types. Just to recap
them, there was a string, there was a
number, there was a bool or boolean,
true or false. There was an array, and
then there was also another object. So
you could bury JavaScript objects inside
of JavaScript objects. There were key
names, values. We learned a little bit
about the formatting with quotes, um, as
well as commas and and brackets and that
sort of stuff. But the reality is if you
just like stare at JSON long enough,
kind of give it a good squint or two,
eventually it'll start making sense. And
that's why I've now changed all of the
input and outputs inside of our NAND
course tutorial to to favor a JSON
JavaScript object just so you guys could
see it and kind of get used to it. From
there, we covered a little bit about how
data is represented in NAN. So
specifically, all data, all inputs and
outputs in NAD are structured as an
array of objects. So there's some top
level square bracket and inside there's
just a bunch of those JavaScript objects
nestled in it. And if you want to
reference the most previous node, then
all you need to do is just use this
little dollar sign JS O N syntax. If you
want to reference nodes from 2, 3, four,
or nodes back, n standing for whatever
number, then you would do the dollar
sign, but then you'd have to like
specifically reference the name of the
node. No big deal. Naden actually does a
lot of that selection for you. And
there's usually a little drop down or
toggle button that you can just click to
get there. We talked about how to
reference earlier fields, how to do some
backtracking with like dot notation and
square bracket notation. Then I also
covered some common gotchas. The most
common gotch in NAN, just to be clear,
is people don't understand that it is an
array of objects that you're referring
to. And so NAD will run once per item in
the array. If you're trying to reference
one item, but you're really referencing
all of them, obviously you're going to
get an error message. It's not going to
work. Likewise, if you're trying to
reference a number of items, but you
only reference some subset of them,
you're going to have some error, a
message, and you know, you're going to
get that dreadful red text that I think
we all hate so much. So, understanding
that everything is just an array of
items and array of objects. This goes a
long way towards insulating you against
that. Finally, we covered some
foundational notes. We started off with
the HTTP request node, which allows us
to basically request or do the same
thing that your browser is doing when
you access a website, pull all of the
code, and then I also showed you guys
how to do cool stuff with AI, where you
take the extracted or parsed components
of that node, like my leftclick website,
and then turn that into some sort of AI
structured data, like a summary, like
some interesting tidbits about that
website, maybe the contact details if
you could find it. I then covered a
little bit about web hooks. If you guys
are familiar, if you guys remember, web
hooks are just like the glue that holds
so much of the internet together. I
showed you guys how to send a request
from one workflow and receive it in
another workflow. And I also showed you
guys how to use a third party platform,
in this case, ClickUp, but you can
really use whatever the hell you want to
send a request upon some triggers. So
now I'm like connecting NAN and ClickUp
with my own native integration without
even necessarily having to know too much
code. And then at the tail end there, I
covered OpenAI and AI agent nodes. The
real value of N8N in comparison to most
other no code tools in addition to its
ability to self-host is their AI agent
functionality that just works fresh out
of the box. So rest assured, we're going
to be covering a lot more of that moving
forward. But we built a very simple
example where I essentially asked my AI
agent what was going on for the day and
then it pulled data from my calendar
intelligently while also still being
able to like talk back and forth in
natural language. We covered some nodes
that modify flows as well, including the
if, the filter, the merge, the split
into batches or bundles. We covered the
split out and then finally we also
covered while I was building that last
example the limit. And then from there I
showed you guys how to build a super
simple and easy essentially email
autoresponder type flow but one that
does a very high leverage highv value
business purpose which is parsing out
defining whether a journalist inquiry is
relevant to us or not than if it is
actually writing out an example based
off of a template. Okay. So now that you
understand how data works in NAD and how
information flows through a workflow,
let's cover some of the more complex
aspects of NADN. And these are parts of
nodn that usually keep beginners away
from this tool. What I'm covering now is
JavaScript functions. N uses a very
specific take on JavaScript functions,
dot notation, JavaScript functions. And
there's just so many of them that it's
very difficult and intimidating for
beginners to know which is the right one
to use. And that's what we're going to
cover over the course the next hour or
so. You're going to learn how to
transform data, how to filter it, how to
map it, how to reduce it. And if none of
these concepts make sense to you right
now, they certainly will in a few
minutes. Okay, let's get building. I
have an NAN workflow open over here
called all NAT functions. I'm going to
click add tag and go down to NAD course
just so I can help organize it a little
bit. And all we have is we have a start
node. This begins a flow when I click
test workflow down here. So I give this
a click. You'll see that this just
turned green. This just tells us that
this has triggered the flow. Uh
peculiarity of the start node is when
you click it and when you get it going,
it doesn't actually output any data. It
just starts the flow. So obviously if we
want to do something here, we're going
to have to add another node. So, let me
click on that right little plus sign.
And then the nodes that we're going to
be using in this video, I'm going to be
using pretty gratuitously. They're
called the edit fields node. And the
edit fields node, for anybody that's
coming from maybe a different noode
editor, especially something like
make.com, you can just think of this as
a way to set variables, rename fields,
and that sort of stuff. So, I'll go down
to edit fields over here. Give us a
click. And now, you know, we have the
start node on the left, and that's the
input. And then in the middle here, we
have an edit fields node with a couple
of different modes. There's manual
mapping and there's JSON. Basically,
what this allows you to do is if you
give this a click, you can define your
own variables
here. And if I click test step, you'll
see that we now have a new variable
accessible to us in the output called
hello world. Now, what I'm going to be
doing is I'm going to be using the JSON
option here. And I've already created a
bunch of JavaScript um that I'm just
going to be using for the purposes of
running through all the functions. So,
this is what the object looks like. We
have a string called hello, number 3.5,
an array with names of Sarah, Sally, and
Stephanie, an object, and this object
has some parameters like first name,
last name, height, and centimeters. Then
we also have a bool that stands for
boolean, and that's just set to true.
I'm doing this because these are all of
the different function types that we're
going to be working through in the rest
of this video. And so I just wanted an
easily accessible way for us to get all
of these and then do cool stuff with it.
I can now add, let's just give this a
quick rename. Let's just say set example
JSON. Then what I'm going to do is I'm
going to go and do another edit fields.
And this edit fields is where I'm
actually going to be mapping the output.
So I'm going to call this output. And
then for now we'll go off of a string
data type. And what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to drag this string into
the value. And now we have access to it.
Now, the way you use functions in NAND,
as I'm sure you're probably already
aware, but just to reiterate, is all you
do after you've selected a variable from
an input and it's turned green, like
this one here, all you need to do is
just click the dot. A period then opens
up this function editor. And now we have
access to tons of stuff. So, you can see
there's some suggested functions here.
This is just because while Anaden gives
you a large library of functions that
you can do stuff with um in practice you
don't actually end up using the majority
of them. But I'm still going to run you
through every single one of these for
completeness's sake and then if I touch
on something that I actually use pretty
often either for my own workflows or uh
workflows that I've seen other people
use then I'm going to I'm going to
mention it. Okay, great. So let's start
with the very first one. Now if you
remember if I click back here this turns
green and we see a result down here to
hello. If you remember the value of this
string right now is currently hello.
Okay, so keeping that in our minds, what
we start with is the includes function.
The way that the includes function works
is basically we can use this to search
within a string to see if something
includes a substring that we're looking
for. So right now we have hello and what
we're basically saying is does hello
include what I'm about to write inside
of here. So if I write h the result will
be true. But if I write something like
x, you'll see the result will change to
false. Keep an eye on this result panel
because this is going to be your best
friend anytime you're manipulating
functions. Uh because most of the time
it'll give you some sort of real time uh
feedback. So you know if I wanted to see
whether or not my string contains the
word hell. I don't know maybe I am very
pious or something. I type helen here.
You see h e l l is a four-letter
substring that is inside of hello.
Obviously this is going to turn true.
But if I were to jumble up the letters,
right? vertigo l e h you'll see that
this is false because this is reading
all strings left to right. So this is a
pretty quick and easy one. Um you know
it's kind of useful to see whether or
not something includes obviously if you
have a very large string you can
instantly do this just to search and see
whether or not that string includes just
some tiny little thing that you're
looking for a mention of something
perhaps. The next one I'm going to cover
is called split. Now split is something
that I use basically all the time. I use
it at least once a day. Um, and I use it
across a variety of no code tools just
because it's so goddang useful. Now, the
way that split works is you essentially
take your string h l exclamation point
in this case and then you convert it
into an array. And the way that you do
so is you give it a character that you
want to split the thing by. So, let me
give you a very simple example. If our
input string is h e l o, let's
hypothetically say I wanted to split
this into two halves. And the way that I
wanted to split it was based off of the
presence of the L and the L here. Okay.
So, what I could do is I could say
JSON.string.split and then in quotes and
you have to use quote signs. If I go LL,
you'll see that I've now split this
string into two um substrings basically
and then plopped them in an array. Now,
if you're unfamiliar with what an array
is or how an array works, that's okay.
We'll get into that later. But for now,
all you need to know is that we
basically taken one input and we've
turned it into an array that contains
two outputs, the H E and the O. If you
split it based off of the presence of an
L, you'll see that we are now generating
an empty space. Why? Well, this is sort
of nuanced, but if you look at our input
over here, that's H E L L. If we're
splitting based off of an L, and what
this is doing is it's catching the empty
string in between these two L's. So
hypothetically, if I wanted to split
this by something else, let's say the E,
you see that this is now splitting into
a substring that's H and then LL O. If
you wanted to do this based off of the
presence of nothing, you'll see that it
splits it based off every character. So
this is just its default um if you don't
feed it in any input whatsoever. So if
you have an empty string like this, it's
h e l l o exclamation point. And
splitting is really useful just as a
quick and easy way to take something,
usually some sort of tabular or CSV
data, and then just turn it into, you
know, an array that you can use naden
for. So, let me give you a quick little
example. Right now, this editor is set
to dollar sign JSON.string. We're
referencing a variable from a previous
um, you know, uh, node. There's actually
a little hack in Naden that you can do.
If you want to like create something
directly in the function editor to do so
with a string, all you do is you add
quotes and then you do something like
Sarah,
Sally, Stephanie. Everything within
these two quotes still technically
counts as a string. And so you can
dotindex it. You can slice it into uh
you can use dot notation, I should say,
in order to attach a function to the end
of it. So hypothetically, let's say we
had three names here and these three
names were just somewhere, I don't know,
they're in some data source that we're
scraping. Well, we can turn this into an
array very easily just by adding the
delimiter of comma and then space. Now,
because we're going comma and then
space, as you can see, we've turned this
string of Sarah, Sally, and Stephanie
into an array. That's a quick example of
split. Split's pretty awesome. I use
split all the time because we just
deleted all of this. We need to reselect
our string. So, I'm going to go dollar
sign JSON. Then, I'm going to go dot st
i n g. That's the name of the key in our
JSON that we fed. And so now we have the
hello again. Let's proceed. Next we have
starts with. Starts with is kind of what
it sounds like. If you want to see
whether or not a string starts with a uh
series of of letters or not necessarily
letters, numbers and stuff like that as
well, characters I should say, then you
can just use starts with. So in our
case, if we wanted to see whether it
started with h e l or something like
that, then this would return true. But
if we wanted to instead uh I don't know
let's say we wanted to see if the string
started with the term by then it would
obviously be false. Similarly to starts
with as you could see we also have ends
with and so the way that this works is
very similarly essentially all we're
doing is we're starting at the back and
we're just working our way forward. So
if the hello exclamation point string
sorry getting a call there um but it
looks like it went to voicemail. If the
hello exclamation point string is, I
don't know, exclamation point, this is
obviously going to be true, right? But
if it's a dollar sign, it's going to be
false because we don't have a dollar
sign present in our string. If we were
instead to go e l, this would again
revert to true. So, lots of options
there. And there are a lot of uh
functions in reality that you'll find
are just the inverse of each other. So,
if there's something for starts with,
odds are there's something that ends
with. There's something for uppercase,
odds are there's something for lowerase.
We're going to cover all of that over
the course of the rest of the video.
Okay, great. There's also this other
function here which I find myself using
quite often. It's called replace all.
And so replace all sort of a power
function. Basically what it allows you
to do is allows you to take this string
which we have here is hello exclamation
point and we can just replace any
character we want in there with another
character. So let's say we're some crazy
anime weeaboo. What we do is we
replace the first letter L and we go
comma and we replace it with W. What
we're doing now is replacing all of the
L's in the string of hello with a bunch
of W's, hello. Right? So we have a lot
of um you know granularity and control
there. If you look over the expression
and function uh documentation over here,
you'll see that this is the first
instance in which we're now splitting
this into two parts. So you know we
actually have two variables that we're
feeding into the replace all function.
There's a pattern aka what we're looking
to replace and then the actual thing
that we're going to be using to replace
it. I could just as easily replace the
term the O, right, with nothing. And if
I do that, it actually just cuts it out.
Just removes that character completely.
So replace all is pretty powerful. I
find myself using this all the time when
I'm developing flows. Um, and I'm glad
that it's in the suggested editor up
here alongside with split cuz you know,
these are the two most common ones
realistically. Okay, great. Moving our
way down, you'll see that there's a very
interesting looking function. This
technically isn't a function. I believe
this is a parameter in JavaScript. Uh,
you know, like technically speaking,
that's why it doesn't have the two
little brackets next to it. But this is
just a quick and easy way to determine
the length of a string. So you know if h
e l l o exclamation point this is 1 2 3
4 5 6 right we should expect this to say
six that's exactly what happens when we
feed in length hypothetically if I were
to replace this with hey how's it going
men you'll see that the character length
of this string is now 24 so uh length is
super valuable I use length all the time
I use length to determine you know
whether or not the input that I'm
feeding into a large language model is
too much right a lot of the time you can
average out the token length of a big
string just by multiplying the number of
um characters per word on average. And
if you look up number of characters per
word, the average is 4.7. Uh and then if
you want to get the number of tokens per
word average, you'll see that that's uh
something like 2 to three. A paragraph
is 128 tokens. I guess I should have
said number of words per token. This
ends up being about um 0.75. So, from
there, if you feed in a string of 1,000
uh characters, right? Uh what was the
the math there? 4.7 or something, I
believe. Yeah, 4.7. So, 1,000 characters
divided by 4.7 is 212 words. 212
words* 1 / 0.75 gives us 282 tokens. You
know, odds are if you do this
calculation and you get the length of
your your string, you're going to know
that every time you call a large
language model, you're going to be using
282 on average over a large uh enough
data set,
282.6 tokens in order to do so. So, you
know, if you're not working with large
language models, maybe a little bit less
applicable, but there's still a variety
of reasons why you might want to use
length. So, um yeah, length is
definitely one of the big boys. Okay, so
working our way down the function panel
here, uh, we have B 64 decode and it's
partner B 64 encode. Now, if you guys
aren't familiar with what B 64 is, you
can think of it in a really simplified
way. It's just a slightly different
alphabet used to represent strings. Um,
if I were to zoom into this example, the
letters H E L L O when they are base 64
encoded translate to A, capital G,
capital V, SB, capital G8, and then
little equal sign. So this is basically
just a way to to like uh I don't know
like rotate characters according to some
formula this base 64 um function. And
the reason why they have a function
available is because a lot of servers
and uh some web services will only
accept base 64 encoded versions of the
strings that you send them. This is both
a security purpose and I believe there's
also some sort of compression purpose as
well. Um but to keep things really
simple, we'll start with B 64 encode.
Then I'm going to feed in the thing that
we just B 64 encoded into a B 64 decoder
just so you can see that they're the
same thing. Okay. So if I were to attach
B 64 encode over to the string H E L O
exclamation point, you'll see that it's
very similar to the string that I just
showed you guys um without the
exclamation point. The only difference
is the last letter I think is an h or
something like that instead of an an
equal sign. So as you can see it's very
similar. Now, if I were to take this
string and then I were to attach another
function to it,
base 64 decode. Notice how we've
basically just regenerated our initial
hello string. We could do this an
arbitrary number of times. I go back to
base 64 encode, then base 64 decode. And
hypothetically, we could make this
thing, you know, the distance from here
to Mars. Um, but as I'm sure you guys
can guess, it's kind of pointless to do
so. So, this is sort of a niche
function. I do use that function. Uh, I
use one of the two functions reasonably
often when I'm doing certain API calls
because sometimes you need to base 64
encode an API key or base 64 encode
credentials, usernames, passwords, that
sort of thing. The only thing I want you
guys to take away from this if you're
unfamiliar with it is next time you know
a service says, "Oh, you'll need to base
64 encode a string." Well, now you know.
All you need to do is just go to your
string, press period, and then type in B
64 encode. Voila, you're done.
Okay, continuing on down, we now get to
another function that I use reasonably
often, one called concat. Concat
basically just allows you to take your
string and then add on another string to
it. Kind of think of this as like a
string addition, right? You're like
manipulating the string. You're sticking
two strings together. So, if I were to
press enter here, go to concat, and then
inside of quotes, I were to say space
world, you can see here that my string
has now changed from hello exclamation
point to hello exclamation point space
world exclamation point. right? The
cardinal example of um you know you
doing something cool with a computer for
the first time. Now I should note that
you can also feed in uh more than one
string. So you could actually feed in an
array of strings. That's why the
concatenate function is kind of cool. So
I could technically feed in world and
then I could go how are
you? And then you'll see that you know
we've now taken um three strings. We've
stuck them all together. The first was
hello, the second was world. The third
was how are you right? The next series
of functions I use all the time and
they're the extract functions for
strings. So we have four. Extract
domain, extract email, extract URL, and
then extract URL paths. And basically
the way that this works is this is just
something that allows you to pull out a
domain name from a string that you
supply that might include it. You can
pull out like email addresses. You can
pull out the whole URL instead of just a
domain. Or you can pull out everything
after the backslash at the end. I'll
show you what I mean by all this uh
right now. So I'm going to use extract
domain first. The way that extract
domain works is you either feed in a URL
or you feed in a believe like an email
and it'll basically tell you what the
domain is. Obviously, you know, this
isn't rocket science. If I delete the
hello string here, because this doesn't
actually have any domain inside of it,
which is why it's returning undefined.
If I were instead to type something like
Nick at leftclick.ai, you'll see that
extract domain extracts
leftclick.ai. Okay. Uh, conversely, if
you were to just go leftclick.ai, it
would remain the same. If you were to go
https back/backslash, it would only
extract the leftclick.ai portion. And
there are variety of instances in which
this is useful. Um, you know, a lot of
the time when I'm web scraping for
either myself, you know, people pay me
to build a web scraper for them, or if
I'm doing it for one of my businesses,
you know, a lot of the time I'm scraping
the web for strings using a regular
expression that follow a certain
pattern. Maybe something like this.
Well, this is just a quick and easy way
where I could feed those strings in and
then it could extract the the domain
name because domain names and URLs are a
little bit different. And a lot of the
time you need a domain name for
something that you don't necessarily
need a URL for. So that's just a quick
example of something that allows you to
extract. If I were to add um some spaces
over here though, you'll see that it it
breaks. So this does not work if you
feed in like multiple or something like
that. It's only really going to work if
you feed in one and then you just want
to extract a portion of it. But this is,
you know, comparable to you slicing the
string in halves. instead of you having
to do some sort of fixed type of data
processing where like you're looking for
the string that occurs after the second
backslash, you know, you can just put
extract domain in there and it'll
basically just always get you exactly
what you want whether or not there are,
you know, threeletter tople domain
endings or twolet like I have over here,
right? So very flexible, very nice. The
second function that I'm going to show
you is called extract email. So as I'm
sure you guys can imagine, if you feed
an email into this, it will return with
said email. If I go back to that other
example and go nickleclick.ai AI. As we
see here, we're now extracting Nick at
leftclick.ai. You know what's pretty
cool? If I add a bunch of other text
here to the beginning and then to the
end. This is different than the extract
domain. Unfortunately, the documentation
is pretty poor. But if I feed in a bunch
of additional information, let's say I
scraped a website and we just have tons
of text. And then just somewhere in this
text, there's one little line that says
Nick leftclick.ai. Okay, one tiny little
line. This will extract and pull out the
nick at leftclick.ai based off of like
an email formatting mechanism. um
whereby it looks for a little string and
then it looks for some at symbol and
then it looks for some domain ending. So
that's really really useful. You can use
this just as your email extractor. You
know, you are going on a website or
something like that. You feed in the
entire string of the scraped website to
this function and then it just pulls out
the email addresses for you. I think you
guys could probably come up with a
million use cases for something like
that. Okay, let me just put this back in
here cuz I hate when it screams at me
with red. And we're going to move on to
the next function which is extract URL.
So similarly, the way the URL works is
uh a little bit differently from extract
domain. In case you guys weren't aware,
this is the domain name right over here,
but this is the URL. So the URL tends to
have some sort of I think this is just
the protocol. Then you have some
standardized delimiter which is usually
this colon and then these two
backslashes and then you have the domain
name. Okay, that's how that works. So uh
this will actually extract a URL based
off of the presence of this. Now, if I
take out the P, right, it's going to
break because there is no protocol
called
HTTS. But I could take out the S and
that would work cuz there is a protocol
called HTTP. I'm unsure if FTP works.
Yes, FTP works. Um, does SSL work? No.
Um, SSH, sorry. Uh, no. Anyway, there
variety of these protocols. Feel free to
look them up if you guys are curious
what sort of URL protocols there are and
sort of like URL structures. But yeah,
this is just a quick and easy way to get
the whole URL, which can be very useful.
And then from here, what I want to do is
show you the last one, which is called
extract URL path. And the way that
extract URL path works is as opposed to
getting the URL itself, which is
everything sort of if I put a slash
here, it's everything before this line
in like the HTTP protocol, they call
everything after this first slash the
path. And a lot of the time websites and
services and stuff like that, they'll
actually store a ton of important
information after that backslash. If I
show you guys what this looks like on NN
in particular, you'll see that this is
my cloud account. So if I were just make
this practical, this is the URL right
over here. It's https
back/nixerive.app.n.cloud. Okay, this is
like the the root part of the URL. This
is the protocol. This is the domain
name. And then this over here is a URL
path called workflow slash and then I
have the ID of my particular workflow
that end uses to grab data from its
server and then display it to me. So, if
I wanted to extract this URL path, if I
just feed in this whole thing, just as
an example and replace my little
leftclick.ai example, you'll see that
what results when I extract the URL path
is basically it goes to this backslash
and then it gives me the backslash plus
the term afterwards workflow plus
everything after um you know the next
slash. And the way that URLs work is you
can go arbitrarily deep over here. Okay,
if we continue down the function list,
the next one up is called hash. Now, if
you're unfamiliar what a hash is, a hash
is basically like a mathematical
algorithm applied to a string that
converts it into just some big long
number. The confusion with hash tends to
be that the number that it generates has
letters in it. So, if I take this string
https
back/back/nix.app.cloud, if I take this
here, then if I hash it according to
their default algorithm, which I believe
is MD5, you can see we get this long
result here. And the reason why a lot of
people don't understand these hashes and
you know they're so scary is just
because this isn't actually like a
string. This is a number um in something
called hexadimal. Hexadesimal is just
another number system where instead of
it going up to 10, it goes 0 1 2 3 4 5 6
7 9 8 9 and then it goes a b cde e and
f. You know how binary is zero and one?
Well there's technically a bunch of
different number formats. There's binary
which is 0 and 1. I think there's
quadinary which is 0 1 2 and 3. Um you
know there are a bunch of other ones
right there's like a number system based
off five number system based on 6 7 8 9.
Our number system just tends to be based
off of 10. That's why it's 0 through 9.
But this hexadimal is a number system
based off 16. And the thing is we just
don't have any other characters that we
can use. So uh or I don't know it just
wasn't convenient to invent new
characters for the 10th thing, the 11th
thing, the 12th thing, the 13th thing,
the 14th thing, the 15th thing. So what
uh computer programmers or scientists
the people that developed this um you
know standardized format did is they
just decided to use the letters A B CDE
E and F. So you can think of it as this
uh you know the number three corresponds
to the number three. Um A corresponds to
the number 10. B corresponds to the
number 11. C is 12, D is 13, 14, and
then this is 15. And the reason why it
stops as 15 is because we start from
zero. So 0 to 15 is technically 16
different numbers. So you know this is
one of the main issues with people in
hashing I find you know the hexodimal
doesn't really explain super easily u
but essentially all all that a hash does
is a hash is just like an algorithm that
takes a string. So if we just go hello
instead of this takes a string and then
just performs a bunch of mathematical
manipulations on the value of h which I
don't know might be 85 or something
whatever the the computer programmers
that came up with the standard for the
the numerical value of every letter is
and then it turns it into something that
is just not easily interpretable by by
humans. Um the benefit of having a hash
is you can then de de hash this and then
you can regenerate this from you know
this
5D4142 back into hello and what you find
hashes commonly used for as I'm sure
you're aware are security applications.
So things like hashing a password for
instance there's this big common saying
in any sort of computer security and
that's never store passwords in plain
text. The alternative to plain text is
hashing the password in some way. So I'm
not going to go too much into this as
I'm sure you can imagine it's very niche
and this doesn't really make you money
to be honest. I mean like you know if
you in some computer security thing
possibly but there are some values you
can feed this and the only real values
that matter here are MD5 base 64 SHA1
SHA224 SHA 256 Shaw 384 Shaw 512 Shaw 3
RIPE MD160 these are all just different
algorithms so if the default is MD5 if I
were to go instead and go base 64 you'll
see that we've now basically done the
same thing that we did with the base 64
encode function right but uh if instead
we want to do Shaw 1 or something you
know we get shot 224, um, shot 256, shot
512. These tend to get longer and longer
and longer the higher the the SHA number
thing at the end, just because this
basically represents more and more
complexity. So, I'm going to leave it at
that, but just know that there are going
to be a couple of instances that may ask
you for hashing on some point in the
future, but as somebody that's made tons
of money with no code platforms, uh, you
know, I don't know, in like over a 100
projects, I've had maybe one uh require
me to hash something, and that was just
really briefly for like one tiny
section. Okay, the next function I want
to run you guys through is one called
quote. It is similar in hash in so far
that I don't use it a lot. Um, all quote
really does uh from a bird's eye
perspective is just wraps your thing
around um your your string in quotes,
right? So, if I just remove this, you'll
see that it is now hello. And if I go
back, it now wraps it in these these
quote signs. But quote can actually do a
lot more than that. It's actually kind
of useful when you start getting into
sending and receiving data through um
you know HTTP requests or web hooks just
because a lot of time you have to
sanitize the data that's being sent. Let
me show you guys a quick example. So, if
there's one thing that you guys might
not know, um, you know how earlier we
defined a string with these two double
quotes and then I, you know, wrote it
down over
here. Okay. Um, well, hypothetically,
let's say somewhere in my string I
wanted to use another quote. What
happens if I try and do this? Well, this
breaks the whole string, right? And the
reason why is because there's just some
built-in logic in string parsers. Parser
is just the thing that determines
whether or not it's a string. But
there's some built-in logic in string
parsers that sees this quote, then it
sees this one and says, "Oh, this must
be the string." Then it sees that one
and then that one and goes like, "Oh,
no, no, no. This must be the string."
Then it sees that one and that one. It's
like, "No, no, no. This must be the
string." Well, how many strings are
there? I can't do this. And then it just
quits. So, there are a couple
workarounds uh when you're using quotes
inside of a string. The first is instead
of wrapping in double quotes, what we do
is we just wrap it in single quotes. And
the second you do that, like this
technically, this this is now
technically a valid string again. But
you'll see, you know, if I just go back
here, you'll see that if I try and add
quotes inside of this now with this
quote function, um, something really
interesting happens. And basically what
happens is this this feature called
escaping. So a lot of the time in order
to prevent this exact issue that I was
talking about from occurring, what you
can do is you can escape a quote sign,
which is um, you can proceed it with
this like reverse backslash character.
What this reverse backslash character
does is this just like cancels out.
Actually, is this a backslash? I don't
know. was a reverse backslash or a
forward slash. Anyway,
um that's funny. I've probably been
calling one the other my entire life,
but hey, might as well have that
realization during filming of a YouTube
video, right? So, uh the way that this
works is we are escaping this character
with this backslash with this slash
character. I'm just going to use slash
to like keep my sanity. And then because
we have this slash in front of it, um,
basically all string parsers and
formatterers will will take a look at
this and say, "Oh, okay. I can actually
ignore the formatting of what happens
next." So, let me show you guys an
example using what I did earlier. You
see how it says Nick says hi. Well, if I
actually put a slash here and then a
slash here, it's now like an acceptable
string, right? But I have to do that
manually every time, right? This is kind
of annoying. Anytime I'm I'm I'm writing
or adding something and I basically have
to go find all the quotes and replace
them. Well, guess what? That's what our
quote uh function over here does. It
just does all that automatically for us.
So, if you wrap the outside with the
single quotes instead, then I remove
this
uh like this, you'll see that it's
actually gone through and it's added in
the the the slashes for us. Um so, this
is just a form of I don't want to say
niche because this can be quite often,
you know, used in quite often in many
applications depending on what you like.
Um it says up here it's useful when
constructing JSON SQL. These are all uh
you know formatting conventions for
sending and receiving data over the
internet. But this this allows you to do
that. This has one parameter. It's the
mark. So you can u actually select the
quotation mark that you want to cancel
it out with, which is pretty neat. So uh
if you want to wrap something, let's
just go back to our hello example. If
you want to wrap this in different
quotes, then you could go single quotes
like this. You could also just create
whatever quote you want. So
hypothetically, let's say that the I
don't know the underscore is my new
quote character. Well, I can just um
have that wrap everything. Okay, let's
cover the next string function. As you
can see, we are making some good time.
The next one here is one called remove
markdown. Now, markdown is another
example of a formatting convention. And
you'll see that this is in large part
what string manipulations are for. They
take some formatting convention and they
just fix it for you. So, the way that
markdown works, and this is kind of
beyond the purpose of this discussion,
uh let's just look this up really
quickly. There's some basic syntax guide
here. Feel free to check this out if you
want. But this is very commonly used
when you are calling um large language
models and open AAI and claude and these
various services to turn text um so that
it's not just plain text but actually
has some sort of formatting. So here's
markdown on the left. Markdown. If you
want to like create a header, what you
do is you add a dollar sign, dollar
sign. You add a number sign and then a
space and then the header. If you want
to do like an H2, you go two
H3. They show us what it looks like in
HTML as well, which is another markup or
rendering language over here. And you
can see that, you know, if you want to
do the equivalent thing for markdown in
HTML, you need to wrap this in some H1
tags. Markdown's a little bit more
efficient. As you can see, the total
number of characters used to represent
the same information was just two here
instead of 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9. And so
when you communicate with large language
models, you know, obviously the main
benefit there is the fewer tokens, the
fewer characters, the less money you
tend to be built, especially with these
bigger APIs. So that's why everybody
just tends towards markdown in order to
get rendered outputs like this. So all
that function that remove markdown does
is hypothetically if I go back to
creating my own string again and then I
were to say heading one, you'll see that
this just takes out the markdown
formatting. It has a built-in parser
again that looks specifically for
instances of these number signs for
headings. If I were to add 2 3 4 5 6 7
8, you know, as you can see, nothing
really changes here. You know, it does
add a space, which is interesting, but I
don't believe it adds a space um on
anything up to six. Yeah. So anything up
to and including six doesn't add a
space. It does on seven. Why? cuz this
is no longer considered um like uh like
there is no heading seven hypothetically
and so now it says okay this just must
be like a bunch of bogus markdown um
number symbol stuff so this must
actually be a real character we're going
to render the space peculiarities of
markdown aren't super important just
know that you can remove it all with
something like this if you want
similarly there's also a function called
remove tags which works as I'm sure you
can imagine very similar to remove
markdown it's just all this does is
instead of removing markdown if we go
back to our markdown in HTML comparison
here. It just removes the HTML tags. So,
this is considered a tag in HTML. If I
were to go back to my end function and
if I were to try and create a new
heading called heading one, what this
will do is it'll jump in. It'll actually
just remove all instances of this. Now,
when is this useful? Um, well, I'll give
you guys a quick and easy example just
because I think that this is something
that I do often enough for it to
represent like for it to be valuable.
But if I go and I do an HTTP request to
my own website, notice how on the right
hand side here, I receive a bunch of
HTML. That's kind of a lot of HTML.
Right? Now, if I go and I add another
edit fields node and then I go manual
mapping and then I go um no tags. If I
feed in my
data and then if I go remove tags, what
you'll see is I've basically gone
through and if I just expand this a
little bit so we could see big. I've
basically gone through and I've taken as
input all of this ugly looking HTML.
Then I've gotten as output just the
plain text of the website basically. And
when you have the plain text of the
website, not only is it a lot more token
efficient when you're calling large
language models and stuff like that, you
know, you could you could run like
searches over this uh it' be easier,
faster and so on and so forth. So this
is just a principle of like removing
waste. So that's how you'd use that. The
next function I want to talk about if we
just go back here and then select my
dollar sign JSON and then go back to
string. The next function I want to talk
about is called replace. Now, as opposed
to replace all, which I use a lot more
often than replace. What replace does it
just replaces the first element that uh
it sees with another element, it doesn't
just replace every instance of it in the
entire string. So, remember how earlier
replace all took L's and then I replace
them all with W's and then it was hello.
Well, in this case, if I were to try and
replace an L with a W, it would go hello
instead cuz it's only grabbing the first
one. If I switch this back now to
replace all, it does um all characters.
But if I go back to replace, you see it
only does one. So it's kind of neat. Um,
you know, it's a little bit niche. I
mean, there aren't too many situations
in which you want to replace one
character and not replace all
characters. At least in my experience.
There's another function here called
replace special cars. Basically, you
know, a lot of other languages than
English will have things like accents.
So like alone, you have deja, you have
excuing characters that sometimes,
unfortunately, APIs do not support. What
this does is it just allows you to take
them out. So if you know I had uh how
the hell am I going to write
that? I just realized that I don't
necessarily have any of these. Um you
know if I was going to write something
like you know
zuer let's go back here. What this will
do, you know, if you feed Ju into
replace special characters, um the
output is just going to be zu like
without the the exaltu um on the right
hand side of this. And you know, this
doesn't just apply to French. Obviously,
there's a ton of languages out there
with all sorts of things above letters
like um and stuff like that in German. I
believe that's how you pronounce them.
Anyway, any Germans in my audience, feel
free to roast the hell out of me. Yeah,
it's just a quick and easy way to just
replace those before you do an API call
to a service that doesn't support them.
So, if you're calling a service and then
it just like keeps on giving you weird
error messages that you don't fully
understand and your input includes one
of these characters with like accent
above or some sort of marking or symbol,
call replace special cars and give it
another try. I use this maybe like 5% of
the time. Most APIs are pretty good now,
but some of them are still sort of
modernizing. Okay, the next function is
called slice. Now, slice is pretty
interesting. I use slice all the time.
If I go and select JSON string, what
slice does is it basically allows you to
select a substring, but not based off of
characters, but actually based off of um
the number of characters from the start
or the finish. So, we're not slicing
based off of L to O. Well, I mean, like
we can if we want, but I guess what I'm
trying to say is we're feeding in the
character order and the position and
then we're using that to extract a
substring. So, everything is zero index.
That just means it starts at zero at an
ind. This is technically the zeroth
character. This is the first character.
This is the second character. If I were
to try and grab everything from zero to
0, 1st, 2nd, 3rd, I think fourth, maybe
I'd go 0 to four and then it would say
hell, right? You know, if I just wanted
to grab the O, I'd go four to six, then
I grab the O, and then the exclamation
point. There is some nuance regarding
the start position, and I believe the
second one is inclusive. You also don't
necessarily always need to have uh the
second value here. So, you can actually
just feed it in a start, and then it'll
just automatically run till the end of
the string. That can be pretty useful
because you know sometimes you don't
know the length of the string, right?
Sometimes you just want to grab
everything from like the third character
onwards. If you think about it using our
previous example, let's say I have
something like this. Well, instead of
using the extract domain, you could use
slicing as an alternative to you
extracting a domain if you wanted to.
Obviously, the only issue would be if
somebody removes the S and it's instead
like an unvalidated or nonsecure
request, then all of a sudden we lose
the first letter. So, it's usually
better uh in those cases to do to use
the tools that were sort of meant for
this. and you'll be able to handle any
flexible amount that you'd like. Yeah,
slicing has a number of uh cool use
cases, I would say. So, generally a fan
of the slice function. Let's go back to
JSON. And let's see what's next. We
already covered split, so I'm just going
to cover that. Next up, we have
something called substring. Substring
is, from my understanding, basically the
exact same thing as slicing. I'm not
really sure why there are two to be
completely honest. Um, all this does is
just returns the same thing that slice
does. So, let me give you an example. If
we were to go uh 0 to four, it's hell.
If we just replace this with slice, you
see the result doesn't really change.
So, I'm not really sure why substring
exists to be completely honest, but this
is just personally uh what I always use.
I like slice better than substring cuz
how much cooler does slice sound? We're
slicing a string than versus we're
extracting a substring. You should just
operate purely off of vibes, clearly. Um
anyway, next up we have a function I use
pretty often. It's called trim.
Basically, what happens a lot of the
time, especially when you're scraping
resources, is you will get data, but
that data will tend to have like a
variable amount of white space to the
left and to the right. Whites space just
means a bunch of spaces or new lines or
something. Trim just removes all of that
for you. So, um, you know, I mean, they
give you an example of lonely. Let me
show you what this might actually look
like with a string that we type in. You
know, this is, hey, how's it going?
Google.com and then we have another
space. What this does, as you can see
here, there are three spaces. There's
one at the beginning, there's one in the
middle, and then there's one at the end.
Uh what this does is it just removes the
ones on the end. Same thing, you know,
if we added well, I mean, you can't
really do it, but if we added like a
bunch of new line characters, uh tab
characters as well. This isn't actually
like taking any of those because the
part of the way that this works is it
just looks for the presence of that
slash and then the nt and I think
there's one more. These characters just
denote like a new line. Pretty useful to
use. So yeah, I like to use trim
basically anytime that I'm feeding in a
string that may have some sort of
variable white space. Uh when I'm
scraping, I use trim all the time. you
know, just kind of make sure that my
data is standardized, formatted well,
and that I'm not just like asking for
any additional like I'm not using any
additional characters or tokens. There's
trim end and then there's trim start.
Um, this just does the same thing that I
showed you guys earlier. It's just it
preferentially removes things at either
the start or at the end. So, trim end
obviously just takes this out. If I were
to change this to trim start, it would
obviously just take that out, but I just
tend to use trim more generally. We have
two more functions under edit, and those
are URL encode and then URL decode. Now,
if you're unfamiliar with how this
works, usually um when you are dealing
with a URL of some kind, you have
characters that look kind of like this.
You have percentage signs, threes, um I
think those rep uh percentage sign 3D, I
think those represent an equal sign.
Percentage sign 20 that represents a
space. The reason why you do this is
because you can't actually just legally
have, you know, like if if this is my
URL, you can't actually legally have um
a bunch of spaces. So, actually, let's
go back and let's go docs.google.com.
Like you can't say hello, how are you?
Uh this would not be a valid URL, right?
But what you could do is you go um
number sign 20 number sign 20 number
sign 20 number sign 20 and now this
would be like an actual URL. It's not a
URL somebody has created but it is a
real URL like we can actually press
enter and and format it. So all that
this does is it basically converts
something that may include those
characters into something that doesn't
and uh vice versa. So let's
hypothetically say you wanted to go to
leftclick.ai AI and then you want it to
go to blog post call. Let's go blog and
then we go a post with the name of
awesome. Okay. If we URL encoded this,
what it would do is it would take all of
the characters that aren't really like
legally allowed. So, you know, in our
case, mostly these spaces, although you
see it actually also does some
transformations under the hood to colons
and backslashes and stuff like that just
because these characters aren't
technically being rendered. you know,
it's just kind of a quirk of how the
browsers are rendering these to us. But
in reality, when you like request to a
server or something like that, they're
they're being encoded. And then uh what
you can do is you can then subsequently
decode this and you can kind of
transform it back to your initial URL.
So sometimes you'll just see an API or
something that'll say, you know, this
requires like URL encoded um or I don't
know this this requires stuff encoded in
a certain way. You can use URL encode
when you're sending and receiving and
making requests to things. I basically
never really use this in practice, but
it is uh something that they offer to
you as a tool in case you need to. Okay,
next up we have a bunch of query
functions. We've already covered ends
with and includes. Now I'm going to
cover index of. Index of is pretty cool.
It basically allows you to find a
substring that is present inside of the
string and then tell you at what index
did that substring occur. This can lead
to some really interesting string
manipulations and some cool use cases
where like you'll find the index of
something first and then you will use
that to take a slice or something from
from one character to another and then
do a bunch of other cool stuff. Send and
receive data that way. But uh yeah, I
mean in our hello example, right, if I
were to feed an index of H, what do you
think would happen? We'd feed in zero. E
would be one. L the thing about L is
notice that you know I have two L
characters there, right? So if I really
wanted to get the index, I'd have to go
L because that's a unique character
there. Could also go O, which would be
four. Then I go exclamation point, which
be five. I go L. I could go L. I could
go L L. I could go low. And then I could
go O exclamation point. And then I could
get like basically a a sliding window of
two characters instead. But just notice
how it always grabs the beginning of
that. in their example steam and then t
we're finding the first um index because
s is at zero t is at one and then even
though it's three characters te ea it
still starts at one which is pretty neat
so yeah I use index of not super often
to be honest I usually don't need to
search through things um numerically
like that but you know it's a good
function to understand last index of is
very similar to index of but it solves
that problem that we had a moment ago
with the l so um you know if we go index
of and we just type in and L the result
is two. But if there are instances where
we might have you know some characters
repeated multiple times or something you
can grab the last index of L and notice
how that is now three in our hello
string. Next we have match. Match is
pretty interesting and you sort of need
to understand a term called regular
expressions in order to really get it.
But essentially this is a much more
powerful find and replace sort of tool.
Um I don't know if this function in
particular allows you to replace
something. I don't believe so. But it
does allow you to find the thing. And
then you could always just like grab
that thing and then replace it later.
But um basically let's say we have a
string, right? And instead of hello, I'm
going to use a much more varied example.
I'm going to say hey man, how are you
doing today? Okay. And hypothetically,
let's say we want to find the man or um
we want to extract the man string. So if
man is present inside of this, we want
to extract it. If it's not, then we
don't want to. Okay. What we do in order
to do this is we build up something in
what's called the regular expression I
think like templating language. So
instead of just like identifying the
thing, we're actually going to extract
it. And the regular expression
templating language like it looks kind
of weird. As you can see here, there's
some there's some backslashes and then
some up arrows and stuff like that. It's
it's not super difficult to do. If I
were to type in a backslash and then man
and then another backslash and I really
got to stop using the term backslash
here. Um, you can see that it did in
fact extract men. But hypothetically, I
could also instead of just looking for
man and like hard- coding it like this,
cuz this really doesn't do anything for
us, right? Instead, what I can do is I
could look for all instances of
threeletter words. Okay? So, um, in this
language, it would be a to z to z. Then
it would be a to z to z. But I just copy
that one last
time. And then we do that one more time.
Now, um, in our case, we're we're
matching the first instance of this. Um,
but if we wanted to match all, I think
we we'd feed in a G operator, which
would be on this backslash and this
slash and then this G at the end, just
because regular expressions are sort of
outside of the scope of a video like
this, and because it's an entirely new
language, um, my go-to is if you want to
build a regular expression, if you need
one, and there are many, many instances
in which you will need one, head over to
this website over here, reax 101. You
can insert whatever your string is that
you want. Hey, how are you doing today?
And then sorry, you'd actually insert
the test string down here. And then you
actually have the ability to play around
live and see how your changes extract
various parts of um the text. So as you
can see, we have this backslash at the
very beginning. Dang, this slash at the
very beginning. We have this slash at
the end, and then we have some options
here. Um these options always just occur
after the last slash. So in our case,
global and multi-line. Um again, this uh
this resource will explain everything to
you if you look at it. But if you wanted
to extract the man, you might type man.
Um, it's going to say that it's not
matching the subject string because we
don't have man in it. But if we say how,
right, you'll see that as I type H, it
illuminates two elements that are being
extracted. H O, now it's these and then
H O. There also a bunch of really cool
things. Maybe we want to go like you
doing, right? But maybe instead of you
doing, we just want to find the presence
of U and then we want to extract
everything from U all the way to the
end. Well, if I were to do that, then um
I could just go period, which matches
any character, and then I could multiply
it an infinite number of times to go to
the end. Or maybe I want to grab
everything before the U. So, I'd go
period U. And now I extract everything
here. You can also play around with the
presence of um these two brackets. This
allows you to extract specific sub
elements or substrings from the parent
string. Um so, as you can see here, now
we have a green section that is
illuminated because we've wrapped this
in a capture group. And then the the
blue U section is sort of also captured,
but it's not in our captured group. And
yeah, that's just more or less a quick
little rundown of what you can expect if
you were to go super deep in regular
expressions. Uh I should also note that
an AI is really really good at coming up
with regular expressions for you. Like
if I were to feed in this and then I
were to say I want a regular
expression to capture
um all threeletter words in the above
string. If I were to press enter and I'm
just using a new model called 03 mini
high. Uh it's new as of the time of this
recording and probably not going to be
new by the time that you guys watch it.
Uh but if I were to do this uh I would
get something like this. And notice that
it's always going to start with a slash.
It's always going to end with a slash.
And if I were to feed this
in, if I were to remove the beginning
and at the end, what you can see is we
basically gone through we we've
extracted all threeletter characters.
Um, and it threeletter words, and it's
done a really good job of it. So, you
know, over the course of the last, I
want to say 6 months or so, AI has
gotten to the point where he can do
this, um, as of the time of this
recording. Uh, and if you know, you're
wondering how exactly to do regular
expressions and you're watching my video
and you're like, "What the hell is that
guy doing?" Um, AI can can do an even
better job than I can like 90% of the
time already. So, they're automating my
regular expressions. What a dang shame.
Next, we have a another uh module or
another function that uses regular
expressions, but instead of returning
the actual extraction, what we're doing
is we're returning the place that the
character occurred. So, in this case,
we're searching for n and then we're
going um I don't know, I think this is
like at the beginning of a word and then
anything else after that. And so it
tells us, hey, what time does the first
word start or in what position does the
first word starting with n occur? In
this case, it's 0 1 2 3 4 and then five.
Um, and keep in mind that regular
expressions tend to be case sensitive
unless I think you specifically turn
that off. So, uh, it's not capturing the
first capital and it's capturing the the
second. I don't really use search
basically ever to be completely honest.
Um, search to me just doesn't really
have any value that index of doesn't.
So, uh, from here on out, we are now
moving into the validate section. So now
we have a suite of functions that I use
very often to validate whether something
is a domain, whether something is an
email, whether something is empty,
whether something is not empty, whether
something is numeric or whether
something is a URL. Let's start with
domain. So remember earlier how we fed
in https
back/back/leclick.ai. Right? And then I
said that this was a URL and inside of
the URL you had a protocol, you had some
sort of delimiter, and then you had the
domain name. Well, this will tell you
whether or not what you're feeding in is
a domain name. So what do you think? If
I feed this in, is this a domain? The
answer is no because we include we've
included the protocol and the delimiter
as well. If I take this out, is domain
now reverse to true. Now, alternatively,
if I change this to is URL, you'll see
that this is true. But if I just feed in
a domain name, you'll see that this is
false because a URL requires all of the
other subsequent
components. Okay, we have a couple of
other ones that we can go into as well.
We can do empty. So if a string is
empty, you can very quickly validate and
check it. So obviously, is this empty?
No. Right. But if I were to take this
and delete everything, then yes, it is
empty. We can go is not empty, which is
just the inverse of is empty. So is is
this not empty? Yes, true. This is not
empty. There is a bunch of stuff inside.
If I take it out, is this not empty? No,
it is empty because there's nothing
inside. And then similarly in the same
vein, um we can do a little bit of
checking to see whether or not something
is an email. So if nick at
leftclick ai, you'll see that this
converts to true because there is
currently no tople domain. That's just
the thing at the very end here. Um that
isn't at least two characters, right?
But if I were to just feed in a domain
name, that would obviously be false.
Quick and easy way to do validation and
verification. And then there's also one
for a numeric, which is somewhat
interesting. Basically, what you have is
the ability to check whether or not all
that you fed in is is a number.
So you can feed in um integers, you
could feed in like decimals, you could
feed in like negative numbers and stuff
like that. Um and if it's a number,
it'll tell you. If you feed in an f or
an e or whatever, um then you know
obviously this is no longer just a
number. It's also a bunch of other
characters here, which is why is numeric
is now reverting as false. Okay, the
next functions are very simple and very
straightforward. There are a bunch of
case functions. So there's two
lowercase, two sentence case, two snake
case, two title case, and two uppercase.
Lowerase is hopefully self-explanatory.
Hello. How are you doing, Nick? If I
feed in this, which has two
capitalizations, it just lowercases
everything. This might be useful when, I
don't know, you're trying to convert
something into a domain. So, if I were
to go uh sorry, convert something like
like into a blog post slug. So, let's
say I had a blog post title and it's 38
ways to make money online, right? And I
wanted to convert this um into something
that I could stick onto my my URL.
Basically, what I could do first is I
could replace
all instances of a space and I could do
so with a dash and then I could just go
lowercase. And what I'm doing now is I'm
converting um this over to something
that might actually fit inside of my
URL. Pretty cool, right? That's what
lowercase does. Now, obviously, there is
an alternative and that is if I just
remove this here, um there are a bunch
of other similar functions that change
the case of the of the string that
you're feeding in. So, if I were to say
38 ways to feed, sorry, to make money
online, and then I would go to go
uppercase, well, then we would just
scream 38 ways to make money online. But
there are a couple of other cases as
well. There's something called sentence
case. The way that sentence case works,
if you're unfamiliar, is it basically
just capitalizes the first letter of the
entire string. So, ways to make money
online, right? If I were to remove this
to sentence case, you'll see that I'm
basically taking all of these and then
I'm I'm pumping them. Uh, I'd have to
remove this dot as well. And then I'm uh
bringing up all of the subsequent first
letters of every word back up to capital
case. For to put this in, I just remove
that. And then there's a there's a
couple more. There's one called snake
case. Snake case is pretty interesting.
Um, this basically does uh almost like
what I was what I was saying earlier
with the URL replacement, but instead of
a dash, we're doing an underscore. And
this is just like a way to like create
variable names really quickly because
there are two naming conventions for
variables. There's um camelc case and
then there's snake case. Snake case just
always has underscores between every
word because uh spaces are not
represented well in programming because
parsers break. And then the last one is
to um title case. And what you'll see is
nothing changes between this and this.
The reason why is cuz this is already in
title
case. All title cases is it grabs the
first letter of all major words. So I
think uh words that are not connectors
like to or at or a or 'the' and it makes
them capital. So ways make money man if
I were to go at I guess that
is oh no it's not if I were to go at
then at would not be a connector the
right most would but not the so yeah I
mean all of these are just different
ways to turn something into um something
else which is nice. Okay the next
function is called parse JSON. It's
pretty interesting. Uh, but basically
the way that it works is a lot of the
time when you receive queries uh from
the internet like when you do some sort
of scraping or when you consult an API,
what you get is you get something that
has a lot of those escaped delimiters
that I mentioned, the slashes before
certain characters. So I'll give you
guys a quick example and you'll
understand this intuitively. Let's say I
have a string here. Okay? And this
string is like a JSON object. So I'm
going to go name and in order to do this
I'm going to cancel it out and then I'll
go you know Peter like this and then
I'll wrap it. Uh if I feed this into
parse JSON, you'll see what happens is
I'm actually parsing this out into an
object. Like previously, this is a
string, right? The string is uh this
curly brace, the quote sign, name other
quote sign colon uh quote sign uh Peter
and then quote sign and then this other
curly brace. But if I go parse JSON,
what I'm actually doing is I'm
converting this to an object. I'm
literally converting the data type into
another data type um which I will be
showing you um you know, cool things
about. And if you if you parse this, if
you click test step,
um what you'll see is sorry uh what I'm
what I mean to say is now that it's
parsed, what you can do is you can
actually reference things inside of the
variable of the thing that you just
parsed. So now, for example, I can
actually just extract the name from
this. So I mean, you know, uh obviously
I'm just writing this all out right now,
which is why this doesn't seem very
useful. You can imagine how if you
receive a big long string, well, you can
actually parse it directly in your
expression editor, which makes this
super powerful. Um, you know, as I
mentioned, I don't use this super often.
Uh, just because I'm not like calling a
lot of dedicated or hidden APIs where I
find that this typically comes up. Um,
but you know, you can you can use this
so that you don't have to like add
another node. You don't have to like
render something or or parse something
in this node and then deal with it
later. What you can do is actually just
like get a string that contains
JavaScript, parse it out, and then
you'll be able to extract whatever value
you want. So, you know, because this is
an object, I can now reference keys or I
can get values, right? I can do a lot of
other stuff with it. Um, and I'm going
to be running you guys through the
object functions in a moment. Okay, the
next function is to boolean. Boolean's
pretty simple. Um, basically if I feed
in a one or a zero, what I do is I
convert this data type from a string
into this boolean which is true or
false. So zeros are false, right? Zero
is is um no, it's off. It's false in
boolean logic. One is on, it's true,
it's good, right? So um I'm basically
converting this from a string into like
a separate data type called true. I
rarely use this in practice because most
of the nodes in n that I'm realistically
going to care about. They're going to
have some sort of type conversion built
in. This next one is called to date
time. This is actually super useful um
because a lot of the time you're going
to be converting to and from some
standardized datetime format in order to
do things like add a certain number of
minutes, add a certain number of hours.
The context here is NAN uses this
specific type of datetime formatting
called Lexon datetime. But basically all
this does is it just allows you to
convert like a string into another type
of object that you can now do math with
basically uh which is pretty cool. So
I'll give you guys a quick example um
just to show you guys just how many
things are representable as dates. If
you just feed in like the number one, it
will find the first date of 2001. Why? I
I don't know. There's just some logic
that's going on under the hood. But
hypothetically, if I were to grab the
current date in um I think like uh day
day no month month day day year year
format it would be 0131
uh 2024. Right? So now this is
converting um the current date to the
standardized date format. Sorry I guess
2025 it converts into the standardized
detype format. What's the cool thing
about this? Well, if I press uh dot here
now, what I can do is now I have a whole
other function suite available to me
that includes datetime specific
functions. So now we can do a bunch of
really cool things. We could convert to
local string and now this actually
converts this into um the specific uh
basically they grab my local and then it
converts it into the specific type of
string that people are most likely to
see here. So you can imagine this might
be really really useful if you're
working in databases or something like
that. There are a variety of other
datetime functions as well which we're
going to get into. But yeah, you can do
things like extract certain times. You
can do things like subtract uh I don't
know five days from January the 31st to
give us January the 26th. All this stuff
ends up being super super valuable um
when you're working. Okay, great. The
last thing I want to cover is to number.
So let's say I have the number
123,54. Okay. All this does is it takes
the string that is 123,54 and converts
it to a number. What do I mean by this?
Well, um numbers and strings are
different, right? And so, um all this is
doing is it's allowing me to do a
conversion from the string format of
1,120,54 to the number format
123,54 which means now I can do things
like I can add. So, I just added five,
right? If I were to try adding five to
the string, all we do is we actually
literally add the string five to it. You
guys kind of see what I mean? If I go 1
2 3504 + 5, what I'm doing is I'm
appending five to this four. I'm
concatenating. But if I make this into a
number, well, now we can actually
perform a logic on it. We can we can I
don't know, multiply it by five or 12,
right? If you were to not, then you
know, if you were to try and multiply a
string by 12, um, I guess it would allow
you to because this is like a very clear
operator. But yeah, the the plus
specifically is sort of like the the
breaking example of doing mathematical
operations on strings. And this is
equivalent to concat
12 as we could see here. So basically
all this is doing is it's just verifying
that this thing is a number. And then
once it's a number, we can do a ton of
like really cool, you know, math and
stuff like that with it. I use two
number reasonably often. Yeah, a lot of
the time like I'll grab a string, that
string is formatted in like a particular
way and then I extract it. I turn it
into a number and then once I've turned
it into a number um you know I can I can
do really cool things with it. And then
there's one other example here in NADN
where um you can have a number that's
like 1.23 E10. That's like 1.23 raised
to the 10. Well, you can actually take
the string and then you can convert it
into like a usable number that you can
perform mathematical operations on. This
is sort of like more of a scientific
need. So you're not going to use it
super often, but I do use two number
just to make sure that my my types are
okay. Okay. Next up, we have the number
family of functions. This is pretty
straightforward. Now that we've done
string, I'll say that string and array
are probably the most difficult ones.
This one's going to be a little bit
easier. Um, let's just type in the
number. And now let's reveal all the
functions available to us. So the first
one we're going to cover is round. Round
is kind of what it sounds like. If I
were to feed in JSON number, which in
our case is 3.5, into round, what
happens? This goes up to four. If I were
to try and uh change the number of
decimal places and go two, it'll round
to 3.5. If I go three, it won't do
anything because this number doesn't
have any more decimal points, right? But
yeah, this will automatically round up
to four, which is just default behavior.
Anything um up to 3.499 repeater will
round down. Anything at 3.5 and up will
round up. Um and yeah, this is just sort
of like default behavior. It's it's
great for like removing complexity from
numbers and stuff like that. Now, I
should note I want to show you guys a
little bit more context here. I don't
just want to use JSON number. So, if you
want to write a number in NAD, you could
do so just by wrapping round brackets
around it like this. So, if I'm rounding
234.5, this will be 235, right? I'm
going 499, it'll be down. But what if I
go this and then I want to round to the
second decimal point. How about the
third decimal point? The fourth decimal
point. I don't think there
uh yes, sorry, I was just getting a lag
actually. If I wanted to round to the
sixth decimal point, all the way over
here, right? This is a two, a three, it
would be down. If it's a a six, it would
be up, right? Because we have a five
down here. Anyway, point I'm making is
you can round stuff and rounding is
cool. All right. Now, why don't we do
the uh more directed version of round,
which is where we specifically say, am I
aiming for the floor or am I aiming for
the ceiling? So, if I aim for the floor
of 3.5, what do you guys think is going
to happen? This is going to return me
the number three. If I aim for the seal
of 3.5, what's going to happen? This is
going to return me the number four. So
basically this is just a directed way to
perform your rounding operation sort of
manually. Right? 3.8 is always going to
go up to four. 3.1 is going to go up to
four. Um if I were to replace this now
with the number three ceiling of three
would be three. 2.9 would be would be
three. 2.1 would be three. Two would be
two. 2.001 would be three. So it's
interesting um you know just how much
granularity NN gives you in being able
to manipulate numbers with this. Uh but
yeah, that's the way that seal works.
The next number function is called ABS.
That stands for absolute, not my ripped
six-pack. Uh basically, when you feed in
something like a number here, um you can
do so uh you know, with with positives
or with negatives or whatever, all this
does is just returns to you uh what's
called the the absolute value of that
number. So, ABS just says, hey, if
there's any negatives, something like
that, I just want you to get the
absolute magnitude of it. If I feed in
2.001, 0 01 it'll just return me two. So
you can kind of think of it as just a
way to strip negatives get only the
actual magnitude of the thing. Magnitude
being the distance from zero. Okay. On
top of that we also have a few other
interesting ones like format. Now the
way that format works is basically you
know how sometimes Americans and
Europeans will format numbers
differently. Like sometimes Europeans
might put like the euro at the end of
the sign or something uh end of the
number and then Americans sometimes
might put the dollar sign or usually at
the beginning of the number. Um,
sometimes they use periods as delimiters
in thousand separators instead of commas
and stuff. Format just deals with all of
that. Now, I'm feeding in 3.5 and I'm
trying to format it. That doesn't really
make much sense for me. So, let me just
feed in a bigger number and show you
guys uh show you guys how it works
intuitively. Let's say I fed in
3,459,221. If I were to leave this up to
the standard way that the format module
or format function I should say formats
things, I'm basically converting this
and then I'm adding a bunch of these
little um delimiters. But I could also
change this if I just add a period
instead. Oh, sorry. If I uh my bad, you
didn't actually add the delimiter. If I
had the local string instead, right? If
instead I wanted to go
French, you'll see that we've now added
a space in between instead of the uh
comma. If I wanted to go um Dutch
instead, I think Dutch, I may be
mistaken, but if I wanted to go Dutch
instead, um we now add periods, right?
This can be useful when I don't know,
you want to drop like a dollar sign in
front or something like that, right? If
I go en here, then now we have uh
basically like a number that maybe we've
done some math on to get to this point.
Um and now we've turned this into
something that is like realistically
readable as I don't know, a string,
which we could do um tons of things
with. we could pass it into a a pandadoc
proposal and template out, you know, the
amount of money it costs. Make things
look a little bit prettier essentially.
So, that's pretty neat. I'm a fan of
format. I use format pretty often. Um,
aside from that, we have a couple of
very simple functions. Um, is even just
tells you whether or not this number is
even. So, is this number even? No,
because there's a one at the end. But if
it's a zero, then it'll be true.
Likewise, there's is odd. So, is this
number even? No. Is this number odd?
Yes. Is this number odd? No.
Uh there are a few other ones like is
integer. Now if you guys are unfamiliar
an integer just sort of means like a
like a like a number that doesn't have
any decimal points. So this is an
integer because there's no decimal
points. But if I were to do this and
this would not no long no no longer be
an integer. This can be important
sometimes but to be honest I don't
really use these type conversions or is
even or is odd very often. Um there are
certainly places for them though. Next
up we have um some conversion functions.
So two boolean similarly to what we had
before. 2 boolean will convert this to
true. Like if I go uh zero, this will be
false. If I go one, it's true. Then if I
go any number above one, it's also true.
So basically zero is just the only
negative. And then even like negative
numbers and stuff like that are
technically true. This is some nuance
that isn't super important to
understand, but um yeah, just to say
that you can convert this into the true
or the false boolean type. There are
also ways to convert numbers to
datetimes. So 43 uh you know is
extracted as this. If I wanted to
convert this number to a datetime, um, I
would go and I'd get a time
stamp. Unix time stamp is the number of
seconds since January the 1st, 1970. So,
I'm just going to copy this. Going to go
over here. I'm going to feed this in.
What this does is it tells me what the
current date time is. I think I have to
add three zeros actually. Um, when I do
that, because I think this one does it
with thousands, but anyway, as we can
see, the date time here is now
2025131. Um, it is
300641 according to my time zone, which
is nice. They automatically do minus07
because that's where I'm at. Uh, but
yeah, you know, you can convert a number
of things from numbers or numeric um uh
like like numbers into um dates as well
to perform functions on later. And I
should note that, you know, this is a
number um you know like like this right
over here is a number. So what you could
theoretically do is you could probably
do this
So, you know how early I had to add that
um thousand separator? If you just
multiply this by a th00and first
instead, then this is still technically
like a like a functioning um number,
right? Cuz basically what I'm doing is
I'm I'm taking this number. I'm defining
it. Then I'm multiplying it by a th00and
then I'm converting that to a datetime
which is now rendered correctly. Um you
know, this will sort of muck up the date
time, but a thousand in my case. It's
just the nadn conversion between a Unix
epoch time stamp over here. Um and then
you know what what NNN is comfortable
with. Okay, great. Um we have a couple
of additional ones. Uh the only ones
that are are really important are the
local string. Um, so this converts
things from I don't know, let's say 500
uh 500 and then
50,34 sorry
50,50,34 automatically converts this
into a string with those commas and
everything like that um in them. There
are a variety of things that you can do.
Um you could use the same settings that
we had before. So remember how earlier
if I go to the C full list
uh remember how earlier you know I fed
in um fr well there's also a variety of
other ways that things um can be
formatted and this is just like a master
list of all of them and some of them
will be well most of them are going to
be very similar to each other but some
of them are also going to be a little
bit different. This just allows you to
format things into the particular local
or it allows you to format it into a
string that is of the particular local
of the people that you want and sort of
like an an automatic basis which is
pretty nice. And then the last one is
obviously just two string. Um two string
just converts a number which you perform
functions on um sorry perform
mathematical operations on into a string
that you can now do things like
concatenate with the term hello. Right?
So, you couldn't just add the term hello
to uh
50,50,34 cuz that doesn't really make
sense. But since we converted to a
string first, this is now basically
this. And then we can easily concatenate
any string to this if we want. All
right, that is the number family. Let's
move over to the array family. Um, and
let's knock these out. What I have over
here on the left hand side is I have an
array with three items, Sarah, Sally,
and Stephanie. This is clearly an array
of names. You can also create your own
array in N8 similarly to how we've been
doing so far just by using the square
bracket
operator. All right, this is technically
now um rendered as an array in code that
we could do things with just by dot
notating. But in our case, as usual, I'm
going to start off with that just to
show you guys how all of this works. Um
and we can see our array has now been
pulled and rendered as a variable from
the previous node. So if I click period,
what sort of functions are available to
me? Well, the first is length, which is
probably pretty similar to the string
one. It's just instead of counting the
number of characters, what we do is we
count the number of elements in the
array. So, we had S Sarah, Sally, and
Stephanie. Those are three elements.
It's not surprising then that we have a
length that equates to
three. Now, we have some other functions
here. Last, if I were to put this in,
what do you think would happen? Well,
we'd extract the last element,
Stephanie. Likewise, if I were to
extract the first element, Sarah,
um, we can do includes. This one in
practice I use very often. Um, and this
just verifies whether or not there is
the element that I'm looking for in this
array. So sometimes APIs will return big
arrays with tons of elements. And all
I'm curious about is, hey, does this
contain the thing that I want? Well, you
know, does this contain Sally? Yes. Does
this contain Saul? No. But does this
contain Sally? Yes. Remember, we're now
doing this on array basis. So we're
looking for the array elements that need
to match these strings exactly as
opposed to just the string basis. If we
did a string and then we to typed a
substring or a slice of that, it would
have returned as true, right? But now
that we're operating off of arrays, we
need to make sure that they match one to
one. Okay, we have map and we have
filter. And these are a little bit more
complicated, so I'm going to leave them
till the end. But, uh, moving our way
down, the next function is append. Now,
append is just a way that you can add an
additional element to an array. Um, if
you append something, you're sticking it
on the end. So, if I were to add the
guy's name here, let's go Eric. Then if
we append quote Eric quote, we've now
added something to the end of that
array. So I use this pretty often. Um
the interesting part here that people
don't know most of the time is that you
can actually just feed in another
array. So maybe we have like a guy's
array over
here. Um you can append a number of
things. In my case, you know, I've just
appended another array inside of that
array. Uh you can also append other data
types like numbers. So, keep in mind
Sally, Sarah, and Stephanie, they all
have quotes around them. You can also
append things like objects. So,
um I believe in order to do this, we
actually need to go like this. No, my
bad. There are so many quote signs here.
I don't know what the hell's going on.
So, in order to append this
puppy, we'll remove that. And then we
can see that the next element over here
is uh is an object, right? Right? It's
an object with name equals Peter. So
yeah, you can append a variety of things
um to an array. Uh but append is just a
way to add to the end of it. Another
function I'll show off is chunk. Chunk
is pretty cool. Uh basically if we have
an array and the array has I don't know
uh in this case it has three elements.
So this isn't really going to work. But
basically let's say it has like I don't
know 10 elements or something like that.
We can chunk it into subarrays of two.
So let me make one really
quickly. Okay. Okay. And if I just copy
this and then if I feed this in over
here,
um, basically what we can do is we can
chunk this into uh a bunch of subarrays
that contain the number of elements that
we specify in our chunk. So laptop,
backpack, smartphone, notebook, pen,
headphones, water bottle, whatever.
We're now chunking this into array where
we have two items. So I don't know,
maybe in this specific case we're asking
people to bring um, you know, everybody
brings two items or something and then
like we all get them together. that way.
I don't know. We're sort of at like the
same level carrying wise. Nobody's
carrying a bunch of stuff. Um, if you
wanted to chunk this more, maybe you'd
go three, you go five. Um, you know, if
you want to do one, that's just
obviously um sort of silly because
you're just nesting every element inside
of another element. Um, zero breaks, so
don't do that. Um, but yeah, that's
that's kind of how chunk works. Do I use
chunk? Basically, never. Um, but I
figured I'd at least mention what chunk
was. Okay. Um, we'll go down to chunk.
Sorry, we'll go down to JSON. And then
working our way down here, we also have
a very interesting function called
compact. Hypothetically, let's say we
had that array that we had earlier. But
let's also say that I don't know a bunch
of these elements weren't empty. So if
we look at what's being returned here,
you see we're being returned an array
that still has, you know, 10 elements,
but three of them are empty. Well,
hypothetically, um, what you can do is
if you just wanted to only get the
elements in the array that had values,
you just type in compact, but it would
actually strip everything that is empty.
I should note that these quotes aren't
the only things that you can have. You
can also have null. Um, this null is not
wrapped in quotes and it's a special
series of characters. It's just like
understood by JavaScript to mean that
there's like a null entry there. Um, but
yeah, compact is just a quick and easy
way to get rid of these null entries or
empty entries. And this can be valuable
because sometimes this is how APIs send
information back and forth, right?
You'll receive some big long array and
then like 50 of the fields inside will
be empty. Well, this way allows you to
just strip those and then only operate
off of the data that actually matters to
you. Okay, the next function is concat.
So, as you can imagine, this is very
similar to pend in so far that you can
add a bunch of things to it. In this
case, you know, if I wanted to add um
Sarah or something, we've now added an
additional element inside called Sarah,
but I could also add um like I did
before an array with Peter and then I
don't know, Eric. And now what I've done
is I haven't added a subarray. So, it's
not like I've added an additional array
inside like I did with append. And what
I'm actually doing is I'm just like
taking these two arrays and I'm just
sticking them together. So you can kind
of think of it as like squishing two
arrays together without really
preserving um like the data type uh
necessarily. Next up we have a very
interesting function, one that I use
quite often called difference. I'll also
show you its intersection which is um
inter uh sorry I'll show you its inverse
which is called intersection. But I'm
just going to create a new array and
I'll go 1 2 3. Then I'm going to go
difference. Then I'll go three, four,
four,
five. So basically, oh, sorry, I need to
make this an array. So basically, what
difference does is difference just
returns you all of the elements from the
first array that are not in the second
array. Okay, so one and two are not in
the second array. Three is in the second
array. So we're only getting one and
two. Difference doesn't care about all
of the elements here. like you don't
insert any of these elements here. It
only ever uh uses the the the first
array that you feed in as like the
primary data. So if I were to say two,
what do you think would happen? Well, if
I click two, obviously this is now going
to disappear because one of the elements
here is now over here and the only
element that is unique. You kind of
think of this as like a unique element,
although um there's another function
called unique. So it might not be good
to to conceptualize that way. Um, but
all of this does is this just takes all
of the elements here that are not in
this array. So, there are tons of ways
and and reasons why you should use this.
One way that I just used this the other
day is I'm tracking a bunch of other
people on YouTube that are about the
similar size to me. Uh, just because I
want to see if there's differences in
posting schedule, lengths of the videos
or something like that. And so, I'm
calling a YouTube RSS feed. The YouTube
RSS feed brings me an array of a bunch
of YouTube posts that they make. Well, I
can store their YouTube post in a
database. And then all I can do is I can
just compare to see, hey, um, you know,
is this RSS feed array different from
this RSS feed array? Oh, it is. Okay.
Well, what's the difference? Is it that
post? Okay, great. Well, now I know that
that's the post that I'm going to take
to like update my database with. I'm
going to add that post essentially. So,
uh, yeah, variety of ways you could do
this. If we use our example
here of um you know
names
maybe maybe what I'm doing is I'm just
looking for um any name from this array
that is not in this array back here. So
Stephanie for instance is not in Sarah,
Sally or Peter. Hence why I'm returning
Stephanie. Now the inverse of this is
called intersection. And this is
similarly another function that I use
all the time. An intersection is super
valuable. Basically, instead of looking
for the difference, it looks for the
instances in which we have both data.
So, we have Sarah in both arrays, so
that's what I'm going to return. We have
Sally in both arrays. That's what I'm
going to return. Do we have Stephanie in
both arrays? No. We have another name
called Peter, right? So, intersection
and difference are both fantastic, and
they're things that uh you know, if
you're working with any sort of like
real industrial or enterprise data, I
think you're going to find yourself
using all the time. Okay. The next
function I want to cover is called find.
find is pretty pretty sweet. Um,
basically it allows you to use math as
part of your function. So, if you just
press enter, you'll see that we've now
added it doesn't just allow you to use
math, sorry, it allows you to use like
any sort of operator. Um, now we've
added this cool little syntax which is
called like arrow notation or arrow
syntax in JavaScript where um we've got
now we have an element. So, we now have
some some variable that we're calling
item and we're saying true. This is
pretty interesting. Um, the way that
this works is think of item as the
individual item in the array. So all
we're doing is we're basically saying,
hey, array zero is equal to item. So
item is just the name that we're going
to use to reference the specific uh item
in the array that we are currently at
because it's going to go through all of
the items. So this is kind of a piss
poor example and I don't really know why
they do that, but let me show you
something that you can do with this.
What if we want to return all of the
elements in an array that are greater
than let's see uh I don't know they're
greater they have more characters than
six. So um Sarah has six charact or five
characters. Sally has five characters
but Stephanie has way more than six.
Realistically I think has like 10 or
something like that. So maybe I don't
know we're just looking to see if there
are any names in our array that are
longer than a certain number of
characters. How would you do this? Well
it's actually really easy. We go dollar
sign JSON.array.find and then we take
the thing item. Then we just check to
see if item length is over six. And if
so, then our result is Stephanie. We're
finding an element in an array that
corresponds to this. Okay. Now, there's
some nuance and some some things here
that I should explain. Um there's
another function that does something
very similar to this called map. Uh
sorry, called filter, which I'll cover
in a second. But this element is special
because it only returns the first
instance of the element that uh
satisfies the request. So
JSON.array.find we define our item and
we're saying the constraint is the
item.length needs to be less than six is
going to return uh Sarah but it's not
going to return Sally even though Sally
also fulfills that request technically.
So find is super powerful. I don't use
find as much as I use map and filter.
Um, but I'm I'm going to cover all of
them regardless. The very important
thing to know here is you just need to
be comfortable using array syntax. Um,
um, arrow syntax. This is called an
arrow function in JavaScript. So, I
should note that it doesn't need to say
item. It could say I as long as the
element or the way that you've named it
on the left is the same as the way
you've named it on the right. This
satisfies the condition. So, in our
case, um, I is just a symbol that we're
using to denote all of the different
elements in the array um, one by one.
Okay, great. So, that's fine. Find fine
is pretty awesome. Let's now cover um
index of. Index of, as I'm sure you can
imagine, is very similar in the array
format to the way that things are
represented in the string format. If we
are looking to find the index of the
entry called
Sally, well, then the entry is one. This
is zero. This is one. This is two. What
if we wanted to find Sarah? It'll return
zero. What if we wanted to find
Stephanie? This will return two. Right?
So, that's what index of does. Um, and
one common theme that you'll find is
that arrays and uh strings are actually
pretty similar in terms of what's going
on under the hood
mathematically. Next up, we have is
empty. If I feed in this array with
three elements to is empty, obviously
it's going to return false. We also have
is not empty, which is the inverse. And
then we have a very special uh function,
one that I use very often, called join.
And all join is is it's the inverse of
split. Remember how earlier we took a
string and then we split it into an
array. Well, join takes an array and
then it turns it into a string. So in
our case, we have Sarah, Sally, and
Stephanie here. We can actually just
join all those together and then we can
get Sarah, Sally, Stephanie. This is now
a string. So hypothetically, what if I
wanted instead to put plus signs between
them? Sarah plus Sally plus Stephanie.
Well, all I do is I go space plus and
then space. So what join does is it just
gets all the elements as they're laid
out. Then it adds whatever characters
you want between all of them. So, we go
comma space. We could go this. We go
underscore, right? We have a ton of
options
here. Uh, we we have a ton of options
here for how we want to do the
separator. Uh, which is pretty cool. So,
I use this all the time. I mean, this is
how I turn a bunch of array data into
like a string or something, right? I
also use this to convert things into
like CSV format, which is where you have
like a comma between. And then the cool
thing is you can just take the CSV, you
can actually make a file of it and just
upload it to a Google Drive or
something. So, tons of examples here.
You know, they show you how to do three
with a space plus space. Um, if you just
join with nothing, then if you join with
um like an empty string, it'll just kind
of stack them all together. This is very
similar to like a text aggregator sort
of function if you're using make or um
some sort of aggregation function in
most no code
platforms. Okay, great. Let's now cover
merge. Now, all merge does is it allows
you to take a specific type of array and
that's the type of array that has um
objects as elements instead of just um
numbers, strings or booleans or
subarrays and allows you to basically
take them all and then stick them into
one big object. So, if you think about
this, what we're really doing is we're
converting from an array into an object.
I'll give you guys a quick example of
what that looks like by actually
creating my own. If I were to grab my
own array, and then I were to create an
object inside of set array where I have
name, that's object number one, and then
I were to say city. The automatic curly
brace adding is kind of annoying. Okay,
so name Nick. Uh, let's do city Calgary.
And then we'll go, I don't know, height.
And then we'll go like 188 or something.
Just like
this. Right? We now have an array that
contains three elements. We have name
neck. We have city Calgary. And then we
have height 188. What if we just wanted
to convert this into one object? Well,
we just go merge. Sorry, that's not
going to work because we're outside of
these curly brackets. Let me just add a
space here to make our lives easier. We
go domerge now. And now we basically
taken an array and we've converted it
into an object where all of the um array
elements are now just key names in one.
So it's name, nick, city, calgary,
height, 188. This is now just one
object. And now instead of a bunch of
array functions, we actually have a
bunch of object functions available to
us, which I'm going to go over later. So
merge is, you know, I mean, like I
understand why they put merge in, but do
I ever actually use it in practice? No,
not really. Next up, we have pluck.
Pluck is pretty badass. Um, basically
what we get to do is if I were to feed
in the same thing that I just fed in
before, then instead of merging it, I
were to pluck it. What I can do is I can
extract the specific things from this
array of objects. Like if I had name and
then uh I mean you know this this isn't
a very good example but if I were to
pluck out the name what I'd get as a
result is I'd get nick. Okay. Pluck just
allows you to extract the value of
something that has a key name equal to
what you've put in here. So
hypothetically if I were to just have
another person in with a name Sally.
What I've done is I've plucked out all
of the names. I've plucked out Nick.
I've plucked out Sally. This is another
one of those manipulation functions
which I don't really use too often. Um,
but it's not bad to know. The next
function we have is called random item.
It is fantastic. Random item is just a
quick way to select something from an
array. I use this all the time. I use
this in like roundroin scheduling. Well,
not round robin scheduling, sorry, like
uh random scheduling. I use this when
like I'll generate a a list of random
numbers and I'll just select one.
Although to be fair, there is like a
random function that you can use. I use
these to like, you know, statistically
randomly and uniformly just take things
from an array and then do things with
it. The next function is called rename
keys. You guys remember that example
function I had earlier? If I just go
back to it, if I had a bunch of entries
with name, name name, and then name, and
instead of using pluck, I were to use
rename keys. What rename keys allows you
to do is it basically allows you to to
search for a specific key name of the
object. So in this case, name, then
convert it to something else. So maybe
instead of name, what I want is I
actually want to call it first name.
Well, this will now um create another
array, but it'll automatically go in and
it'll rename all the keys and all the
objects in set array. This is another
one of those like more complicated like
data formatting functions that I don't
really find myself using often, but I
have used this before and uh it's worth
at least knowing. Okay. And JSON.array
reverse does probably what you're
expecting it to do. Um it just takes as
input an array. So, in my case, an array
of Sarah, Sally, and Stephanie, then it
reverses it. But for some weird reason,
every time I put JSON array at reverse
in, it crashes my NAND server entirely
and then I have to spin it up again. So
this is a very interesting development
if I'm honest. I wasn't expecting this
one function to just consistently crash,
but I've repeated the behavior a number
of times and just does not really seem
to be cooperating. Anyway, imagine if it
said Sarah, Sally, and Stephanie in your
input. Um the output would be Stephanie,
Sally, and then Sarah. Sally is the
middle unit, so it wouldn't necessarily
change. Anyway, I'm going to exit this
page, fix it, and then come back. Okay,
next we have the slice function. Um, the
slice function works the exact same in
an array as it does in a string. If we
wanted to slice between zero and two, we
get Sarah and Sally. If we want to go
one and three, we'd get Sally and
Stephanie. Next up, we have a very
interesting one called smart join. Uh,
basically, I'm going to rely off the
given example here just because it's
such a nuanced and and I want to say
uncommon function to use that I don't
really use it basically ever. But you
know over here you see how we have um an
object that is specifically formatted as
follows. Field age value 2 field city
value Berlin. Okay, let me copy this
over. I'll show you guys what this
means.
I were to pump this in and I were to go
to smart join. And if I were to feed in
um field and then value and I close it
off and what this would do is it would
basically take as input my array and my
array is broken down into basically an
object with a field and a value for
every thing. Like if you think about it,
there's no need to break it into a field
and then an age and then a value and
then a two. You could just go age and
then two, right? City and then Berlin.
Um, but it takes this very particular
formatting and then it basically plucks
similar like to what we were doing
before. It plucks out the fields and
then the values and then it uses it to
turn into a new object where the first
element that you feed in is going to be
the key and then the second element that
you feed in is going to be the value. I
don't really ever use this so I probably
wouldn't worry too much about
understanding it if you don't. Next up
we have sort. Sort just sorts things
alphabetically to start. Um, if you want
to do anything more complex than
alphabetical sorting, you're going to
have to use one of those arrow functions
that we talked about again. And
unfortunately, the way that the arrow
function works is not very intuitive.
It's just a handme-down of um I guess uh
you know like some programming or
JavaScript conventions. Basically, you
want to grab A, which is going to be
your earlier element, and you want to
grab B, which is your later element. You
just always want to wrap it like this.
And then in order to turn this bracket a
comma b into some sort of inverse order,
what you'd have to do is you have to go
to b localal compare and then go a like
this. It's kind of annoying, but we've
just reversed it. Basically, we've
sorted this. Well, we didn't reverse it
actually. We sorted this based off of
the presence of the characters in the
alphabet. You know, SA comes before S,
which comes before ST. Uh because we're
we're doing this inverse comparison. If
you were to go alphabetically, it would
just be standard. it just be a and then
b um why you have to use the localal
compar in this particular format to be
honest I don't really understand or get
um I don't really ever sort anything
other than numbers um from like largest
to greatest or strings um alphabetically
ascending and then if you think about it
if you sort things one way you can also
just sort it and then you can just
reverse it in order to get the other
thing right so like most of the time in
practice I'll sort first and then I will
reverse after now I'm not going to type
the two brackets there because I have a
feeling it's probably going to break my
my nan add an instance again for
whatever reason. But yeah, that's that's
how that works. Next up, we have JSON
string. Um, this just converts all of
the elements in an array into like a
JSON string that you could do stuff
with. So, this is now a string. It's not
an object. It's a string and you can do
string manipulations on it. A lot of the
time you have to convert things into
JSON strings in order to send or receive
them through API. So, I'll use this
reasonably often. Next, we have two
spliced. Two splice is actually really,
really interesting and I could see a lot
of cool uses for it, but I personally
don't use it very often. Essentially
what it allows you to do is allows you
to take as input an array. Then what you
do is you will add specific elements at
an index that you specify then remove a
bunch of elements after that and then
actually designate the thing that you
want to add. So I know that sounds kind
of difficult but let me show you as as
our example Sally Sarah Stephanie. Let's
say this is the zeroth position. This is
the first position and this is the
second position right? Let's say I want
to add something at the first position
right over
here. So, in order to add something, I
go one and then I go comma zero. And
I'll show you why in a moment. And then
let's say I just wanted to add another s
name. Let's
say s Oh jeez, I already have
Sally. Samantha. Yeah, Samantha. I would
type in uh like this. What I've done is
I've inserted Samantha into the first
place of our array. If I wanted to move
it so that it's after Sarah, I just go
two. If I want to do it so it's after
Stephanie, I go
three. And I know can I add it in
fourth? No, I can't because of the it
takes the length of the string length of
the array and then it uh sticks it in at
the end. So yeah, this is me just
bringing some at the back. Baby, that's
what I'm doing now. I'm bringing her
forwards. I have the power. Uh next up
is uh the second parameter is kind of
interesting. Basically what this does is
it deletes a certain number of entries.
Uh which is kind of kind of neat. You
can delete the number of entries from
the start index onwards. If I want to
delete, let's say three entries or
something. I think I have to refresh
this unfortunately. Sorry. Let's do one.
Yeah. Yeah. Because we can't delete
anything at the third index because
there's nothing left. But
hypothetically, we go 0 0 first. If I
delete everything from the zeroth index
and then I go one out, I'm going to
delete between zero and one, which is
this, right? If I go two, I'll delete
Sarah as well. If I go three, I'll
delete Stephanie. That still allows me
to add Samantha though. Um, sometimes
the NAD editor will sort of bug out like
this if you have an additional comma.
So, just be really careful. But anyway,
this still allows me to add Samantha.
So, the way that I like to think about
this function is this function is just
sort of like an all-in-one. Um, if you
wanted to do two or three things
simultaneously, if you wanted to add an
element at a specific place, then if you
wanted to remove a bunch of elements,
um, and then if you wanted to, I don't
know, like designate a specific element
to add, um, then you'd be able to to do
so here. And the cool thing is this is
this can be an array. So I could add
more Peter uh more people here too. So I
could add like Samantha, Peter, and then
Stacy. And then I could use that to if
you think about it logically um replace
the three elements that I have in here.
So like you know this is what the string
looks like when I concatenate them. This
is them afterwards. So this is just sort
of like a I don't know. It's like a it's
like a three in one if that makes sense.
Do I use this one often? No, I do not.
Uh still pretty cool though. You know,
you could probably impress some people.
The next one I want to cover is called
union. Union is pretty awesome. Um this
is uh like it's the union operator in
logic. And basically if you feed in two
arrays and they have overlapping
elements, it will just ignore the
overlapping elements and then just give
you a unique um total array which only
contains unique elements. So you know
how we have Sarah, Sally, and Stephanie.
Let's say I feed in another one with
Sarah, Sally, and then
Stacy. What we do is we basically add
these two. perform a union on the first
which was Sarah um Sally and then
Stephanie and then the second which is
Sarah Sally and Stacy and we don't
duplicate the Sarah and Sally elements
right these are unique we just add the
single new element that's sort of like a
difference between the two so you can
kind of think of this as similar to the
intersection and the difference
functions this one just doesn't
preferentially add things from the
beginning or the end it just does it
with both equally which is nice function
is unique and I use unique all the time
it displays only the things that are
unique in your um array. So this is a
very quick way to dduplicate data. If I
if you think about, you know, an array
and I have 1 2 3 4 5 and I pass it
through the unique function, I'm only
going to have five remaining. If I go 3
4 5 23, you can see I've added nothing.
But if I go six, now I've added a single
additional element. And it does so by
preserving the placement as well, which
is quite handy. So I use unique all the
time. Very very common for me to use
unique.
Okay, let's now cover um the two
functions that I've been leaving until
the very end here. Actually, three
functions if we count reduce as well.
Map, filter, and reduce. These are
extraordinarily powerful. Um I use map
and filter all the time specifically.
And these, you know, if you figure them
out, will end up being probably your
most used array functions um because
they are just the cardinal v array
functions. So, the first thing that I'm
going to do is I'm going to do map. Now,
if you remember back to um that previous
function that I showed you guys, um we
are now going to be using arrow syntax
again where we have some item and then
what we're doing all the map does is map
just does something to the item. Okay,
so let's hypothetically say I wanted to
append gmail.com to all of these
entries. I could do so very simply just
by
concatenating gmail.com. Let's
dogmail.com like that. So what I've done
is I've taken my item which is I and
then I've said for every item I want you
to perform this function I do concat and
then gmail.com. Pretty sweet, right?
Well, why don't we now make them all um
lowercase as well to lowercase. Then I
double up on the brackets. Um now you
can see that we have basically all of
these formatted as email addresses. So
now I'm kind of mixing and matching
combining functions which is cool. Okay,
so what's really cool about the map is I
mean I just did this with a string,
right? But you can do this with whatever
data type. Like hypothetically, if
instead of JSON array, I fed in 1 2 3
into map. What I could do is I can just
multiply this by two, then I can
instantly change all of these a
proportional amount. If I divide these,
you know, I could do a bunch of cool
stuff with that as
well. U modulo 2 probably like like
there's there's so much that you could
do with a map function, it's crazy. I'm
not even going to like start, but um
just know that this solves like 99.9% of
all array queries. Now, similar to
similarly to the map function, you also
have one called the filter function. If
you've never used the filter function
before, I'm just going to give it a
click because it'll automatically check
this out for me. What the filter
function does is it basically does the
same thing as map in so far that it goes
it goes over every element in your
array, but it allows you to like filter
out elements that don't match the
criteria. So let's say I have a simple
array here 1 2 and three and I filter
out all elements where I is less than
three. Right? So all elements where I is
less than three. Well 1 is less than
three. Two is less than three. Three
logically is not less than three. It is
three. Um so I only have 1 and two.
Okay. If I were to do this with um my
array, I could also filter based off of
string u constraints. So my array, if
you think about it, is Sarah, Sally, and
Stephanie. What if I was only interested
in returning um entries that had a
length of less than six? Sally and Sarah
more than six, Stephanie. So, we're
basically doing the same thing as find,
but we're we're doing it a little bit
differently. We're sort of proceeding
with it a little bit differently. So,
map and filters I mentioned are
fantastic. I use them all the time.
There's one more which employs similar
logic, but you're probably not going to
end up using it anywhere near as much.
It's called reduce. Now, reduce can be
very complicated to understand. Um, so
I'm just going to cover it like really
really briefly. Um, but essentially what
it allows you to do is it allows you to
define your own function and then you
can do stuff to things iteratively. So
let's say I have 1 2 3 4 5. Okay, I'm
reducing. What you do is you have some
accumulator then you have some initial
value and then you have an arrow where
you go accumulator plus initial
value. So what's happening? I think it's
a c I think it's called initial value. I
might have some other term for it. I
might be misunderstanding but basically
you have like a and then you have b and
what you want to return is you want to
return a plus b. So what this does is it
says a is your current element. So a
would be uh for the first pass around be
1 and then b would be the one next to
it. Okay? So 1 + 2. Then it would take
the result of 1 plus 2, which is 3, and
then it would add it to the next thing,
which would be 3 + 3. Then it would take
that result, which would be six, and add
it to the next thing, 6 + 4. Take that
result, which is 10, add it to the next
thing, 10 + 5. What do we get as a
result? We get
15. Now, you can do a number of things
that aren't just mathematical functions
to this. Um, but this is sort of like an
accumul like it like it aggregates
things the further it goes along. So
obviously large arrays, you know, that
you're running some functions on um will
be bigger and bigger and bigger
mathematically. You can do things like
divide too. So I don't know, a divided
by b. It's kind of interesting. A * b
obviously grows. A minus b you're going
to get a negative number, right? Cuz
you're going backwards, but I'll leave
reduce there just because, you know, in
practice, you're probably rarely going
to use it. Okay, that now takes us to
the object suite of functions. So I'm
just going to change the type to object
here. And I'm now going to be extracting
data from this, which is an object that
is nested one level deep with a first
name, a last name, and a height in
centimeters. Apparently, Kof Arladen,
uh, one of my favorite characters from
fantasy, is 186 cm. Wonderful. So, um,
I'm going to go JSON dot object. And I
have access to this. And I'm going to
press dot. And the first thing you're
going to see when you're operating with
an object is you're going to see some
additional fields up at the top. So
basically we'll go in we'll parse this
out and then we have access to the first
name the last name and the height in
centimeters. So these aren't functions
these are parameters but I'm going to
write them down anyway. First name will
equate to both right last name will
equate to Arllin and then height and cm
will equate to 186. Pretty neat huh? So
these aren't functions as I mentioned.
These are just ways to reference um you
know uh values in in set array. Let's
actually get into the functions. There
aren't too many of them so it's going to
be pretty straightforward. The first is
called keys. Keys is pretty
self-explanatory. All we do is we just
get the keys and we pluck it out and
turn it into an array. So in our object
first name, last name and height in
centimeters. These are all the keys. On
the right hand side, both Arland and
186, these are all the values. So if we
want to extract the keys, we use keys.
Similarly, if we wanted to extract the
values, well, you just type values. So
now we're extracting kind of the other
half, right? Both Arland and 186 instead
of first name, last name, height, and
centimeters. In addition to that, um you
can do is empty. This just tells you
whether or not the object is empty. So,
this object clearly not empty. There are
a lot of things there, right? Is not
empty. That's dang right it's not empty.
There's a lot going on in
there. Next up, we have has field. Has
field is pretty self-explanatory.
Basically, we're just looking to see if
there's a field called um whatever. So,
maybe we're feeding in an object. We
just want to check to see if there's a
field called first name. Well, we just
go first name. That's true. But what if
we wanted to check if there was a full
name field? Full name in this case would
be false because there's no key that
corresponds to full name. Realistically,
they probably should have called this
has key and not has field. But what are
you going to do, right? JavaScript.
Okay, great. Next up, we have compact.
Compact just does the same thing uh in
objects as it does to arrays. So,
basically, if we had any empty um values
here, um we could we could uh basically
remove them instantly. I'll show you
guys an example. If I go first name
Nick, then I go um last name, and then I
go empty, the end result of feeding this
in to our compact function, it just
removes this last um element in field
entirely because it's empty. If I put an
X there, you'd see it had populated.
Okay, the next function I want to talk
about is going to be called um keep
fields containing. This is kind of an
interesting one because I don't know,
they they change the the name or the
meaning of fields over and over and over
again. Basically, you see over here how
I have first name, last name, Arlin,
height, and centimeters. Well, what if I
only wanted to extract parts of this
object that have both in it. So, I want
to extract the field name and the value
of the field and value that contain. If
I put that in there, you see that I've
now created a smaller object called
first name. And that's it. I don't
really ever use this in practice, and to
be honest, I don't use most of the
object manipulators in practice, but we
have remove field. Remove field just
allows you to specifically take things
out that you don't want. So maybe we
want to remove the last name. We want to
remove the height in centimeters, right?
We also have remove fields containing.
So this will go and take out fields that
contain a value that we want or don't
want. So in our case, we don't want any
fields containing the value of both. So
we take first name out entirely. And now
it's just last name, height, and
centimeters. And then we have our
obligatory tojson string which just
takes in the object and then it turns it
into a JSON string that we can send to
receive uh basically um through API
call. So you know if you're trying to
send an API call or trying to send data
somewhere and it keeps on telling you
that your JSON is misformatted just try
passing it through to JSON string first.
Um I use it pretty
often. Last thing I'm going to show you
is URL encode. This is pretty
interesting. Um but basically you know
how earlier we were talking about URLs,
right? Let's hypothetically say I have
some database available. Okay. What you
can do with a URL is you can encode what
are called query parameters. Query
parameters look like this. You put a
question mark and then after you put the
name of the variable or the key name and
then the value and if you want to add
more the name of the variable or the key
name and then the value and name of the
variable uh aka the key name and then
the value. So what this allows you to do
is allows you to turn a JSON object
which is sort of like this structured
thing, right? and it allows you to just
instantly encode it as one of these URL
parameters or query parameters. This is
pretty uh useful anytime you want to
send or receive data add it to a website
or something like that because instead
of you having to like manually put all
this stuff out like hypothetically I
could totally go first name equals and
then I could go dollar sign
JSON.object first name, right? Be kind
of similar. Um, but I'd have to do this
sort of structure over and over and over
again, which would just be a massive
pain in the ass, right? Hypothetically,
instead of me doing this,
um, what if I just went, you know, this
is, as you can see, it's just really
unseammly. Um, you know, instead of
doing this, if I just went, uh,
JSON.object URL encode, u, you know,
this is kind of a lot more
interpretable, a lot shorter, a lot
easier. So, I use URL encode pretty
often. Okay, let's cover boolean
functions. And boy, do I have a surprise
for you. If we go
JSON.boolean.bool, I should say, um,
you'll see that there really only two
functions. There's two number and then
there's two string. So two number just
turns a true into a one and then a false
into a zero. In our case, what we have
is we have a true down here. So the
output is going to be a one, right? If
we wanted to instead turn this to a
string, this just turns the bool, which
is uh technically even though this is in
letters like t r ue e, this technically
isn't considered a string. So what this
allows us to do is allows us to take a
bool and then convert it into a string.
So we could do things like, you know, to
uppercase or something. If we were just
to go bool to uppercase, um, as you see,
it doesn't really allow us to because
this isn't like a function that you can
apply to bools. So you got to go to
string first, uh, basically. Okay, the
last thing we're going to be doing is
talking about datetime functions. Now
the first thing we have to do in order
to get a datetime function is we have to
get a we have to get a date time right.
So if you guys remember the way that I
did this in order to get the Luxen date
time it was called was I went uh
01 sorry 3101 2025 then I went to date
time saying that it can't convert it. Uh
why was that? I think my format might
have been different
actually. 01 was it 01? Yeah, sorry. It
was um I think it was 0131. Yeah, deluxe
and datetime. Okay. Anyway, uh okay. So,
once we have something in the
standardized datetime format, um there
is a million in one things that you can
do. All you do is you press period. And
now the standardized datetime format
offers just uh god I don't know 20 or 30
functions. Now, I'm not actually going
to show you every single one of these
because some of these are such uh, you
know, obvious variants of each other,
like you can plus a date, you can
subtract a date, and that sort of thing.
But I am going to cover all the ones
that are important that I find myself
using pretty often. So, the first one's
called format. Format is super valuable.
Basically, it allows you to get
something that is a datetime, okay? Like
this that allows you to format it
however the hell you want. So, you know
how there are millions of datetime
formats out there or millions of date
formats? Some people want it uh year
year slashmon month/ day. Other people
want it month/ year uh day/ year year.
Well, this allows you to do so using
characters that are um designated in
this formatting guide. So, basically you
have tokens like S, tokens like
lowercase U, tokens like Z, tokens like
K, right? And all these correspond to
things like hypothetically if you wanted
to um instantly translate any time into
an extraverbose localized datetime you
could just type fff or sorry ffff and it
would automatically do that. So let me
show you. If I just typed
fff I've now converted this into a
datetime and then I've immediately
formatted it into this super
extraordinarily complicated looking date
which is just like a string
representation. I could remove some
complexity with FF. I could remove even
more with FF. And I could just go FF to
get some other format. Likewise, I
actually create my own format if I
wanted to. So maybe I wanted to go um
year year year. Okay, sorry. Y I meant
to say um because you got to lowercase
Y's. Then month and then date date. And
then let's say I wanted to go hour hour
minute second. Okay, I've taken this
date then I've converted it to a date
time. Then I've formatted it in this
specific structure. As you can see, we
end up with um not only the year, the
day and the month, and the day, we also
end up with like the number of hours,
minutes, and seconds. Now, in this case,
it's 00 0. Why is it 00 0? Well, um I've
been inserting standardized date times
here. What you can actually do is
there's a specific function that grabs
the current date and time called dollar
sign now. So, dollar sign now, if I were
to just remove this, dollar time, dollar
sign now is already in a date time. So
you actually don't need to convert this
to a date time. Um all you would have to
do is you you just format this um as
follows. Year year
um month month day day and then
h mm
ss or maybe hh I think if I want to get
three and then I think you just go a
uh no p it'd say like am or pm or
something like that. Uh, I kind of
forget how to do that though. But
anyway, um, now you know you can format
the exact current time, uh, which is
pretty cool and pretty useful. And I
believe there used to be, and I don't
know if there still are. I think there
was like a time stamp variable or or
something else, but I'll I'll leave that
out um, just for the purposes of this
discussion. Okay, great. So, if I just
go back to my previous um, example,
which just had sort of a simpler look at
a date because we didn't have a bunch of
seconds and stuff like that. If I press
period again, you'll see that now we
also have a few options. We have minus,
we have plus, and then we have diff 2,
and then extract. And these are the most
commonly used datetime functions and
ones that I use basically all the time.
Minus just subtracts a given amount of
time from a date, and it allows you to
designate things just in like natural
language. Well, not natural natural
language, but like using dates, uh,
days, hours, uh, weeks, that sort of
thing. And then plus adds. Let me show
you what this looks like. So, you know
how right now this is like 0000? Like
basically there's no there there's not
even a single second to the day. Well,
what if I wanted to add, you know, 30
then seconds? Well, you'll see we've
just changed this here. 40 seconds, 50
seconds, 60 seconds, 70 seconds, 80
seconds, 90 seconds. Let's say
hypothetically we wanted to add 10 days
to this. Well, now it's February the
10th. How about 10 weeks? Well, now it's
March the 11th. Well, now how about 10
months? Well, now it's November the
30th, right? You could even add years.
Um, this is pretty standard, right? If
you wanted to take this out, you just
subtract instead by using minus. So,
variety of different functions uh
available to you for just doing like
simple date manipulations. Um, a couple
of other ones that I use pretty often.
Uh, there's this one here called diff 2.
Basically, what you do is you feed in
the most commonly used one is now. But
basically, you feed in the starter over
here on the left and then you get the
difference between that and the second
date over here, which in our case, we're
just going dollar sign now. And then we
get the number of days. Hypothetically,
what we could also do if you wanted to
reverse this, right, this is a negative
value. We could go dollar sign now diff
2. Then we could feed in this whole
thing. And then we'd get that it's been
667 days from this, aka I'm about 66%
done. um the current day because this
was counting from like the zeroth
minute, the zeroth second, the zeroth
hour of, you know, January the 31st,
2025. Likewise, we could uh show this
off in weeks. We could do this in
minutes. We could do this in seconds.
Man, it's kind of crazy to me that 960
minutes have already gone by in my day.
What the hell have I been doing? Anyway,
um aside from the existential value,
obviously there's just a lot that you
can you can do and get
done. And then, uh we could also
extract. So we could extract things from
this really easily. Like now is
obviously January the 31st, 2025, right?
What if I wanted to extract the month?
Well, we get the first month of the
year. If I wanted to extract the year,
what if I wanted to extract the day,
right? I can basically go in, I can
extract the current second, man. I can
extract the the minute, right? The
minute of the hour of the day. Um, so I
have I have a lot of options available
to me. Uh, and so this this ends up
being pretty valuable when
uh I don't know, usually when I'm
sending or receiving something or when
I'm performing logic for stuff like
invoice follow-ups or email follow-ups.
Um, using all of these functions just
makes a lot a lot easier to calculate
how long it's been since something has
occurred and and so on and so forth.
Variety of other functions. Um, this one
uh is end of. This allows you to round
up to the end of the month. So if I were
to give you an example, this doesn't
really make sense because I'm at the
end. So, why don't we do start of
instead? Um, start of just does the same
thing. It just rounds um in the opposite
direction. But if I want to round out my
current date to the start of, then
basically what I've done is I've rounded
my date, which was January the 31st, to
the the beginning of the month, which
was the first. So, this is very similar
to the floor function. It's just you're
technically flooring like a date, which
is pretty wild. Um, if I wanted to go
start of the year, it would be the same
thing cuz this is January, right? If I
wanted to go end of year, you can see
that we're now 2025, 12, 31, 23, 59, 59,
9999, so on and so forth. This goes all
the way to the very very end of the
year. I don't remember if you could do
decade. No, you can't do decade. Uh,
could you do millennium? Yeah. Anyway,
lux and datetime is a something for
another time. Lux and daytime is for
another daytime. Uh, if you guys want to
check the myriad cool functions, um,
just Google this and then you'll see a
variety of dot functions similar to what
we've been screwing around with here.
Luxon's extraordinarily powerful, but
obviously some of the syntax and stuff
like that can be a little trickier.
Okay. And then aside from that, there
was just a couple other ones that I used
pretty often. Um, oh yeah, yeah, they're
components. So, you know how earlier we
were extracting things and we were doing
so by saying like month. Well, you can
actually just get like day, you can get
like month, you can get like year. Uh,
and you can you can dotindex it that
way. Um, there's also zone. Um, so, you
know, a lot of the time when you feed in
a datetime object that you get from an
API or something, it will
include stuff like this minus 07. Well,
what you can do is if you just type in
zone, it'll tell you what the name of
that time zone is. uh which can be
really useful you know just when
clarifying stuff contractual documents
can be useful because a lot of services
also require you to feed in a time zone
and a lot of these also just use like
zone codes or there's like a lot more
names to these zones than I understand
so in practice I usually end up using
something like that in order to
reference it and then there's um just
some helper functions like is weekend so
like you know you can find out if the
date is a weekend let's say you're
sending some sort of invoice follow-up
well you can you know do your math and
then you can determine if something is a
weekend and then if it is a weekend, you
can grab the date and then you can add
one to it or two to it and then you can
send it on the Monday instead. You have
a lot of options, I should say, which is
pretty neat with formatting, you know,
date times as things like, you know,
whether it's a weekend or in this case
whether it's a leap year or so on and so
forth. So, yeah, I'm going to leave the
daytime functions there, but definitely
check that out um if you guys want a lot
more power and control over the way that
works. I didn't add daytime functions in
the batch of 106 just cuz these aren't
technically like NADN functions. These
are functions outside a library called
uh Luxen and uh you know that's not like
native to NAND or anything like that but
obviously they're still super powerful
to know so I highly recommend it. Okay,
hopefully by this point you now have a
reasonable understanding of NAD
functions. Again, I know I mentioned
this a few times in the video but you
don't have to memorize all these. You
can grab all of the stuff just straight
from the documentation and the NAND AI
tool is also pretty good at just
figuring out sort of the finer nuances
behind some of these functions. So,
what's more important than knowing the
specific information itself is just
knowing how to find the information if
you need to. And that's really what most
modern developers do. It's not like
we've all memorized every single
function on planet Earth. We're just
capable of going through a list of
functions, reading a little bit of
documentation, and figuring out which
ones apply for which use case. Now,
let's take your NAD knowledge to another
level by transitioning from solely cloud
hosted environments to self-hosted
environments. To make a long story
short, self-hosting just refers to the
idea that you actually take the NAND
source code and then you put it on a
server. Now, you are doing it on the
cloud. Technically, you're putting it on
some sort of cloud server out there,
although you can certainly do it on your
own computer as well. It's just a little
bit of nuance that I don't really think
most people care for these days, but
there are a number of benefits to
self-hosting. The biggest one is cost.
So instead of you spending a fixed
amount per you know thousand operations
or executions or or or workflow node
runs what you can do with a self-hosted
environment is you could basically pay a
monthly rental to the service that hosts
the server. Then you could run as many
executions as you want. So instead of
you spending you know hundreds if not
thousands of dollars to run let's say 1
million executions per month you could
spend maybe 10 or 15 bucks to rent a
server and then um you don't have to
spend any money whatsoever to NAD. you
just take care of all those executions
within the the server rental. That
sounds a little bit more complex to you,
don't worry. I'm going to dive into how
to do all of this stuff in the next few
minutes. It's also really good for data
security and privacy concerns. There's
some niches that you work in,
specifically healthcare, uh, legal, some
financial, where you can't actually send
like customer or patient data up to the
cloud or you can't have it, I don't
know, leave the bounds of your country.
And so in this way what you can do is
you can rent servers that are within
your country or maybe on premises and
then you know run an NAN install there
making sure that you're not leaking any
customer or member or patient data. This
to be honest isn't super important in
practice but there are a few industries
in which this applies and self-hosting
is the primary solution for a lot of
those industries. The first and simplest
way to self-host is using Render. For
those of you that are unfamiliar, they
call themselves the fastest path to
production for a reason. Now, I'm not
affiliated with them, but I'll show you
how you can get up and running with
Render in just a couple of minutes. This
is easily the simplest way to go ahead
and do so. So, first things first, just
create an account over here. Now, I
already have an account, so I'm just
going to put in a fake one here. Fake
email address and the fake password.
We're going to click create account.
They're going to ask you to verify your
email next. Now, since I've already gone
through and done all of the sign up, I
can then go and then sign in. So, I'm
going to sign in with my account. After
you are done verifying your email,
you'll be taken to a screen that looks
like this. It'll say deploy a web
service, static site, Postgres database,
or explore all service types. Now,
unlike a lot of the other videos here,
I'm actually signed up to the service.
I'm actually going to be paying when I
need to. But I want to let you guys know
that like, you know, the these videos
tend to be invalidated pretty quickly
because all of the platforms that we are
signing up for self-hosting on, they all
tend to have different UIs and UXs and
they change the way that their
dashboards look and stuff. So instead of
paying attention to the very specific
buttons I'm clicking and stuff like
that, just try to understand what I'm
doing more generally. So what you're
going to want to do is you're going to
want to find an area in the page that
says deploy a web service and then go
down to where it says existing image.
What you're going to need to do is
you're just going to paste this in uh
verbatim. So nadn has a deployment
method called a docker. Docker is just a
very simple and easy way to grab like an
image of the nadn install off of the
internet. So, if you just Google, you
know, nadn docker like I'm doing here,
you'll get a page that looks something
like this on the docker hub. And if you
just scroll down, you'll find a URL that
looks something like this.
Docker.n.io/nadn.io/nadn. This is just
what you copy. Then you go back to
render and just paste it in where it
says image URL up here. And then you
click connect. I'm going to leave
everything else as blank. And I'm going
to click on free for hobby projects. In
reality, what you're probably going to
want to do is you're going to want to
launch a starter uh standard or pro plan
depending on your usage. If you are
doing thousands of requests a minute,
pro is probably uh sufficient for you.
If you're just getting up and running
and maybe have like two or three clients
or two or three um you know, systems
that you're you're maintaining that send
workflows every few minutes, starter
sufficient for you. If you do free, just
note that they'll automatically spin
down the service. This can be kind of a
pain in the butt, but I'll just leave it
at that. Once you're done, it's going to
go through. It's actually going to spin
up the Docker image and you're going to
set up your server. So, let me cut in a
second. By the way, it was on this
website that I first found what NN
actually means. Uh, it was written by
the creator himself and he says that it
means nodemation and it is pronounced as
N8N. Apparently, the reason why was he
just didn't really like typing a ton of
characters. So, he said Nad, nodemation.
Good enough. Okay. And then after a
couple minutes, you're going to get a
message that looks something like this
with editor being accessible on this
local host. All you need to do is go up
here to the link, give it a click, and
then you'll have the ability to set up
your owner account. So that's what I'm
going to do
here. And once I'm done, going to click
next. This will then send a verification
email using my server actually, which is
interesting. Do some fun little
onboarding. Heard about y'all from
Google. Then we actually have the
ability um and this may not necessarily
be the case when you guys are watching,
but as of the time of this recording, we
have the ability to get a bunch of paid
features for free with a license key. So
I've already done this on a bunch of
other ones. I'm going to skip it, but
yeah, now naden is here. We could start
any workflow we want from scratch. This
is running entirely in our own server.
You'll see that because it's a free
server, it's going to be a little bit
slower than usual. Um but all hot keys,
everything you could possibly want
works. And because you're using a Docker
image, it's going to be up to date. So
this is by far the simplest and easiest
way to get up and running with this. I
should note this isn't the only way to
set up Naden on render and we've also
glossed over a fair number of like the
configuration options that you have. If
you want to check out some of those
configuration options, feel free to
check um the Nad Docker page, there are
variety that allow you to like switch
the database that you're using by
modifying environment variables and
changing basically a bunch of things
related to encrypting and and so on and
so forth. If you also look up the NAN
community environment variables and just
pump that into Google, you'll find a
bunch of different settings that people
use to optimize their NAND installs. Um,
but that's just beyond the course of
this video. The second simplest way to
set up NADN in a self-hosted environment
is using Railway. Now, for those of you
that don't know, Railway is very similar
to Render in that it allows you to very
quickly and easily spin up servers and
spin up databases for those servers. But
our signup here is going to be a little
bit different to what we were doing
before. We're actually going to have to
continue with GitHub. For those of you
that are unaware, GitHub is a way to
host your code or repositories that
you've worked on. Uh, make a long story
short, all you need to do to make sure
that this method works is spin up a
GitHub profile. on. I believe you have
to add some authentication. So,
github.com. Let me just open this in an
incognito tab. There you guys can see
what it'll look like when you do not
have an account. Then click sign up over
here. Add your credentials as necessary
in order to get that account up and
running. Then all you have to do is go
back and authorize your rail railway
app. This will give you $5 in free trial
credits as of the time of this
recording. And now we have an account
here that I just have to accept a bunch
of terms for. Then move on to deploy a
template. The one you're going to want
to click is n with workers. It's
currently the most popular one um on the
platform. Then just type in deploy. And
basically what's going on now is we're
using our $5 in free trial credit to
spin up an NN instance with workers
which are just a little addition and I
believe it's a postcre database with
Reus Reddus. I don't really know how you
pronounce that. But the specifics of the
implementation aren't super under aren't
necessary to know or understand until
you actually get up and running with NN.
So the purpose of this is just to make
sure that you you have an NN self-hosted
instance. We can actually access it
using um a public URL. So let's queue up
some Jeopardy music and let's see how
things go. At a certain point, you'll
get a page that looks something like
this. All of these will turn green. This
is the actual deployment process and
it'll say it's applying a bunch of
changes. You'll get updates in the right
hand column here that show you that
various deployments were done. So in my
case, it started with Reus, then it went
to Postgres, and it's kind of working
its way backwards over to the primary
and add an instance before finishing off
with the worker. Eventually, all of
these nodes will have green little check
marks associated with them. And all I
have to do is go back to primary, then
give this URL a click. It'll open up
your NAD instance, same as we had
before, and I can go through and I can
add all of the information that I want.
And because it's a new instance,
obviously, it's asking me to go through
the onboarding again. And so this is
going to happen every time that you set
up a new instance. It's going to offer
to give me paid features for free
forever. Um, and then voila, you know,
we're basically good to go. Again, we
have our NAND instance up and running.
The third simplest way to get NAN up and
running in a self-hosted environment is
using Digital Ocean. They have a
one-click NAN install template. Very
simple, easy, and straightforward. You
just type in Digital Ocean into Google,
and this will be one of the first hits.
I'm going to sign up to an account here
from scratch. Show you guys what it
looks like. So, just pumping in my email
address and my password. I like Digital
Ocean's design. Very
nice. It's now going to do some bot
verification just to make sure that I'm
a real human
being. And once we are in Digital Ocean,
we're going to have to go through our
confirmation
sequence. And we have some onboarding
that I'm very quickly going to get up
and
running. And then once we're here, you
do have to enter in some payment
details. So, in my case, I'm going to
enter some payment details just to
secure the account. I'm going to do that
offscreen, of course. Okay, great. And
now we are registered in Digital Ocean.
And in order to get all this stuff up
and running, it's very, very easy. All
I'm going to want to do is go over to
the Digital Ocean um I believe it's
called their marketplace or their store.
So, go back over
here. Let me go. I think it's
marketplace. There we go. And what we
want to do is we want to click on or
search for
N8N. be a one-click install. All we're
going to do is create an NN droplet.
It's now going to connect back to our
account. We can select the specific
server area we want. Um, just select
whatever is closest to you. It should
automatically do this. And then it
should automatically select an Ubuntu
version. In my case, it's 22.04 on the
marketplace. I'm just going to use the
basic plan. Um, it's going to try and
like get you up to the the peak. Um, but
I'm just going to go down to regular.
And then I'm going to go down to six
bucks a month or 9 cents an
hour. Actually, 9 cents an hour, I
should
say. Now, you're going to have to create
a root password. So, I'm going to do
this
here. Looks like it needs to be a little
bit
longer. H. Uh, one uppercase letter. O
man, this is
tough. Oh jeez. Uh, why don't we just
go
to Okay, that's rough. So, I'm totally
going to forget that. So,
y three. That sounds good. Paste that
puppy in there. I'm going to store it
very securely on YouTube where everybody
could see it. And then we're going toh
create the
droplet. Now, this is going to do the
whole deploy procedure similar to like
how we, you know, what we've seen
before. very same idea. It's just going
to obiscate or obscure some of that data
from Digital Ocean. I find it's just a
little bit less I don't know, they put
that stuff a little less front and
center. Um it's also an older platform
versus something like Railway or Render,
which is focused a lot more on uh
obviously, you know, user experience and
being modern and stuff like that. So,
we're going to give it a few minutes and
let it finish. Okay. And then your
droplet should be up and running. The
issue in Digital Ocean and the reason
why this is like third instead of first
is because you can't just access it via
the IPv4, the IP address. Paste it in,
you'll have some some issue. It will
refuse to connect. So, we have to do
instead is you have to actually add this
to a domain um using DNS. What I'll show
you guys how to do here is on my own
leftclick.io. I go to advanced DNS here.
Then add an A record. The host is going
to be NAD. The IP address is going to be
this. And I'm just going to try and do
this as quickly as possible. So click 1
minute. What this is going to do is it's
going to provide me a publicly
accessible URL at
nadn my domain
name.ai that routes to this address
here. So if you don't have this um
you're going to have an error every time
you try and access the IP the IPv4 which
is the IP address. So I'm going to give
it a minute and then I'm going to access
n.click.ai. After that all we need to do
is go to console here. Give that a
click. It'll open up this window, which
looks pretty scary, make you feel like a
computer hacker. All you have to do is
press enter, enter in the domain name.
Enter in whatever the email address you
want to use for their encryption
protocol is, and then um I'm just going
to not set up a time zone. It's actually
going to go through and run some
additional configuration options for us.
So, here it is. It's now building this
out. Once you're done, it'll say
installation complete. Access your new
edit end server in a browser to continue
at this address. So, I'm going to copy
that
over. Go back here. Open up a new tab.
And as you can see, we now have the
owner account screen. Same as we had
before. We can set it up. It's going to
ask us some onboarding
info.
And voila, you can now go in and then,
you know, muck around in our canvas.
Again, the fourth way to set up Naden in
a self-hosted environment is using
Heroku. Now, if you just Google Heroku,
spelled H E R O K U, you'll get to a
website like this. Heroku is definitely
a lot older of a platform. You can see
they have some updates that are coming.
So, maybe that has changed as of the
time of this recording, but we will type
in N Heroku. What you want is you want
this GitHub repo here or a GitHub repo
that looks something like it. Now,
GitHub actually has a native deploy to
Heroku button. So, what you can actually
do is you just click this button and
then it'll deploy it to Heroku. They've
done some updates over the course of the
last 3 months. I should note that every
time we're doing this, we're getting
slightly different versions of NAND and
stuff, but you click on that button,
you'll then be taken to Heroku where you
can log in to an account, which I have
yet to do. So, I'm actually sign up to
an
account. That's what I'm doing here. Uh,
no company. So, enter your email
again. And I am in the United States.
Let's say
Delaware. Now, creating my account. So,
we're going to check my email like I did
a moment ago. Okay, now we have to add a
bunch more info. Um, and it looks like
you have to make your password super
long. Okay, now we have to enter some uh
two-factor
authentication. I don't really know what
I want to do here. Um, one time
authenticator. Yeah, that's probably
what I'm going to do. I then have to go
and download an app called Authenticator
from the um Google Play Store or the
Apple Store. The way that this works is
it'll basically just generate a code
based off of the current date and time
multiplied by some secret key thing that
Heroku has installed. Then what it'll
allow you to do is you're actually going
to be able to scan it using something
that looks just like this. And basically
you put in your little QR code in that
in that center area here, which is what
I'm
doing. And it's just given me a
verification code that I can now pump
in, which will be
this. There are multiple different
authenticator apps. You could use
whichever one floats your boat. I like
using the Google authenticator one. Just
simpler and easier for
me. Okay, now we have some more
onboarding questions just to go
through when this puppy finally loads.
That is, am I doiciled in Italy? No.
Awesome. Okay, great. So now once we're
signed in, we can go back to that N8
Heroku GitHub install. Click deploy to
Heroku and it'll actually just do that
oneclick deploy for us.
going to call this nadnick common
runtime and I'm going to dismiss this.
And then the only things that we have to
do is are we have to change the
encryption key. So we have to change it
to whatever the heck we want. I'm going
to do
um I don't know Nick is super awesome
and jacked. All
true. Um and then the app name is going
to be the Heroku application name which
is naden Nick. So naden-nick. Cool. and
we click deploy.
Beautiful. As this is a one-click
deploy, all of the configuration
settings are just up on their own. So,
as you can see, there's some config
variables here. These are the same
things the environment variables and
render um and then railway that we saw
earlier. But I'm just going to let it
play and we'll see what happens. Great.
You're going to get a bunch of green
check marks as per usual. And then we're
just going to go view. Now, because we
don't have um like HTTPS installed
basically and Heroku, which is a little
bit behind on this stuff, you're
probably going to get a dangerous site.
What you're going to want to do is
you're going to want to go visit this
unsafe site down here. It'll actually
take you to the page. And as you can
see, there's no real difference in the
uh that's okay. There's no real
difference in um any of the the safety
here. Um it's just like it's your own
website. They're just lacking the
protocol that we'd be interested
in. So yeah. Um voila. We are now on our
website. We're going to go software
business owner, myself, um less than 20
people, and then Google as per usual.
And we got some paid features. And then
voila, we can now start from scratch all
over again with our naden install
self-host number four. The next way to
selfhost naden is actually just do it on
your own computer using Docker. Uh you
can do so on like your laptop or maybe
you have some server rack or something
like that. I don't necessarily recommend
this unless you know what you are doing,
but I'm putting it in here just for
completeness sake. What you're going to
want to do is just head over to
docker.com. It'll allow you to download
the Docker desktop version. Now I have
an Apple Silicon Mac, so I'm going to
give this a click.
This is then going to go through the
download process. Once I'm done with
that, I have my docker.d image. Again,
this is going to be different if you're
running a um I don't know, like a Mac or
a PC or something. Make sure to download
the right one for your version. In my
case, I'm copying this over to the
applications folder, which takes its
sweet ass time. Then after that, you can
just search for Docker, whatever way
that you are currently interacting with
your FileFinder. That's how I do
mine. It'll verify the package. Yes, I
want to open the package. That is why I
doubleclicked it. And then uh you can
accept and then use these advanced
settings. My case, I need to enter my
password to do so. Okay, great. So, um
you can sign in, you know, through go
through the whole rigomeroll if you want
to like creating an account and stuff.
I'm just going to skip all this. And
what you want is up up here where it
says search, you're just going on paste
in not that um just look for NAD. So
naden io/naden is right over here. So
what you're going to want to do is
you're going to want to click pull.
That'll go through setting this up on
your own computer basically. And once
you've pulled it, you're going to want
to run it. Now I should note that you
can do this through terminal as well.
You don't need to necessarily do this
just through like the Docker desktop.
Docker desktop's just a much easier way
of getting up and running with this. And
then you're actually going to want to
instantiate this by clicking run. And
when you do so, it'll ask you for some
optional settings. I'm going to do 5678
right over here. Volumes, host path,
environment variables. I'm just going to
leave that as is. And I'll just do
n-nick. Going to give that a run. And
you'll see that, you know, my computer's
a lot faster than a lot of the other
ones we've been using. So, it's already
done with the deploy. If you click 5678,
you'll now be at localhost 5678. Which
is again my own server. And now I'm
actually running n directly on my
computer. So, because I have way more
server resources than, you know, most of
these ones that I could rent out
realistically, I bought like one of the
swankier MacBooks. Um, you know,
everything here is going to run way, way
faster than, you know, if I were to do
so using some sort of cloud instance.
You also need to keep in mind I'm not um
I don't have to send and receive data.
It's actually just all locally here. I
could see this making sense for people
that want to play around with like
higherend applications. Just keep in
mind that this does complicate the
process quite a bit because now, you
know, your web hook urls are all local.
Now, if you want to um find a way to
expose, right, if I go back here, if I
type web web hook, but you'll see that
we can't currently access this. So, if
you want to, I'm actually going to go
back to my docker container. I'll stop
it. If I click delete here, so we're
going to want to find the nio this one.
Uh we can pull it if we want, but in my
case, I'm going to click run. What I
want is I want to set the web hook URL
to this. And then the host port I'm just
going to leave at 5678. We'll call this
NAN-IK again. So now when I run this
after it uh gets up and running I'll
have access to my local host setup
again. So let me just go through the
rigomearroll of the
signup. And now if
I I need to find a way to automate this
just given how many times I'm signing up
to all these. No thank you. Now if I
start from scratch and I add a web hook
URL, what you'll see here is it
automatically puts in um this address.
Now this still isn't enough to make it
accessible. But what we need to do is we
need to find a way to pass in requests
from
naden-nick.leclick.ai to our local NAD
instance. And that specific thing is
beyond the purpose of this tutorial.
Essentially, what you're going to have
to do is you're going to have to set up
ngx, which is uh basically an HTTP web
server that makes it so that when you
send a request over to that address, um
it'll automatically forward it over to
your local host on your machine. But
there's a ton of great documentation
written on all this stuff on NAD. Um,
feel free to check out configuration
environment variables and then if you
just type nadnx right over here, it'll
show you guys uh well there variety of
like answers direct from the founder of
nadn himself um that walk you guys
through what that process looks like.
The last way I'm going to show you on
how to set up nad in a self-hosted
environment easily and quickly is using
Hostinger. For those of you that are
unfamiliar, Hostinger is very similar to
the other tools that I mentioned here.
Um they just kind of hold your hand
through the process a little bit more.
So, if you just type in NAND and then
Hostinger up here, it'll take you to
this page. There's a one-click VPS
template, which will get you up and
running quickly. Um, these are the
prices on a 24-month term, but when you
click on it, you'll actually be able to
select a uh a smaller term if you want.
So, period 24 months. Let's go down to 1
month here. I'm going to click on
continue. It's obviously then going to
ask me to create an account and do all
my pricing information and stuff, but
let's do this one. Okay, good to go.
We're now going to click get started.
That's going to take us to our H panel.
H panel is just like the hosting or
panel. And we have a guided setup here.
I'm going to choose just the the default
options because they walk you through it
fair amount. The template that I'm
looking for is NAN. So that's the one
that you're going to want to do. It will
launch um it will ask you to set up some
malware scanning BS. I never do that.
And then you do have to set up a root
password of some kind. It'll be the same
sort of idea as before. That looks
pretty good to me. Oh, 12 to 50
characters. Can I just double this up?
Yes, I can. We have the VPS host name.
We had an SSH key, which I don't really
need. It's going to save all this stuff.
All this looks good to me. I'm going to
click finish setup, and it's going to
run through the process now of setting
up my VPS. After that, you'll get a
message saying the VPS is ready. We'll
click manage VPS here. Um, it's going to
obviously ask us some fun stuff. Thank
you for the onboarding. Then, we have to
do is head to panel access. Click on the
login URL and this will take us to our
lovely hopefully familiar at this point
um NAN signup
page and then from there you can proceed
through the onboarding as I've done five
times already. Click get started skip
the paid features trial and then you are
now good to go. We are in the canvas.
Perfect. So now you not only know how to
put together workflows in Naden and
drive real business value but you know
how to self-host. we've actually leveled
up on the deployment side of things,
which is historically very difficult to
do. What I'd like to do next is I'd like
us to take a step back, zoom out a bit,
and then look at naden not isolation
anymore, but as one of many tools that
you could choose. And particularly what
I'm going to do in this video is compare
naden to make.com. These are two sort of
competing noode platforms, and I know we
haven't talked too much about them up
until now, but I think it's important
for you to understand the merits because
some organizations are going to want one
solution, some organizations are going
to want another. And especially if
you're doing any sort of consulting,
you're going to want to know enough of a
difference between the two platforms to
be able to make strong educated
decisions. Yeah, let's start with module
availability. I've also included a
winner here. So I think that the winner
in module availability is make if we go
back to NAND here and then I click on
this plus arrow on the right hand side
and I type action in an app and I scroll
through. Don't get me wrong, there are
lots of platforms but I don't know in
total maybe a couple hundred, right?
These are all the platforms that NN is
natively um connected to. Whereas, if we
go back over here to make, we click on
this plus button, scroll through, I
mean, that's probably to where NAN was.
So, I don't have a numeric way of
figuring this out, but I'd say make.com
is probably at least 15 to 20, maybe 25
times as many platforms. And that's not
taking into account community platforms
and stuff either, although I don't
really know if that's fair considering
that NN probably has some community
functionality as well. But yeah, I guess
the point that I'm making is since
Make.com's been around a little bit
longer if you're just looking for like
direct out of the box connections that
just tend to work, make.com is probably
your your better bet. Um, it's
definitely substantially more
streamlined to get up and running as
opposed to you having to make your own
API calls or that sort of thing. Okay,
the next is JSON and code integration.
So, you know, as I mentioned earlier, if
we click on label general Q&A, we scroll
in a little bit. Message ID, JSON ID.
This is pretty interesting because we
actually have like code in our no code
or low code tool I should say. And the
really cool part about it is naden
actually allows you to use JavaScript
just natively in any of these fields as
long as you um go over here and click
expression. So for instance if I just
like you know I don't know wanted to do
something to this JSON ID. Okay. I
wanted to uh check if it starts with the
number three or something. Uh like I I
can do that. I can I can literally do
that. Um, let me check what this
actually was. This is a one. If I click
one here, you see it just turned to
true. Two, false. One, true. So, I can't
understate how crazy this is to me as
somebody that, you know, kind of like
back in back in the hood, man, like the
make.com hood, things were rough out
there. We didn't have any JavaScript or
anything like that. Uh, we we had to
make do with like built-in make.com
functions. The second that you sprinkle
a little bit of code onto your Note Code
platform, like like basically everything
becomes possible very very quickly and
easily. Um, you know, make doesn't
really want to let you do that because
obviously if you could just like do
something like this with one little, you
know, like a few characters, then how
are they going to make their money,
right? Like obviously it's uh the
simplicity and effectiveness of the no
code automation platform in a way is
directly opposed to their ability to
monetize if it's being built on a per
operations basis. So NAN definitely
wins. There's no comparable feature in
make.com. The only thing that's even
somewhat comparable is they uh there's
this third party service called customjs
and this isn't even like a like makes
company like this is some other company
that like built a way to do this. You
can actually like add some code yourself
in JavaScript but as you see it's
nowhere near as dynamic. You don't get
any feedback. You don't know when the
code was sent or received. Uh you don't
have little tool tip windows that pop
up. It's just nowhere near as as
dynamic. And you actually have to pay
another platform in order to run
JavaScript inside of make which is
hilarious. So, JSON and code
integration, N wins hands down. There's
no, it's not even close. Um, I could
show you, you know, a bunch of other
stuff here. Like, you could literally
make your own JavaScript window. You
could write as much code as you want
here. Um, but I'm not going to cuz I
think it's pretty clear who wins that
one. Okay, the next up is flow control.
N wins flow control. Now, what is flow
control? Essentially, you know, earlier
I was talking about how this is one of
the simpler flows that you could build,
right? This is sort of like in one
direction. It's unidirectional. You
don't have like loop backs and stuff
like that. And it can get pretty
complicated with that stuff, but in
general, it's it's much more powerful in
nuance than anything that make.com could
hope to do. Um, a good example of this
is just this text classifier. As you
see, this Gmail trigger feeds into a
text classifier which natively outputs
like five different if then statements.
Okay, cold outreach, general Q&A,
Gumroad notifications, invoices and
receipts, unknown. It just automatically
does this built-in. If we wanted to do
something similar here in make.com with
a
router, which is the equivalent um
function that kind of splits flows
up, I would have
to go and add a filter for every route.
I have to say, you know, category has to
be equal to um you know, cold
outreach. I have to label it. And then I
have to do that like, you know, six
times or however many times I did.
Um, so, you know, for one, we we just
tend not to have that built-in kind of
filtering or or uh what's the term flow
functionality. On the other hand, um, I
find loops are just a lot better done in
N8. Now, I'm not going to show you an
example of a loop here, but you can
actually just like natively loop things
back into each other in N8. Um, it's
kind of crazy to me just to be able to
do that to drag the output of one
function into the input of another.
There is no native way to do this in
make. Like I can't can of do that. And
the main reason why is they just don't
want to like you know over complicate
the hell out of the process for you. Um
so instead the way that it works is if
your previous module outputs multiple
bundles then all um subsequent modules
will run for the same number of times or
they will run the same number of times
that there are bundles in the previous
module. If I give you guys a very simple
example with a parse JSON module, which
is just a way for me to convert um
JavaScript object notation into
something that's accessible by
make.com. If we go array and then I go
here and
then go
one
to if I were to run this, what would
happen is my first module would run once
because I just outputed an array. I just
converted this into make.com's format.
So an array was um produced with three
elements. I then iterated over this
array which basically just means to turn
an array of elements into three separate
runs. So this is run number one, bundle
one, run number two, bundle two, run
number three, bundle three. Then it ran
this set variable module three times. If
I make um the value of this the
value I run this
again you'll see that I don't really
have like a looping feature but we do
run the same number of times as there
are bundles in the previous section.
What I mean by that is if the input to
this is uh one bundle then the output is
that same bundle but we didn't just
input that one bundle we output three
and then three outputs were made
simultaneously. Operation three has a
value of three. Operation two has a
value of two. Operation one has a value
of one because that is the value that I
extracted from the particular bundle run
um from that parse JSON module at the
beginning. So without really beating a
dead horse at this point, I'm just going
to call it there. But n is is certainly
far far better than make.com in flow
control. Um they have the ability to
filter just like make.com does, but then
also have built-in ifs, loop over items.
They can merge data from two different
data sets. uh they have built-in error
handling. It's
fantastic. Another thing I want to bring
up is testing. If you guys remember
earlier when I was attempting to test
the NA10 flow, all I did was I pinned an
example and then I could actually
manually modify the content of that
example here. Then all I needed to do
was I just ran the subsequent modules or
subsequent nodes rather one by one,
right? And it always just used that same
input. I can't overstate how valuable it
is to have that ability in a noode tool
because the alternative is basically
make.com where if I want to run
something from left to right, I
basically need to make an API call to my
email server every single time I do
that. So there's no caching of data.
There's there's nothing that easy. If
you wanted to build that in, you'd
actually have to manually do that by
using something like a set variable
module, setting it to whatever you want.
Yeah.
And then on all downstream modules
having to reference that set variable
module for your testing and then anytime
that you wanted to switch from staging
to production basically you'd have to
switch back over and over and over and
over again. Um which means you'd have to
go through every module and then change
the email body variable back to uh you
know the text the email text variable
over and over and over again. And that's
really annoying. It's also annoying
because they kind of charge you a little
bit more for it. So not even close and
AD's just much better with testing
authorizing and connecting. Uh, make
wins for sure. Um, I know that I showed
you some pretty simple connection flows
here where all you needed to do is log
into your Gmail, but in reality, Naden's
connection flows are substantially
harder most of the time. Um, if you
wanted to connect, I don't know, like a
Google sheet or
something. Actually, you know what? Now,
you could probably do one click off,
right? Yeah. Okay, I take that back. You
can do one click off here. But
previously, if you wanted to do um I
don't know, something like a Google
Drive, you would have to create a
credential and then you would have to go
and use um you'd basically have to like
do a whole API connection, which is
obviously extraordinarily intimidating
for new users. So like really, you're
going to have to go into the Google
Cloud Console and get the OOTH redirect
URL, the client ID, the client secret,
and you have to read super annoying but
also very intimidating documentation on
how to do this. you know, honestly, you
could screw up and it could take you
forever and you could be totally
dead-ended. Whereas, if you wanted to do
the same thing with make.com, you would
just add a, you know, a Google Drive
module here. And then the connection to
this is literally just again sign in
with Google. It's sort of a one-click
sort of deal. So, very straightforward.
Make.com even despite the fact that they
have like 10 times the built-in modules,
it's just much much better there. So,
make definitely wins uh on that respect.
For web hooks and mail hooks, u make
wins as well. It's extraordinarily
simple. And this isn't going to make
sense unless you have like a um no code
background, but it is extraordinarily
simple to set up a custom basically
event handler in make.com. All you do is
you click add, you make new web hook.
Let's just do YouTube example. I've had
to start writing YouTube example cuz I
went through all of my connections a
little while ago and there were like 8
million that were just ASDF. I'm just
going to say YouTube example and 8N
versus make web hooks. They just give
you an address and you can just send a
request to this address anytime you want
and then something will automatically
populate here. It's crazy if you think
about it. And NAD, you know, they have
an equivalent feature if you go down to
web hook, but I find in general um it's
just it's just a lot clunkier and it's a
lot more annoying to use. The NA web
hooks are substantially more annoying to
deal with. If you do the wrong request
type instead of a get or you do a post
or something like that, they won't just
tell you that you did the wrong request
type. You'll just be stuck here waiting.
uh there's a difference between test
URLs and then production URLs which you
know is important if you're like a
computer programmer or something but the
vast majority of nontechnical folks they
won't remember to change um the test to
the production likewise and then they
ask for some sort of like off usually um
by default so it's a lot more secure
don't get me wrong but if you want to
just get up and running with this stuff
make is is definitely superior another
issue is uh there's no built-in mail
hook feature make basically coined the
term mail hook like a lot of people
expect this a mail hook is just like a
web hook it's just instead of a web hook
it's an email address. So if you send an
email to this address, like if I go back
here and if I were to just make an
email, I could actually like have a flow
set up that, you know, basically like
does something every time you send an
email to this address. Think of the uh
possibilities and opportunities here.
You could basically instantly, you know,
create a system that you CC something
and it does something else. It it it
adds a record to ClickUp. or if you BCC
or something like that, maybe it
automatically starts following a user on
a social media platform. Like the
abilities here for mail integrations
particularly are limitless. So if that's
something that you're looking to do a
lot of, you know, definitely look more
towards make AI features. Uh I hope that
this is self-explanatory, but um NAN
wins hands down. Uh I know I covered the
text classifier here, but the biggest
module and probably the most popular one
is the AI agent module here. As I
mentioned, the really cool part of the
AI agent, if I just exit out of this and
kind of scroll down, is it even has this
inherent chat feature, which is crazy,
but uh there's nothing like this in
make.com. Make's not even close. You
basically have to rebuild the wheel
every time you want to do something like
this. So, uh you know, when a chat
message is received, and you could even
you could chat with the model right
here. It will go and it will call a chat
model of your choosing. So, open AI chat
model. Going to select my
credentials. Uh sure, let's do GPT4
mini. Then it'll also talk to a uh
memory store that you have which stores
five or however many messages you want
from your past conversation history. And
then depending on that you can choose a
tool that you want it to do which is
pretty crazy. So uh I don't know this is
the the simplest API in the whole wide
world. Um I don't know if I'm actually
going to do a tool usage. I'm trying to
like find a very simple example. Maybe
we'll we'll do the Gmail API and then
we're just going to read through
Um, let's not send. Let's
get maybe get many. We're going to
simplify
them. And then now we're going to chat
with our little AI agent. Hi, how's it
going? Our AI agent is already here and
ready to help you. What can you do for
me? It can retrieve information, do
email management, task assistance, and
general advice. Like, that's pretty
crazy. Could you retrieve the most
recent email from
info@leftclick.ai? We're just going to
send it a message, ask it to retrieve
the most recent email from info
leftclick.ai. It's then going to call my
little tool and it's going to take a
while for that tool to obviously consume
and do whatever it is that it needs to
do. But then it goes through and it
finds the tool in my email inbox just
using natural language. And as you can
see, I set that up in like 3 seconds,
right? So it includes a snippet,
includes all the data and all that
stuff. Um, you can make this arbitrarily
complicated. I added a single tool here.
You could add 500. I mean, you probably
shouldn't add 500, but what you can do
is you can add five and then one of the
other ones you can add is another AI
agent which filters some other stuff.
Essentially, what you're doing is you're
you're making this big decision tree,
which is pretty neat. And you can chain
together however many of these things
that you want. Um, it does start to
break down after a certain point. And I
won't say that it's like super business
um capable at the moment, but it's very
clear that this is going to be the
future of the vast majority of
businesses. They're just kind of a
agents that route decisions and do
queries. So yeah, not even close. Nad
wins hands down. If you're looking to
get more involved in AI agents and
that's like kind of the the the next
step you want to take, then NAN's the
one for you. Sharing and collaborating
functionality, Nad also wins on that
front. Um, if I just go over here, uh,
if I wanted to share this flow, which,
you know, it's kind of two parts. So,
let me just delete this Agent. Sorry
buddy, you're not taking my job just
yet. We click share over here. Sorry,
not share. Well, we could we can
collaborate with other people in our um
workspace very easily with that button.
But if we go over here and then we click
um download uh you can basically um very
quickly and easily download like a
blueprint file or a JSON uh which is
similar to um what make.com allows you
to
do. And what this data is is it's
basically like a code representation of
all of the modules in your flow along
with all the connections and like the
positions on the page and all the test
data and stuff like that which is
obviously pretty neat, right?
The benefit to this though is if you
think about it um there there's also the
ability to import from a URL um which is
kind of new. So you can actually import
a workflow from a URL. You can remember
how earlier we said that there were a
bunch of templates. Well this is what's
happening under the background. You can
actually just click any one of these
workflows and instantly just import it
to your um a workspace. You can also
copy the template to your clickboard and
I can just paste this in and it'll
literally just like paste in this huge
Lego block like thing. And as you can
see, you know, you can get arbitrarily
big and complicated with this stuff. I
mean, you know, this flow could be, I
don't know, it could start here or go
all the way down here. There could be 8
million modules involved. Not that I
recommend you build flows that have 8
million modules, but I think you guys
see what I'm saying, um, with this copy
and paste stuff. Make.com's a lot more
annoying, I find, with this. Um, you
have to use this little import blueprint
thing, and they have to choose a file on
your computer. Um, there's nowhere near
as big of a template library available.
Like, there are templates, don't get me
wrong. I just find that the templates
are nowhere near as nuanced or as
valuable and this is coming from
somebody that like actually uses these
to make real money. These are usually
just one or two step flows and like yeah
they're cool and stuff and that's nice
but nowhere near as detailed as like the
thriving developer open source community
that NAN has unfortunately. So your
ability to collaborate is definitely
impacted. Hotkeys NAN definitely crushes
it with hotkeys. Not just um uh like the
the availability of the hotkeys but also
the fact that they like teach you
everything. If you mouse over stuff,
it'll just tell you what hotkey you need
to click in order to have it happen. So,
top right hand corner here, I'm mousing
over this plus button. It says, "Hey
man, quit clicking this button. Next
time, just press tab instead." Right?
Variety of other examples of this, but
yeah, they lend themselves to this
little text interface quite a bit, which
I like. And uh you know, there aren't
very many hotkeys in make.com at all if
I'm being honest, aside from just like
the built-in ones in your browser. Like,
you know, you can tab through fields for
sure, but really like that's it. I could
just tab through fields. Is there really
nothing else? If I wanted to um copy
something, the
copy, paste, you know, cut. I mean, like
these are all things that are obviously
native to my um native to my computer,
not really built into make.com. And I
consider it such a shame because I think
make.com could be so much more easy to
use with some hotkeys, but they are
really just targeting that total noob
demographic, I would say. Um note-taking
and documentation, naden wins for sure.
Um if I wanted to document a flow in
make.com for this, I would have to click
on this notes feature. I'd have to right
click on this, go add a note, and I'd
say, you know, note about
XYZ, then click exit out of this. I'
right click this, add a note, note about
ABC. Not only is this just not very
intuitive, like the only way to see my
notes is I have to physically go down
here to notes and then give it a click
and then and only then will I see it.
Not only is this not very intuitive,
it's just it's very limited with like
what you can do. I mean, sure, you could
make this really long if you wanted to,
I guess, but I don't know. There's like
no there's no formatting. You can only
see it if you click on the button. You
have this little arrow. I guess what I'm
trying to say is NAD just does a much
much better job on notes because
remember that template that I just
copied and pasted a moment ago. If I
copy this again and go back here, like
if I paste this puppy in, just look at
the way that this is documented, right?
You have a variety of different
formatting um options natively accepts
markdown, which is just a text
formatting method. You can drag and drop
these to be visible anywhere you want.
There's so much information basically on
everything that you can you can like
document any flow that you possibly want
uh for you or somebody else in your team
for instance. So that makes it just a
lot easier and clearer to use in
general. Okay, let's do the financial
comparisons and then at the end I'll
talk about which platform I would use if
I were in your shoes right now and I
were kind of at the start line of my
business versus if I were sort of
halfway through. So financial comparison
wise um now I think you know how each
platform works realistically. Let's now
turn to the major topic that is on most
people's minds and is honestly the main
reason why most people choose one
platform or the other. Um, the
financials involved. So, how much money
could you realistically expect to spend
on each platform if you wanted to? What
I'm going to do next is I'm going to
break costs down below so you guys can
make the best decision for you. To keep
things relatively equal across each of
these, I'm going to be using a
hypothetical example. We just need to
run the system that I built 2,500 times
per month or a little under 100 times
per day. So, 2,500 times per month. I
don't know, it's like 80 times a day or
something like that. I'm assuming that,
you know, you get 80 emails a day. That
may seem a little crazy for you, but I
guess if you think about it logically,
if you're running like a big info ad
email or hello ad or something, 80
emails a day, while on the higher end of
the number of emails you might receive,
it's actually not that crazy to
consider. So, we're going to start by
doing a financial breakdown of NAN and
then I'm going to do a financial
breakdown of make.com as well. If I
start with this N8N financial breakdown.
Basically, the way that their pricing
works is, and I I've clicked monthly on
all of these. You can also buy annual
plans, and I think the pricing is a
little bit different, but not by that
much. NAND is absolutely 100% free if
you self-host it. I'm going to cover
that in a second, but I just want to
make sure that everybody here knows
that's like one of the main draws of the
the self-hosting feature. Now, I'm going
to be comparing this on a cloud hosting
to cloud hosting um basis just because
doesn't really make sense to compare
apples to oranges. Let's compare oranges
to oranges to start. If you were to
compare oranges to oranges and then go
cloud um based hosting for both nand and
make.com, here's what it looks like. Um
you will pay $24 a month for 2,500
workflow executions and five active
workflows. What is a workflow execution?
To be clear, a workflow execution is
this. One run of this is a workflow
execution. So that runs 80 times a day.
you're consuming 80 workflow executions
a day. You are allowed five active
workflows. What is an active workflow?
If we go back to personal here, I'm just
going to save this flow and exit out and
go back to the dashboard. Five would be
five systems that are clicked to active.
So 1 2 3 4 5. That is all you would be
able to do for $24, which to be honest,
pretty crappy. The fact that they limit
the number of active workflows you have
on the $24 month plan, that's kind of
crappy. Um, so not very good there
because I mean I can think of a dozen
scenarios where well scenarios is a
funny word. Uh, I can think of a dozen
instances where you could have where you
would need substantially more than five
to do even like some of the more basic
things um in a business. So I really
don't like how they limit the number of
active workflows. It's probably like the
shittiest part of their pricing model to
be honest. But obviously, you know, the
self-hosting comes in handy and anytime
you're over five, that's typically what
people do. So, if we were to run a
scenario 2,500 times, you know,
obviously this would be under the $24 a
month plan because we have one active
workflow. That's how much it would cost.
$24, I should say, per month. Now, let's
chat really quickly about the
self-hosting. If you self-host an N
workflow, you don't pay them a dime.
Your only costs are the server that you
are going to be using to host your NA10
open- source instance. That's it. So,
most of the time in practice, a server
costs like at the beginning and low end
of the range might be 5 to 10 bucks a
month. the higher end of the range, you
might be spending like 30, 40, 50 bucks
a month if you have like a pretty good
server. If you want to spend like a
couple hundred bucks a month or
whatever, you'll have like the best
server ever, but you probably don't
really need to unless you're doing
something mega enterprise. So, what that
means is, you know, you can kind of get
away with five bucks a month and
theoretically on that five bucks a
month, you could like probably scale to
over 100,000 workflow executions. So,
like that's 40 times what you're getting
for €24 a month. You know, there are so
many options like there's render, that's
one uh service, digital ocean, easy
panel. I mean I could throw out like 500
here but yeah you can you can get you
know servers and all these for like 5 to
10 bucks a monthish and then you could
run 100,000 uh workflow executions and
since a workflow execution in nn is very
different from an operation consumption
in make like this is pretty huge right
if the average make scenario has 10
operations or 10 modules and it run it
takes 10 operations every run like
theoretically this is like a million
operations a month for like five bucks a
month so that's what's really attractive
to a lot of people that do make.com uh
and that's one of the reasons why a lot
of people are switching over to
NANN. Now, in terms of scaling, they're
not captured in our example. Um, the key
point in NN is how affordably it scales.
Make.com doesn't really scale very
affordably. A single scenario can
consume many ops, usually between 5 to
25, I want to say. Um, N8N will only
ever count a single workflow on their
cloud offering. Additionally, if you're
doing self-hosted, you can run an
infinite number of workflows for the
same or slightly elevated cost per
month, which is nothing. So, that's
pretty cool. Obviously, um, NAN has, uh,
quite a lot of big deck energy there. If
you could just self-host your make thing
and just never have to pay them, how
great would that be, right? Moving on,
let's do a make.com financial breakdown.
So, as you see here, there are variety
of plans on the monthly side of things.
There's a free plan, there's a core
plan, a pro plan, themes plan,
enterprise plan. I should note that um,
you technically don't have like a free
plan here for the cloud hosting. It's
just the self-hosting. So, technically
like make.com is more accessible um, at
the lower levels. You can get started
for free, right? All right, you don't
actually have to pay a dime, nor do you
have to know any computer programming or
anything. You can actually get up and
running for $0. But generally, if you
want to do anything meaningful in a
business, you're going to need you're
going to need core or up. Um, the good
news is core starts at just $1059, so
10,000 ops a month. Pretty simple. When
I wrote this, I thought that our
scenario would include five modules. I
believe it only ended up including four,
right? Yeah, it only ended up including
four. So, um, this is actually even less
than this. So the logic that I did here
with five was I said, you know, if we
run this 2,500 times a month, we have
five modules which get executed. 5*
2,500 is
12,500. 12,500 would be over the limit
of most built-in $10,000 and ops a month
plans like core for$1059 or pro for 1882
or teams for uh 3412. So you'd have to
upgrade. Um that would then cost $18.82
per month on this plan on 20,000
instead. Um, but you know, because we're
doing this for just uh I don't know,
four time. Technically, this fits under
the core plan for $1059 a month, which
makes a lot more cost- effective than
NNN's cloud hosted offer for this
example. Uh, this does make it less cost
effective than their self-hosted offer
still in most cases because you can
usually get a server for less than this.
Um, and that server would be able to run
like 100 times this, right? Now, the
issue with make.com, I would say pricing
wise, is it just scales really fast. Um,
most scenarios are going to include a
ton more modules than our little example
did with five or four I should say. And
a lot of the time there'll be some sort
of looping functionality where you might
run the scenario once, but you have 50
bundles. So 50 * 5 or four is instantly
200. And if you run that like more than
a few times a day, you basically are
like using your entire month's operation
budget with just one scenario. So that
kind of sucks. Um, yeah, I'm not going
to graph it for you guys, but
essentially it's like more affordable at
the beginning and then it like spikes
way up. And what's interesting, um,
depending on how long you guys have been
in, you know, the no code business for
is this is basically the comparison
between Zapier and Make.com. Um, a few
years ago, Zapier was kind of the one
that was like, you know, scaled way the
hell up. And if you were like a pro and
you wanted to like get better at this
stuff, you'd move over to make. But now
that same determination is kind of being
made between Make and and N. And it
makes sense if you think about it
because the market itself in no code is
getting more sophisticated like I don't
know five or 10 years ago. I mean how
many people were out there developing no
code stuff? Fewer, right? But over the
course of the last 5 years like some of
those people have become really good and
the median ground of the market has
become reasonably good. So if you're
really good or reasonably good, it makes
sense that you'd start going towards
more developer friendly applications,
right? That's just logical. Anyway,
which one should you choose? Drum roll,
please. This is probably what most
people here were waiting for. Nick, what
would you choose if uh you were in my
shoes? Let me tell you, it depends. I'd
pick uh I'd pick one or the other
depending on circumstance. So, as I
mentioned before, almost all no code
platforms are capable of the same
things. If you can do something in make,
you can absolutely do it in NAD. It's
not just a matter of is this possible?
It's a matter of how many steps would be
required in order for me to do this? How
difficult would this be? Right? So, I I
really want to like prove that to you
guys that you can do anything in either
one. And that's why I built that same
system in both. and we had relatively
different approaches for them. Now, a
simple answer to the question is make is
going to be easier for simpler things.
Nad is going to be easier for more
complex and operationally intensive,
more expensive things. So, if you find
yourself doing easier things more often
and if you're not very technically
competent, you know, it's easier for
simple applications. Nad is going to be
better for you if you're operationally
intensive. Congratulations. You guys
have now made it to the end of the NAND
mastery course. You went from somebody
that probably had no idea what NAN was
or how to put together a workflow to
somebody that is now comfortable and
confident enough to do this sort of
thing regularly while also understanding
some of the finer nuances related to
data related to some of the nodes that
most people don't get stuff like the
merge node the split node and then how
to um coral those hundreds of NAD
functions into something that actually
works and hopefully makes money. After
that we covered self-hosting. though you
learned how to actually deploy a real
live instance of nadent directly from
the source code. Then finally we looked
at nad not in isolation but as a
comparison to make do one of the
competing tools right now that a lot of
people are also using. At this point you
are no longer an NAND beginner. You are
an NADN master. You have spent more time
on this tool than most people ever would
believe it or not in just a few hours.
You guys can reference anything in this
video using the bookmarks and using the
chapter headings down below. So don't
feel like now that you've gone through
it, you can never brush up on any of
these skills again. I've tried to make
this as organized a resource as humanly
possible. Now knowledge is not valuable
in isolation. So now that you know all
of this stuff intellectually, it's time
to actually go out there and do
something with it. And this is what I
think the main gap is between people
that understand AI and automation
concepts as builders and then people
concepts as strategic business people.
Now, I'm obviously leaning more towards
the latter. Everything that I teach is
always in a business context, but to be
honest, that's really where no code
shines. It's not really great for hobby
projects. It's more of a thing to
actually drive actionable revenues. So,
if you guys like what you've done so
far, you guys see potential in potent
and maybe wanted to start a business
model doing something like this, then
join my community, Maker School. It is
the simplest, straightest line road map
to go from a total beginner who has
never sold any sort of AI automation in
their life to an experienced business
professional who runs a thriving AI and
automation company. Inside you guys are
going to find a 90day road map that
takes you from a total automation agency
beginner to somebody that has their
first client guaranteed or your money
back. daily accountability and
step-by-step guidance where I will
legitimately check in with you at least
every 24 hours to make sure that you're
on the right path. Copy and paste
outreach and sales templates that are
closing deals right now. A library of
proven naden and make.com workflows and
blueprints that you can copy and paste
immediately. And coaching calls that I
do live with thousands of people where I
answer specific questions that you guys
ask. Plus, you'll see me there every
day. I respond to the bulk of community
posts. I record customized videos for
all of you. And I'm essentially just a
pillar of that community. So, if you
guys are serious about making money for
yourselves rather than just watching
videos on YouTube or a bunch of other
people do that, then this is the sign.
I'm giving you permission to go out
there and try something new. We'd love
to have you. And uh if you do end up
joining, definitely say hi. Would love
to help coach you through the first few
steps of your AI and automation journey.
Thank you for completing this course and
I earnestly hope to see you inside a
maker school and just on my YouTube more
generally.